<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Jura cleri, or, An apology for the rights of the long-despised clergy proving out of antient and modern records that the conferring of revenues, honours, titles, priviledges, and jurisdiction upon ecclesiasticks is consistent with Scripture, agreeable to the purest primitive times, and justified by the vsance and practce of all nations / by Philo-Basileus Philo-Clerus.</title>
            <author>Philo-Basileus Philo-Clerus.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 233 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 49 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34480</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C612</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R23895</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">07918701</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 07918701</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40451</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34480)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40451)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1200:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Jura cleri, or, An apology for the rights of the long-despised clergy proving out of antient and modern records that the conferring of revenues, honours, titles, priviledges, and jurisdiction upon ecclesiasticks is consistent with Scripture, agreeable to the purest primitive times, and justified by the vsance and practce of all nations / by Philo-Basileus Philo-Clerus.</title>
                  <author>Philo-Basileus Philo-Clerus.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 96 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. and L. Lichfield for Tho. Robinson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  History.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  Church of England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40451:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40451:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>JURA CLERI: OR AN APOLOGY For the <hi>Rights</hi> of the long-Deſpiſed CLERGY, Proving Out of Antient, and Modern Records, That the Conferring of <hi>Revenues, Honours, Titles, Priviledges,</hi> and
<hi>Jurisdiction</hi> upon <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticks</hi> is Conſiſtent with Scripture, Agreeable to the Pureſt Primitive Times, and Juſtified by the Vſance, and Practiſe of all Nations.</p>
            <p>By <hi>PHILO-BASILEUS PHILO-CLERUS.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <bibl>Ign. Ep. ad Smyrn.</bibl>
            </q>
            <q>
               <p>Sacerdotum Splendor, &amp; Exiſtimatio haud dubie ad ipflus Religionis gloriam redundat, nec fieri potest, quin Religio illa ſordeat, cujus Miniſtros Populus deſpicit.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Gabr. Sionita.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>OXFORD, Printed by <hi>A.</hi> and <hi>L. LICHFIELD</hi> Printers to the Vniverſity, for <hi>THO. ROBINSON,</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:40451:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:40451:2"/>
            <head>TO THE <hi>SACRED MAJESTY OF</hi> CHARLES II, <hi>By the Grace of God, and his undoubted Right,</hi> King <hi>of</hi> Great Britain, France,
<hi>and</hi> Ireland, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Moſt Dread Soveraign,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>MONGST the <hi>numerous Train of Mercies,</hi> that attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Your Majeſties <hi>Thrice hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py Reſtauration, Reviving</hi> the Hearts of a <hi>drooping Clergy</hi> may deſervedly be reputed none of the meaneſt. For if a true, impartial Eſtimate were taken of all mens Suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, it would be found no Calling whatever drank ſo deeply of the bitter Cup in our unnatural Warres as that, all the Rich Rewards
<pb facs="tcp:40451:3"/>of Learning being withdrawn, Priviledges reverſt, their Lands expoſed to Sale, and Houſes to Dilapida<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. But tis an Obſervation of ſome, that after the moſt bloiſterous Stormes, when the Ark of the Church has been long floating, and ready to ſink, God uſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſends the faireſt Calmes. Near 20 yeares together has the Dignity, and of late the Office of the Miniſtry lain <hi>bleeding,</hi> and twas drawing to its <hi>laſt Gaſp,</hi> if a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racle of Providence had not ſent a
<hi>Soveraign Balm.</hi> And however for the preſent the wounds are a little bound up, yet has it contracted ſo much weakneſs through ill Vſage, that twill ask no ſmall time to reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver its ſtrength, though it meets with never ſo much tendernes &amp; Indulgence from its <hi>Nurſing Father.</hi> Tis re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corded to the Eternal Renown of the great <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> that amongſt all his Imperial Titles he gloried in none more, then being ſtyled, the <hi>Advocate of Gods Church.</hi> Pardon then, <hi>Great Sir,</hi> an holy Preſumption, if ſo incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable a thing as I addreſs my ſelf to one of the Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenteſt Monarchs upon Earth, in behalf of the long op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed Embaſſadours of Chriſt. The <hi>Bounty</hi> and
<hi>Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificence</hi> of your Godly Progenitours, conferred large
<hi>Revenues,</hi> and <hi>Immunities</hi> upon them, which the Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legious hands of ſome late Innovatours ſeaſed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Now is there any thing more becoming the <hi>Royall</hi> Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> the Eldeſt Son of the Church, Defender of the Faith, and Heire of ſuch a
<hi>Father,</hi> then to reſtore God his own. <hi>Tertul.</hi> relates that the Heathens upbraided the Chriſtians with their penurious baſenes in matters of Religion, and how much the Papiſts were ſcandalized at our firſt Reformers for diverting the Churches Patrimony to private Uſes, all the world is too well acquainted. Let this Reproach be rowled
<pb facs="tcp:40451:3"/>away from the Goſpel, and let not Babylon be more liberal to uphold Idolatry, then Zion is to maintain true Religion. The Eyes of all the <hi>Reformed,</hi> and <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh</hi> world are upon you, tis the
<hi>Hope</hi> of the former, and <hi>Fear</hi> of the latter, that under your Protection our Britiſh Church may recover its priſtine Glory. But if your Majeſty expects to have the Church furniſh'd with able accompliſhed perſons, <hi>proportionable</hi> encouraegme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts muſt not be denyed, leaſt the moſt pregnant Wits, and raiſed Parts turn aſide to the more gainfull Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſions of Law, and Phyſick, which Promiſe both am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pler Rewards, and higher Preferments, and are not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with ſo vaſt a charge as the <hi>Study</hi> of a <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine</hi> does neceſſarily require I know the <hi>winning of Soules</hi> is in it ſelf a ſufficient <hi>Motive,</hi> but all that are bred up in the Schools of the Prophets, do not preſently ſhake hands with the world in the heat of their Youth, but muſt have ſome other <hi>Allurements</hi> ſuitable to fleſh and Blood. Wiſdome it ſelf approves this courſe and uſes the ſame Attractives, Riches, and Honour are with me <hi>Prov.</hi> 8. Now ſince your Sacred Majeſty had no hand in firſt retrenching their <hi>Priviledges,</hi> and alienating their
<hi>Revenues,</hi> tis hoped you will not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract the leaſt <hi>Guilt</hi> by Tolerating what may be redreſt. So will you engage the Prayers of the Church, a <hi>ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Guard</hi> then all your Victorious <hi>Armies.</hi> So will your Kingdomes proſper; which otherwiſe muſt never look to be happy, whileſt the Church is miſerable And how powerfull will the United Interceſſions of ſo many Thouſands be, dayly imploring the Throne of Grace, that the yeares moſt Barbarouſly cut off from the Royall
<hi>Father</hi> may be added to the <hi>Son,</hi> that as the Glory of the ſecond Temple went beyond that of the
<pb facs="tcp:40451:4"/>firſt, ſo may the Holyneſs, and Splendour of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored Hierarchy exceed that of former Ages, which is the Soules Deſire of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Majeſties Moſt Faithfully Devoted and Sworn Subject in all Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onate Loyalty Ph. Ph.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:40451:4"/>
            <head>A Preface to the <hi>Ingenuous Reader.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Preſume there are few in our Britiſh Iſrael unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted how deeply the Reputation of our Clergy has been wounded by the Fiery Darts of <hi>Fanatick Spirits,</hi> and ſcoffing Atheiſts. And I wiſh thoſe late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in power could waſh their hands from the guilt of this ſin, which they too much adopted, either by counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nancing, or conniving at, and thereby haſtned their <hi>deſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Ruine.</hi> Twere fond arrogance to hope that my ſmal Mite ſhould much contribute to vindicate their Honour, and wipe off that <hi>black dirt,</hi> wherewith they have been beſmeared: yet could I not forbear paying my due Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects to that Sacred Function, and manifeſting my ſence of their unparalel'd ſufferings. Many Months did I wait, expecting, that ſome learned Pen would have taken this task in hand, but when I ſaw thoſe Eminent Perſons (whoſe Bookes I am not worthy to carry after them) either other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe imployed, or forgetfull of this grand Concernment: rather then ſo good a Cauſe ſhould be betrayed by ſilence, I was perſwaded to conſecrate my weak Endeavours (the product of ſome leaſure Houres) to the Churches Service. I know here are ſundry Paſſages that will not reliſh with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, from whom I muſt expect ſlender thank for my paines, but let the iſſue be what twill I ſhall content my ſelf, with that of an Ancient, <hi>Non tanti eſt unius vita, quanti eſt Dignitas omnium Sacerdotum.</hi> Nay if the loſſe of my poor Fortunes, my Hopes, my Life, could purchaſe my Dear Mothers Tranquillity, and happineſs, I could gladly ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice all, and make it the Birth of my firſt Action. Many a tear have the breaches of our Engliſh Zion coſt me; and all my hearts deſire is, that Sober Perſons would lay aſide petty Animoſities, and for the Churches Peace, on the one hand, not peeviſhly ſcruple innocent Ceremonies, nor on the other rigorouſly obtrude unwarrantable, but unite againſt the
<pb facs="tcp:40451:5"/>
               <hi>Common Enemies, Papiſts</hi> and
<hi>Sectaries,</hi> whoſe impla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable malice equally threatens ruin to the Reformed Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy, the one directly ſtriking at their very Being, the other deſigning the ſame thing, but taking an oblique courſe by undermining their comfortable Subſiſtence, Honours, and Priviledges. This only I muſt diſclaim before all the world, that I have not the leaſt thought in the following Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, to become an Advocate for <hi>Luxury, Pride, Idleneſs, or any thing that is morally diſhoneſt: the ſevere Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation</hi> of which I both hope, and wiſh thoſe in Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity may vigorouſly endeavour.
<hi>Scandalous Loiterers be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no leſſe pernicious then Schiſmaticall Innovatours,</hi> and ſooner may my hand rott off, and my Tongue cleave to the roofe of my mouth, then ever I ſpeak, or write in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of ſuch, or againſt the power of Godlineſs. My Name I have ſtudiouſly ſuppreſt, leaſt the inconſiderableneſs of it ſhould create Prejudices, and injure the truth. But if any be ſo curious as to enquire after it: Let him know that I am one who can ſafely Profeſs, that ever ſince I was able to look into Controverſies, have alwaies reverenced Gray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed Antiquity, and deteſted factious Novelty. Nor had I held my peace formerly, but that I deſpaired my poor Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket could have done any thing to the quenching of ſuch a Fire, when the whole Nation was on a light Flame. This far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther encouragement I have to uſe the more ingenuous Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, as not any way partaking in what is here contended for, nor (as to my particular intereſt) gaining the leaſt by our
<hi>late happy Revolution.</hi> And as farre as I am ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with my own deceitfull heart, I dare no leſſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently avow, that I was not induced to put Pen to Paper, by any <hi>ambitious Hopes,</hi> a private Retirement (which through mercy I injoy) being all I covet: So that my great, my only Aime is, <hi>Piety,</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> the flouriſhing of the Church, and State, which like, <hi>Hippocrates Twins,</hi> have long Mourned, and tis hoped will now Rejoyce together.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40451:5"/>
            <head>THE CLERGIES REVENUES.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>A Prieſthood proved as Antient as the World, continued in all Ages, with an Honourable allowance to the First<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born, and the Levites.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat God in all Ages has had a ſelect number deputed to attend his Publick Worſhip, and Miniſter in Holy things, is a Truth that none can deny, who own the Scripture. For 2000 years, and upwards after the Creation this was intruſted to the Firſt-born, as is evident out of
<hi>Philo, Joſephus, Maimonides,</hi> and other <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Writers, who all unanimouſly acknowledge that the Prieſthood was ever an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to the Primogeniture till the Law given by <hi>Moſes.</hi> It being the confeſſed duty and priviledge of the eldeſt, to take care of Sacrifices, and other Rites then in uſe.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bertram de Rep Jud. c.</hi> 2.
<hi>Grot. in Num.</hi> 19.22.</note> Thus <hi>Adam, Seth,</hi> who taught his children to call upon the name of the Lord, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. And <hi>Enoch</hi> thoſe Ante-Diluvian Patriarchs; and (that Heathen <hi>Janus</hi>)
<hi>Noah</hi> a Preacher of Righteouſneſs 2. <hi>Pet.</hi>
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:40451:6"/>2.5. After the Flood, <hi>Melchiſedeck, Abraham, Jacob,</hi> &amp;c. whileſt the Law of nature laſted.</p>
               <p>Upon the delivery of the Moſaical Law, we find the Firſt-born redeemed and diſcharged from their attendance, God himſelf giving them a <hi>Writ of eaſe,</hi> and deſigning the Children of
<hi>Levi</hi> for their Succeſſors, <hi>Numb.</hi> 3.45. In whoſe hands the manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Eccleſiaſtical Affairs continued, near 2000 years more without any conſiderable interruption, till in the fulneſſe of time by the Incarnation of the Son of God, the Prieſthood of <hi>Aaron</hi> being aboliſhed, our Mediatour of a better Covenant, no leſſe faithful in his houſe then <hi>Moſes, Heb.</hi> 3. left not his Lambs without Shepherds, but appointed Preachers of the Goſpel to take the room of the caſheered
<hi>Levites,</hi> and promiſed his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence with them to the end of the world, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.</p>
               <p>Thus we ſee a Prieſthood clearly deduced, and that God never wanted ſome in a more immediate manner to attend his Worſhip from the day the firſt foundation of the earth was laid. Our next Quaere is what proportion was allotted for the maintenance of theſe three diſtinct Succeſſive Orders. For the firſt-born there is little controverſie; it being granted on all ſides, that their Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges and Honours were great, being appointed Lords over their Brethren,
<note place="margin">Chryſ. de Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerd.</note> a Princely Prerogative, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49.8. and a double portion aſſigned them, the better to ſupport the Dignity of their Degree, and <hi>Function.</hi> See
<hi>Grot.</hi> upon the <hi>Deut.</hi> 21.17.</p>
               <p>We come in the ſecond place to ſurveigh the Levitical In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, and enquire what a liberal allowance God made them. Now the beſt courſe to take an eſtimate of that is by examining the Proportion this Tribe bare to the reſt. You have all the 12. Tribes, that were able to go forth to war, muſtered and polled, <hi>Num.</hi> 1.46. compared with the
3.39. where the <hi>Levites</hi> are num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bred from a moneth old and upwards: yet ſee what a vaſt diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion, the former amounting to 603550, the latter to barely 22000. none excepted. Let us then but make ſome ſmall allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance for thoſe under 20. and above 50. years old, ages excuſed from the war,
<note place="margin">Joſephus.</note> and ſo not reckoned in the firſt ſumme: theſe we cannot rationally imagine to be leſſe than a third part more. So that by this computation, the Levites will not amount to above a fortieth, ſome ſay a fiftieth, or 60<hi rend="sup">th</hi> part of the nation. Their
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40451:6"/>numbers being thus caſt up, let us deſcend to the proportions of their allowance. And here I am perſwaded, that ſome Fanatick Sacrilegious perſons will be ready to blaſpheme, with that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane <hi>Alphonſus,</hi> in a paralel caſe; if they had been the All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighties Councellors, they would have made a more equitable diviſion, then we find recorded, and would have judged a fortieth part more than ſufficient for ſuch Loiterers. But the moſt wiſe God made them anothergets proportion, allowing them 48 Cities,
<note n="*" place="margin">Cunaeus de Rep. Jud.</note> ſome Royal ones, and the faireſt in the Nation, with the adja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Country 2000 Cubits, or a mile about every way; no ſmall matter in that petit tract of Land, hardly exceeding four of our larger Counties. <hi>Hieronym. ad Dardan. Adricom.</hi> Adde to this the tenth of all increaſe of Corn, Cattel, Firſt-fruits, offerings, Vows, Redemptions, amounting to no leſſe than 24 ſeveral dues, as the Learned <hi>Buxtorph</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Synag. Jud.</note> collects out of the Rabbies: and which may juſtly come in as none of the meaneſt advantages, all this brought to their Barns, without any farther trouble, charge or confideration; that Nation ever conſcientiouſly paying their Tithes, and frequently preventing the demand, being perſwaded it was the Hedge of their riches, according to the
<note n="*" place="margin">Drus. Prov.</note> 
                  <hi>Talmudical</hi> Canon. Now put all this together, with many other particulars mentioned in
<hi>Joſephus</hi> and the Rabbies, even <hi>Selden</hi> himſelf (none of the beſt friends the Church ever had)
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Rev. Hiſt. Tith. c.</hi> 2.</note> is forced to grant that this ſmalleſt Tribe had neer three times the annual Revenue of the largeſt among them. If any one deſire to be better ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied about this, let him but read <hi>Philo</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>: out of whom I ſhall ſet down this one remarkable obſervation, that the people were commanded to bring their offerings firſt to the Temple, that the Prieſts might not be upbraided, or bluſh to take their proviſion thence, as not coming from the courteſie of men, but from the bounty of the Lord of all. And he farther adds, that through the populouſneſſe of the Land, the abundance was ſuch. that the pooreſt Prieſt in the 24 Courſes, might juſtly be reputed a wealthy perſon; concluding, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ibid.</p>
               <p>Now this was the maintenance allotted by the moſt prudent of Law-givers, confirmed by an inviolable Decree, as the <hi>Magna Charta</hi> of that Nation, and chalking out to others what method
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40451:7"/>they ſhould uſe in ſuitable Caſes. Nor do we find the great Searcher of Hearts, ſtraitning his hand upon any ſuch
<hi>politick conſiderations,</hi> as that <hi>Riches puff up,</hi> and tis beſt for Religion to keep its ſervants in poverty. Theſe covetuous Axioms are of leſſe ſtanding, and cannot challenge God for their Author.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Equity, Scripture, and the practiſe of the primitive times plead for the Revenues of the Goſpel Ministry, with in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of the Heathen bounty towards their Prieſts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE have ſeen the Firſt-born, and the Leviticall Prieſthood liberally provided for, and can leſſe in reaſon, in equity, be allotted to the Miniſtry of the Goſpel, which the great Apoſtle of the Gentiles proves to be more excellent and glorious, and in point of honour far beyond it,
2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.7, 8, 9. the one being imployed to kill, and ſlay beaſts, the other being Commiſſioned Embaſſadours of Jeſus Chriſt. Tis confeſſedly true then that under the Old Teſtament, God had a peculiar right to the tenth part of every mans eſtate, as a Tribute due to his Soveraignty: and all Laws aſſure us, that what was once legal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly inveſted in a perſon, continues ſo for ever, unleſſe forfeited or reſigned. Now the former cannot be ſuppoſed, and for the latter we find nothing in the New Teſtament, wherein God either di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly or indirectly has quitted or renounced his title, or changed it for another rate. At the firſt expreſſe appointment of Tithes, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16.21. Tis manifeſt the principal end was to maintain Gods publick worſhip, and for the comfortable ſubſiſtence of thoſe that attended it. Admit then there be ſome alteration as to the manner, yet the ſubſtance ſtill remains. And the Apoſtle ſeems <hi>totidem verbis</hi> to confirm it, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi>
9.13.14. They which wait at the Altar are partakers even ſo—in the ſelf ſame manner as it was under the Old Teſtament, <hi>(mutatis mutandis)</hi> ſhall it be continued under the New, tis both Equity, and the divine deſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, <hi>For the proportion was given to the ſervice, not the men.</hi> I know
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:40451:7"/>ſome inſiſt much upon the propheſie of
<hi>Ezekiel, c.</hi> 45.
<note place="margin">Villalpandus.</note> confeſſedly reſpecting Goſpel times, wherein God commands the Land to be divided into three parts, reſerving one for himſelf, his Sanctuary and Prieſts, appointing a ſecond for the Prince, and the remainder to the houſe of
<hi>Iſrael.</hi> And tis an obſervation of <hi>Origen, Hom.</hi> 11. <hi>in Num.</hi> and of S. <hi>Auſtins</hi> in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 146. that if under the Law the tenth was paid, then more muſt be paid under the Goſpel, becauſe our righteouſneſſe muſt exceed the righteouſneſſe of the Scribes and Phariſees, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5.20.</p>
               <p>Tis true we have not ſuch clear proofs of the payment of Tithes in the three firſt Centuries, neceſſity of the times, and frequent Perambulations forcing the Proſeſſors of the Goſpel to neglect their juſt rights. But to draw an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment hence againſt them, is all one, as if a man ſhould diſpute againſt the neceſſity of Circumciſion, and Sacrifices under the Law, becauſe God diſpenſed with them, during the 40 years wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring in the Wilderneſſe, till the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> came to a ſetlement. <hi>Joſh.</hi> 5.5. <hi>Amos</hi> 5.25. Certain it is, the Primitive Chriſtians did not content themſelves with Decimating only, no, their fervent zeal carried them out farther, many times to ſell all their eſtates, and lay them at the Apoſtles feet, <hi>Acts</hi> 4. which 1000 of devout perſons imitated in after Ages, either in their lives conſecrating ſome part of their ſubſtance, or at their deaths bequeathing it as a Legacy.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Tertul. Apologe c.</hi> 39.</note> Nothing more frequent in thoſe ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly times, then theſe <hi>Depoſita Pietatis. Origen Tract.</hi> 31. in S. <hi>Mat.</hi> mentions ſome Eccleſiaſtical Rents and Incomes in his time. And <hi>Cyprian,</hi> when he found his hearers ſomewhat ſlack, and cold in their contributions, upbraids them, That they did not give ſo much as Tithes, <hi>Nunc de Patrimonio nec decimas damus: De <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nit. Eccl. parag.</hi> 23. Is not this ſufficient? <hi>Euſebius</hi> ſpeaks of a Houſe belonging to the Church under <hi>Aurelius A.</hi> 273. which he commanded <hi>Paulus</hi> to ſurrender up. <hi>Eccle. Hiſt. L.</hi> 7. <hi>c.</hi> 30. Nay we read in <hi>Optatus Milevitanus L.</hi> 1. that the Church of <hi>Carthage</hi> had <hi>ornamenta plurima aurea, &amp; argentea.</hi> And if ſcoſſing <hi>Lucian</hi> may be credited, in
<hi>Tra ans</hi> daies, he deſcribes one of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, or Churches, richly guilt, and adorned. <hi>Dialog. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lopatris.</hi> Strange pomp! even whilſt the perſecuting fury laſted. Tis granted, the Pagan Emperours did alwaies ſequeſter ſuch
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:40451:8"/>eſtates as were thus devized. <hi>Euſeb. Eccl. Hiſt. l.</hi> 9. <hi>c.</hi> 8. Hence we find the poſſeſſions of <hi>Lucina,</hi> a rich <hi>Roman</hi> Lady, demiſed to religious uſes, eſcheated by <hi>Maxentius,</hi> and her ſelf baniſhed. <hi>Sabell. Enn.</hi> 7. <hi>L.</hi> 8. And theſe Sequeſtrations laſted till
<hi>Constantine</hi> and <hi>Licinius</hi> revokt that impious decree, commanding all Houſes, Gardens, or whatever goods belonged to the Church, to be reſtored, <hi>Euſeb. Eccle. Hiſt. l.</hi> 10. <hi>c.</hi> 5. which puts it beyond diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, that there were Eccleſiaſtical Revenues before their time, otherwiſe that Edict had been in vain. And ſoon after free leave is given to every man to exerciſe his charity of lands or goods,
<hi>Cod. Theod. L.</hi> 16, without danger of a ſtatute of
<hi>Mort-main.</hi> So that the ſtorm being thus happily blown over, wealth came tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling in upon the Church. <hi>Conſtantines</hi> great
<hi>Largeſſe</hi> is recorded by <hi>Euſebius,</hi> (and with ſome fabulous additions) in the Life of <hi>Silveſter,</hi> by <hi>Damaſus</hi> and <hi>Anaſtaſius. Cedrenus</hi> farther informs us that in the 20 and 26. year of his Empire, he laboured to pul down the Idols with their Temples, and to convert their demeaſnes to the worſhip of the true God. Many of his religious Succeſſors trod in the ſame ſteps, and the world did as twere with an holy emulation contend, who ſhould moſt adorn the Spouſe of Chriſt. Whence tis almoſt incredible to what ſplendor the Church grew in a few years:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>V. Concil. Berytin. de Eccle. Edeſſ. Agrippin. A.</hi> 356. <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. <hi>A.</hi> 375.</note> and this proſperity continued till new tempeſts ariſe, and thoſe barbarous Inundations of the Northern fury over whelmed all.</p>
               <p>Nor was this proper only to the Servants of the true God, but even Pagan Idolaters practiſed the ſame. None amongſt their numerous Deities (whereof <hi>Varro</hi> and <hi>Heſiod</hi> reckon up a parcel of
30000) wanted his Preiſt to ſerve at the Altar, but their great Gods were not content with a few, <hi>Jupiter, Mars,</hi> and <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulus</hi> had ever good ſtore, who lived in great ſtate. <hi>Strabo</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts a thouſand Hierodouliſts belonging to the <hi>Priests</hi> of <hi>Bellona, l.</hi> 12. <hi>Geogr.</hi> Now the very light of nature did dictate this
<hi>equitable rule</hi> to them that thoſe who ſerved at the Altar ſhould be maintained by it.
<note place="margin">Tulli de Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinat. Dioniſt. Halyc.</note> Hence we find
<note n="*" place="margin">Brentius in Levit.</note> vaſt allowances made them, with ſtanding demeanes; and Tithes too, not oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſionall, and to <hi>Hercules</hi> alone, but conſtant, but to all, which cuſtome many conceive they borrowed form the ancient Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>archs,
<note n="*" place="margin">Brentius in Levit.</note> the ſons of
<hi>Noah</hi> ſpreading it among the Nations, the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:40451:8"/>Devil ever Apeing the true Relligion. I ſhall not at preſent en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire after more then the Greeks and Romans, who ſucceſſively ſwaied the world, and for the former of them Harpocration is wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, joyn'd to that of <hi>Callimachus</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.—Then fot the Romans, <hi>Varro, Cato, Plutarch</hi> in <hi>Lucullo, Livy of Gamillus, l.</hi> 5. have invincibly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated it to be their practiſe.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Nat. Hist. L.</hi> 12 <hi>c.</hi> 14.
<hi>&amp;</hi> 19.</note> If any man deſires to ſearch fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, he may find <hi>Pliny</hi> affirming of the <hi>Sabeans,</hi> that it was not lawfull for the Merchants to diſpoſe of their Spices and Perfumes untill the Preiſts had ſet apart the tenths for their God <hi>Sabis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſhall not inſiſt upon that of <hi>Feſtus, Decima quaeque Veteres Diis ſuis offerebant,</hi> becauſe <hi>Scaliger</hi> and
<hi>Selden</hi> except againſt it, though I think without any ground; but conclude this Paragraph with that of <hi>Junius Paral. l.</hi> 3. <hi>c.</hi> 7
<hi>Decimae jure omni poſt hominum me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriam Deo fuerunt ſacrae.</hi> Thus the very <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who had not the law, were yet by nature directed to doe the things of the law. But I have only glanced at this, it being ſo copiouſly handled in others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>Church Revenues long untouched,</hi> C. Martel
<hi>the firſt that invaded them, but ſoon ſeconded by</hi> Henry
<hi>the</hi> Eight <hi>and others, though moſt unhappily.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>For ſome 100 of yeares the Church Demeanes were look'd upon as ſacred, and Tithes an <hi>Eſtate entailed</hi> upon thoſe that at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the Divine ſetvice. And how durſt any earthly power attempt the cutting off that which the King of Kings had ſetled by a perpetuall Act, and never to this day reverſed or null'd. During all the Leviticall Adminiſtration, though we meet with many of the Rulers deſperately wicked, yet ſtill they retained ſo much reverence to Religion, that none arrived to ſuch an height of Impiety in their greateſt exigences, as with a ſacrilegious hand to touch theſe holy things. Under the Goſpel, C. <hi>Martel</hi> is bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:40451:9"/>to be the firſt that led the dance, and taught Chriſtian Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces this crying ſin. The occaſion thus, as tis recorded by <hi>Gaguin l.</hi> 3. <hi>p.</hi> 43. Upon the Inundation of the
<hi>Goths, Vandals</hi> and other barbarous Nations into Chriſtendom, the bowells of the Clergy yearning towards their diſtreſſed Brethren, they were willing in ſuch a juncture to morgage the beſt part of their Revenues to furniſh this famous Warrior with an Army to ſuppreſſe the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barians, upon ſolemn promiſe, and oath of reſtitution (with advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage) when the danger was over. But Sword-men are not eaſily held by ſuch weak obligations: for having once got them into his clutches, and taſted the ſweet of ſo fat a morſel, being drunk with ſucceſſe, he divided them amongſt his Victorious Legions. <hi>Hinc noſtrae lacrymae,</hi> hence the Church may date the original of her ruine. For the gap being opened, there wanted not prophane Spoilers enough to follow the ſteps of this bold leader. Now tis but a ſhort cut from <hi>Callis</hi> to
<hi>Dover;</hi> and this example eaſily wafted over that Straight. Several attempts were made againſt the Clergies wealth, but none took till
<hi>Hen.</hi> 8. who had too much occaſion to quarrel with the Monks and Friars, in whoſe Cells and Cloiſters, the blindneſſe and ſuperſtition that reigned from the ninth to the thirteenth Century, had placed all Devotion: though however Monaſteries were then abuſed, and are now lookt upon with prejudice, yet in the Primitive times they were the
<note n="*" place="margin">Hoſpinian.</note> Seminaries of Learning and Religion; and under this notion are ſo much cryed up by the Antients. Now the King finding many Tithes converted, and appropriated to theſe Houſes (which ſome conceive to be one main cauſe of their downfal) being carried away by the error of the times, and tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported by paſſion and covetouſneſs, never thought of reſtoring them to their proper owners, but politickly concluded the beſt way to ſecure all was to get the whole Temporalties and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venues of Religious Houſes, by Act of Parliament eſcheated to the Crown, which was ſoon hudled up. Next that the Laity might be the more engaged to ſtand by him, and oppoſe <hi>Rome,</hi> he was content they ſhould partake in the ſpoiles, and ſo divided them amongſt his Nobles, with a prodigal hand diſtributing as freely as he received. In this fatall Deſolation, ſome reckon there were ſwallowed up no leſſe than 645. Monaſteries, 96 Colledges.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:40451:9"/>110 Hoſpitals, 2374 Chanteries and Free-Chappels,
<note place="margin">Harpsfield Hiſt. Eccleſ.</note> to which may be added 3800, and odde impropriate Churches, to this day maintained by pitifull Arbitrary Penſions,
<note place="margin">Spelm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. Tithes.</note> though his Sacred Majeſty, as becomes a true Nurſing-Father, has already taken it into his Religious care, to make better proviſion for ſome, and tis hoped will proceed to perfect ſo good a work.</p>
               <p>The great Oracle of our Law, my Lord <hi>Cook,</hi> complaines much of this alienating Abby-Lands, and ſaith twas every good man's wiſh, that their Revenues, and Impropriate Tithes, had been converted rather for the advancement of the Church, to a better maintenance of the labouring, and deſerving miniſtry, Releife of the Poor, and ſuch pious uſes, which would ſtill have retained a Character of their Devotion, that firſt dedicated them, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented the Scandall, and Obloquy thereby brought upon Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. All the world being amazed at ſuch impiety, and the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny glorious Projects urged in Parliament, to colour the Action, which we have recorded,
<hi>Inſt. B.</hi> 4. <hi>p.</hi> 44, coming to juſt nothing, the burthen of the Subject being afterwards rather increaſed, then leſſened. I am none of thoſe that deſire to pry into the ſecrets of the Allmighty, much leſſe to give ſentence with the bold Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts, but tis ſomewhat obſervable that though <hi>Henry</hi> the Eight left an hopefull Progeny behind him, One Sonne, and Two Daughters, <hi>(and if multitude of Wives would have done it, might have had many more)</hi> yet in a few yeares there remained not one of his ſeed to ſit on the Throne of <hi>England.</hi> The righteous God many times viſiting the ſinnes of the Father, upon the Children. And if a curious eye would but run over the Liſt of thoſe Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiers and Grandees, enriched by the ſpoiles of the Church, it will ſoon be diſcerned the bleſſing of the Lord went not with them; many notable Judgments breaking in upon moſt of their Perſons Families, or Eſtates.
<note place="margin">See <hi>Wolſeys Life.</hi>
                  </note> The great Ring-leader <hi>Martels</hi> iſſue laſted not beyond the Third Generation, and Cardinall <hi>Wolſey,</hi> who began with the ſmaller Covents,
<note place="margin">Oration. Stan</note> did not hold up his head long after, but ſoon declined in the Royall Favour, and came to an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy end. <hi>Staniſlaus Socolovius</hi> takes the <hi>Turkes</hi> ſuccesfull In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion of <hi>Hungary,</hi> to be a Judgment upon that Nation,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>L.</hi> 7. <hi>de Bell. Sacro.</hi>
                  </note> for their undervaluing the Clergy, and ſeizing upon their Temporalties. And
<hi>Gul. Tyrius</hi> imputes the diſmall blow given to the Templars
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:40451:10"/>fortunes to have proceeded from their detaining Tithes, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vading the Glebe-Land of the Church. Whoſoever deſires to ſee more of this nature may be furniſh'd at large in
<hi>Bredenbachius de Sacrileg. Vindic. &amp; Paen.</hi> ſo true is that of
<hi>Solomon, It is a ſnare to a man to devour that which is holy,</hi> Prov.
20.25. Let no man then imagine that eſtate will long proſper, which is purchaſed by rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing of God. For <hi>Calvin</hi> himſelf, ſtiles Tithes, Gods proper Right, a <hi>Sacred</hi> and <hi>Royall Tribute,</hi> which he appointed to be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered in his own name, to ſilence murmurings. <hi>Com. in</hi> 27 <hi>Lev. p.</hi> 2. God is the great <hi>Land-Lord</hi> of the world, <hi>the Earth is his,</hi> Pſal. 24.1. <hi>Nine</hi> parts he has Farmed out to the Sons of Men, the <hi>Tenth</hi> he requires as a Reſerved
<hi>Rent,</hi> and Acknowledgment that they hold it of him, appointing heretofore the Firſt-born, then the Levites, and now the Preachers of the Goſpel his Stewards, and Receivers.</p>
               <p>I ſhall not here nicely debate the Tenure of Tithes, many learned perſons plead the <hi>Jus Divinum</hi> of them, and modeſty will allow me to go thus farre that they can ſhew a fairer title to it, then ſundry other things that rigidly put in for it. Tis moſt clear, our Law is point blanck,
<note n="*" place="margin">Cook L'Eveſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que de Winch. Caſe.</note> 
                  <hi>Diſmes ſont choſes ſpirituels, &amp; due de Jure Divino.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But let Goſpel or Law ſay what they will, too many to this day, obſtinately detain the Lords Portion as their juſt Poſſeſſion, given to, or bought by their Sacrilegious Anceſtors, of ſuch, who many fear, will at laſt, hardly juſtifie their Authority in ſelling, and alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nating, or ſecure the Purchaſers. Then <hi>Caveat Emptor,</hi> all Lawes eſteem the detainer of ſtolne Goods, little better then the Theif. Nay ſome plead Preſcription, and think that 100 years quiet Poſſeſſion, is a ſufficient Title, but <hi>Nullum Tempus occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit Regi,</hi> The King of Heaven cannot looſe his Right by time, eſpecially when ſo many of his Meſſengers, have often in their Maſters name put in Exceptions,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Spelm. de non Tem. Eccl. Sclater, Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagne,</hi> &amp;c.</note> and made Demand. Tis a judged Caſe,
<hi>Dominium transferre non poteſt, qui ipſe Dominus non eſt.</hi> Now when things are once <hi>Conſecrated to God, the property is inveſted in him.</hi> And who is ſo bold as to enter the Liſt with the All-mighty? can his heart endure, or his hands be ſtrong in the day that God ſhall plead with him?</p>
               <p>Others comfort themſelves with this, that though a private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:40451:10"/>cannot revoke his gift, yet the Publick Magiſtrate, &amp; the Body of the Nation may doe much. I muſt not be too buſie in ſtating this tickliſh point; yet, methinks, Reaſon ſeemes to ſuggeſt, that when once the Supreme Powers, have by their conſent, ratified ſuch a Donation, as in this caſe it has been done over and over, it may be judged <hi>Tantamount,</hi> and they equally engaged; but as I dare not condemn, ſo I cannot abſolve, unleſſe with the late Earl of
<hi>Pembroke, I</hi> ſhould aſcribe <hi>Omnipotency to a Parliament.</hi> Tis ſufficient to me, that the God of Heaven has enacted a peremp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory Decree, <hi>Ezech.</hi> 48.14. which all that fear him will be ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to tranſgreſſe, <hi>that which is once holy, can no more become alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable,</hi> eſpecially ſince Interpreters generally take this Viſion to concern the daies of the Meſſiah.</p>
               <p>I know there have been many conſcientious perſons, who have trembled to touch theſe hollowed things, and have in
<note n="*" place="margin">Amongſt others that Eminent Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tron of Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, the Lord <hi>Scuda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more</hi> has late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſprivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged, and made ſubject to Tithes, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral of his Worthy Copy</note> tenderneſs reſtored the Churches Patrimony, which their daring Progenitors feaſed upon. The Lord remember them in the Great Day of Account, and increaſe their number, that <hi>Church-Robbing</hi> may not ſtill be the ſin of <hi>England;</hi> which, though an Earthly Tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal may acquit men of, yet there <hi>is a Court of Conſcience, another Impartial Bar,</hi> that all muſt appear before, where the Judge is a Party, <hi>You have robbed me, Mal.</hi> 4. And let not that known Rule be forgotten, <hi>Non remittitur peccatum, niſi Reſtituatur ablatum.</hi> But enough of this, if not too much.</p>
               <p>Lands at <hi>Abby Dore</hi> in <hi>Hereford</hi> ſhiere.
<hi>LLantony</hi> in <hi>Gloceſter ſhiere,</hi> &amp;c. a for others to write after. Nor does there want matter for their Charity. All the Revenues of the
<note n="*" place="margin">Rebuffus de Decim. Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gor Tholoſan.</note> Templars, Hoſpitallers, Knights of St. <hi>John</hi> of
<hi>Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem,</hi> with the whole Order of Ciſtercians, &amp;c. being by Papal Diſpenſation, which ſtill holds, wholly exempted.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:40451:11"/>
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Pretences of Reformation. Objections from Scripture anſwered, Many Inconveniences attending the Clergies Poverty.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I Know the great Pretence, and Cloak for Sacriledge has been, and ſtill is, to reduce Religion to the <hi>Primitive Purity;</hi> but the event moſt commonly, if not ever, has proved it to be no other, then <hi>to bring the Clergy to the Primitive Poverty. Lud. Vives</hi> in his Com. upon S.
<hi>Auſtin, de Civit. D.</hi> tells us, that <hi>Ceres</hi> Prieſts put on a Coat the day of their Initiation, which they never left off till ſuch time, as it was ſo ragged, that it would no longer hang to their backs. And if Spiritual perſons were left to ſome mens allowance, this would be their Portion, and <hi>neceſſity would conſtrain them to faſt, and pray.</hi> Certainly it is a ſhameful blot that will never be wiped off from our Reformers, that inſtead of redreſſing grievances, and removing corruptions in Religion, they have ſtill unhappily fallen to plundering Church Revenues. Thus 'twas in <hi>Germany, Sweden, Denmark,</hi> and I wiſh
<hi>England</hi> could be left out of the Catalogue. I am aſhamed thus to uncover my Mothers nakedneſſe, and that theſe things ſhould be publiſhed in <hi>Askelon;</hi> but they are too notorious, acted in the face of the World. And I ſcarce have heard or read of any Reformation free, except that of <hi>Wittenberg,</hi> who contracted leſſe guilt then their neighbours, imploying moſt of the demoliſhed Abby-Lands, in other publick and Religious uſes. So that I may complain with the Father,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Austin Ep.</hi> 154.</note> 
                  <hi>Non Pietate everterunt Idôla, ſed avaritiâ.</hi> And if it be lawful to ſpeak it, I muſt needs ſay it has been often my fear, that too many were inſtrumental in, and rejoyced at the Extirpation of Popery, for no other reaſon, then that it made way for their Sacriledge, and if danger of looſing their ill gotten goods did not terrifie, they would as little be troubled at its re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn.</p>
               <p>But the thread-bare excuſe for all is, That they were beſtowed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:40451:11"/>in dark times, and to ſuperſtitious ends: ſhould I grant the whole, which I ſhall have more occaſion to ſpeak to in the following Chapter; yet I am half afraid, that the <hi>ignorant Superſtition of our bountifull Anceſtors, will find more favour in the great day of reckon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, then the knowing Sacriledge of their Penurious Poſterity.</hi> I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, 'tis matter of wonder to me, that any enuious eye ſhould repine at the large Revenues of the Church, which the Libera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Magnificence of Princes, and other Benefactors have beſtowed upon it. Did their Purſes pay for it, there might be ſome reaſon for murmuring; but when none are oppreſſed, none injured, many thouſand Tenants gratified by good Leaſes, and the hungry bellies of the poor relieved by the full Tables of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticks, it ſpeaks an unworthy ſordid ſpirit, to deny others Liberty to exerciſe that Charity, which their covetuouſneſſe will not permit. Who will grudg them a plentiful maintenance, that freely receiving, freely give?</p>
               <p>But ſome inſiſt much upon the poverty of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, which they very zealouſly commend as a pattern for Preachers of the Goſpel, exempting all other orders of men, and priviledging them from this ſtrictneſſe. Excellent Doctrine! which allows ſo fair a liberty to the generality of Profeſſors, as not concerned to imitate this grand Exemplar, nor obſerve his rigorous Injuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of leaving all, and following him.</p>
               <p>But may it not as rationally be concluded, if his life reſpected no other then thoſe that immediatly attend his Worſhip, his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts reach no other, that no other ſhall receive benefit by his Death, no other be ſaved by him. Though this conſequence will hardly be granted, which yet undeniably follows from the Premi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes. Indeed we have a Command,
<hi>Luk.</hi> 9. that the Diſciples ſhould poſſeſſe <hi>neither gold, nor ſilver, no mony in their Purſes, not two coats, neither ſhooes.</hi> So that if the Letter muſt be ſtuck to, why are not all Preachers, by vertue of this, injoyned to <hi>go naked, and barefoot.</hi> May we not therefore ſafely believe, that many of theſe Precepts were onely
<hi>Perſonal, and Temporary;</hi> as that, <hi>Go not into</hi> the way of the Gentiles, but to the loſt ſheep of the houſe of Iſrael —
<hi>and ſalute no man</hi>—which all but the <hi>Quaking Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> acknowledge to be no longer binding. If then there be any force in thoſe Allegations, they equally belong to all that
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:40451:12"/>have given up their names to Chriſt; and cannot be reſtrained to the Clergy alone: for if want and poverty were to be their conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued portion, twas madneſs in St. <hi>Paul</hi> to require them to be <hi>lovers of Hoſpitality, Tit.</hi> 1.8. which they can exerciſe only in <hi>good wiſhes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Again, is there no difference between the Apoſtles and us, that their practiſe is ſo much urged? They had ſuch immediate aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, that there was no need of ſtudy for their Preaching, whereby they had leaſure enough to <hi>fiſh, and make Tents</hi> for a livelihood: but Ours are forced to pore upon Books, to meditate, write, and all hardly ſufficient to ſearch out the deep myſteries, which coſt them no pains, the Spirit ſupplying the place of all. Now to make amends for thoſe Extraordinary Qualifications, and abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant meaſure of Spiritual Graces, wherewith they were furniſht above us, it hath pleaſed the <hi>Lord of the Harveſt,</hi> in theſe later daies, to raiſe up Chriſtian Magiſtrates, to aſſiſt and encourage his <hi>Labourers,</hi> and appoint them a more ſetled plentiful allowance.</p>
               <p>Others mutter that <hi>Affluence is a great Temptation,</hi> and expoſes them to Pride and Luxury. For this let experience judge whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther many times <hi>Diogenes</hi> prove not more ſupercilious then <hi>Plato,</hi> there be not as much inſolence under a Freeze-Jerkin, as a Velvet Jippo, a
<hi>Geneva Rocket,</hi> as an <hi>Epiſcopal Caſſock,</hi> Nay there are ſome Scores will be ready to depoſe, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe few years, they ſaw as <hi>little Humility,</hi> and as <hi>much Volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuouſneſſe</hi> in ſome <hi>ordinary Heads of Colledges, and Paſtours of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations,</hi> (caeteris paribus) as ever <hi>was charged upon the late Arch-Biſhop of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>or any that enjoyed the fat See of Wincheſter.</hi> Let not any one miſtake me as a <hi>Patron of idleneſſe, or an Advocate for the Luxury of ſpiritual perſons.</hi> God, and my Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience bear me witneſſe, how much I abominate ſuch a thought; all my fear is, that beggery, and the <hi>ſordid competency,</hi> which ſome men talk of and project, is the readieſt way to uſher in Atheiſm and Prophaneneſſe. For poverty of Preachers brings them into contempt; and when once men begin there, the next ſtep is to deſpiſe
<note n="*" place="margin">Spotswood in Congullus.</note> Religion it ſelf. Inſomuch, that it may confidently be affirmed, there is nothing more diſhonourable to the Goſpel, or diſadvantageous to the happy progreſſe of it, then the low con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of its publiſhers. Perfection is not here to be expected, the holieſt men are ſtill fleſh and blond, and do we not every hour ſee
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:40451:12"/>it before our eyes, how much <hi>want depreſſes the ſpirit, and cools zeal.</hi> A poor Preacher, that has a large Family to maintain, will hardly take the courage to reprove a boſome vice, in his Lordly Patron, and diſſolute Pariſhioners; if he lives upon their Tren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and muſt ſtand to their allowance, many faults muſt be winked at, and a <hi>fair conſtruction put upon foul miſcarriages.</hi> But when able parts, an upright converſation, and ſuitable revenues meet, that a Paſtour can as well give, as receive courteſies, and not depend upon the
<hi>Benevolence</hi> of his people; with what au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority can ſuch a man deliver himſelf: his Doctrine is imbraced as an Oracle, for, (as one notes) tis an errour that will never be beaten out of the pates of the Vulgar, who imagine <hi>wiſdom alwaies to go hand in hand with Riches and Power;</hi> and tis a complaint as old as <hi>Solomon,</hi> that the <hi>poor wiſe man,</hi> with all his wiſdom, is deſpiſed, <hi>Eccl.</hi> 9.15. May it not then juſtly be feared, that poverty of the Clergy will beget a dull and ſtupid irreve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in the minds of ordinary perſons? Majeſtie it ſelf being apt to be ſlighted and trampled upon, when deſtitute of its accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomed ſtate: and our Judges find, theres nothing does ſo much purchaſe them the Cap and Knee of the trembling multitude, as their Robes, Pomp, and Grandeur. Sure I am, tis one of the greateſt ſcandals to the Papiſt, to ſee the Magnificence and Splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of their Prelates, and the meanneſſe, I had almoſt ſaid beg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gary, of ſome of ours. And, though the power of Religion does not conſiſt in theſe externals, yet ſomething muſt be allowed to
<hi>Christian Prudence,</hi> which may well ſuggeſt this ſeaſonable advice to our Governours, to reſtore God his own, who gave <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar</hi> his. <hi>Hieronym. de Cevallos</hi> is my Author, that if a true eſtimate were made of all the Spaniſh Territories, 'twould be found the Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticks poſſeſt near as much, if not more, then the Seculars.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Relat. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niv. L.</hi> 1.
<hi>p.</hi> 4. <hi>Brerewood Enq. Sands Eur. Spec.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Boterus</hi> goes a ſtep farther, who has a conceit, That for <hi>the Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and Wealth this nation bestowed upon the Clergy, God gave them the Indian Mines.</hi> And their vaſt Demeaſnes in <hi>Germany, France, Italy, Poland,</hi> &amp;c. almoſt ſurpaſſe belief. For the Eaſtern Churches, if <hi>Hercules</hi> may be meaſured by his foot, the riches of the ancient Greek Patriarchs, may be conjectured at by one
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cedren. p.</hi> 638 <hi>Ed. Par.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phylact,</hi> who kept a ſtable of 2000 Horſes, with all other things anſwerable, and by the multitude of their
<note n="*" place="margin">Codin Curopalat. de Official. Eccle. Conſtant.</note> Officials, recorded in unqueſtionable Hiſtorians.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:40451:13"/>
               <p>Then for the great plenty and Luſter they formerly lived in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us, we may judge by one Metropolitan <hi>William Warham</hi> A.
1504, when no leſſe a Peer then the Duke of <hi>Buckingham</hi> was his ſteward, and cheife Butler riding before the firſt Meſſe with his white ſtaffe at the Archi-Epiſcopal Inthronization. And the many ſtately Fabricks of Pallaces, Churches, Colledges, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpitals <hi>&amp;c.</hi> built by their purſes, ſtand Eternal Monuments of their Noble Minds, and to upbraid the Ingratitude of Poſterity. For now tis grown the reproach of our Reformed world, that for the moſt part they have taken up the <hi>Niggardly Opinion</hi> of that A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtate Diſciple, who thought all to be waſte that was beſtowed on Chriſt in ſuch a ſort, and would <hi>make the ſtrict Rule of meer neceſſity an adequate proportion for the great Supraviſours of ſouls.</hi> As if the bountifull hand of God which has dealt ſo liberally with all other Degrees, was only ſtraightned towards his own Inheritance. Is it not ſtrang in a Chriſtian Kingdome, to ſee every
<hi>half-witted ſhallow-braind Fellow</hi> of an other profeſſion,
<hi>leap into a conſiderable Eſtate, purchaſe the laſting Inheritance of ſome</hi> 1000, <hi>without the leaſt envy or cenſure; and yet the petty Salary of</hi> 80, <hi>or</hi> 100 <hi>per An. grudged the Nobleſt, and beſt-furniſhed Souls the Earth beares.</hi> Twas the ſaying of a wiſe States-man, <hi>that Scandalous Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance makes Scandalous Miniſters,</hi> and what pityfull Sots many grow by reaſon of ſhort Stipends, becoming obnoxious to the Scoffs and Deriſion of Prophane ones, experience ſadly teſtifies. Aſſuredly then, if a man ſhould make <hi>a Covenant with Hell, &amp; Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract with Satan</hi> to ſupplant the kingdome of Chriſt,
<hi>he could not proceed in a more hopefull method, then to drive his Miniſters to Diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties, and Straights.</hi> I can ſafely profes my ſelf as litle a Freind to <hi>Rome,</hi> as any perſon living, yet can
<hi>I</hi> not but commend this vertue in an Enemy. And I take the Splendour, (I had almoſt ſaid) prodigall Maintenance of their Clergy, to be the greateſt ſupport and Pillar of that long tottering Structure. Now is it not a reproach to a Nation profeſſing the purity of the Coſpel, that the Idolatrous Maſſe-Munger amongſt the Romaniſts, and the Pagan Sacrificers ſhould receive a more ample and honourable allowance then the Faithfull Servants of the true God. Nor need any one dread the Clergies growing too rich if the Revenues were as large againe. Since <hi>Hoſpitality and Charity are two Principall Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:40451:13"/>required at their hands and due from them; theſe will keep <hi>them low enough, and prevent their Purchaſing.</hi> To ſay nothing of the Dilapidations, and deplorable ruines in ſo many late flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Cathedrals, and other ancient Piles, which are ſinking, unleſs ſupported by their Munificence. Nor to mention their chargea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Educaion in the Univerſities, which commonly eates out moſt of their Portions, the expences of Bookes,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Voſſit Biblioth.</hi> Dr. Wilkins
<hi>Preacher.</hi>
                  </note> 600 <hi>Pound being ſoon conſumed in purchaſing an indifferent Library of ſome choice Authors in each kind,</hi> as many have made appear. Nor laſtly to take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of crazy bodyes the Epidemicall Fate of moſt hard Students, whereby they are enforced to more then ordinary charge of Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick, and other neceſſaries. And if their providence has not laid up againſt ſuch a ſtorme, (which conſidering the premiſes, and their ingenuous manner of living cannot rationally be expected) both they and theirs, muſt look to encounter Hunger, Nakedneſs, and ſuch like hardſhips, or (which goes nearer then all the reſt to a generous heart) turn <hi>Profeſt Mendicants. Moſes</hi> made better Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion for his Old Teſtament
<hi>Levites,</hi> when it deſcended as an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance to poſterity, when Age was excuſed, a Diſpenſation be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing given after 50 yeares, the Gray-head taken care of, Widows ſupported, and the Children (unleſs impotent) ever ſucceeding the Parents in the ſame Imployment. But under the Goſpel, <hi>the poor Pittance allotted dyes with the Incumbent, the Function being not confined to one Tribe or Family, but any Perſons duely qualified are gladly admitted, whereby many times the Progeny of ſeverall eminent Worthies in the Church, that thought their Lives not dear for the Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of Jeſus, whoſe Charitable hearts towards the poor Members of Chriſt would not ſuffer them to hoord up, have been expoſed to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>numerable difficulties, the Publick never regarding them, one of the Fouleſt Spots in the Fair Face of our Reformation. And our ſhame full neglect herein, does in a Politicall Senſe much juſtifie that</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of Devills,
<hi>Forbidding the Clergies Marriage.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:40451:14"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Some harſh expreſſions concerning the Clergies Revenues, in the Writings of the Antients, and Modern Reformers, examined.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TIs confeſſed, we meet with many bitter Invectives dropping from the Pens of ſome of the Primitive Fathers about this Subject. But if their words be well weighed by an unbiaſſed Reader, and one place compared with another, it will appear, their heat was not againſt the Revenues of the Church, which in cold blood they ever commend, but the abuſe of them, the Pride, Covetuouſneſſe, and Luxury of the Clergy, which many times are unhappy Conſequents, no neceſſary Effects of Plenty, and good Laws may much, if not wholly reſtrain them. For that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Sentence, which is almoſt worn out, being ſo frequent in the mouth of every Ideot,
<hi>Hodiè venenum infuſum eſt in Eccleſiam,</hi> who knows but it might be a device of the Old Serpent, to nip the tender buds of growing charity in thoſe early times, for Satan was never more concerned to put his wits on work then now, when all things ſmiled upon the Church, whoſe flouriſhing is ever unwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come news to him. At beſt, (if it be not feigned, but a real voice) I take it to be no more then a Divine admonition, or <hi>the Rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of a Devout ſoul breathing out its fears,</hi> what might be the iſſue of ſo ſuddain, ſo great a change. For as it may prejudice the ſight to be brought preſently out of a dark Dungeon, to the bright Rayes of the Sun: or after long Famine, to be admitted to a full Table of delicate Viands may hazard a ſurfeit; ſo danger might well be apprehended, to come immediatly out of the depths of perſecution, and miſery, to a glorious Liberty, and the height of all earthly Attainments. But whatever miſcarriages then enſued, cannot with any colour of reaſon, be pleaded againſt the preſent ſtate of our Britiſh Churches.</p>
               <p>Tis farther acknowledged, that we find no leſſe harſh ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſions in our firſt Reformers, the Hiſtory of the
<hi>Albi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genſes,</hi> the Remains of our own <hi>Wicklif, Huſſe,</hi> &amp;c. againſt the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:40451:14"/>Wealth and Grandeur of the Glergy. But if a man with a diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eye will peruſe the Annals of thoſe times, and conſider the Ignorance, pomp, and ſloth of thoſe that engroſſed all ſpiritual Promotions, <hi>Court-Paraſites, Popes-Baſtards,</hi> (or in the more re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fined Italian Dialect) <hi>Nephews,</hi> Foraigners unacquainted with the Language, and ſo they might have the Fleece regardleſſe what became of the Sheep; when ſuch as theſe devoured all the fat of the Land,
<note place="margin">Mat. Paris paſſim.</note> had the
<hi>faireſt Benefices</hi> aſſigned <hi>for Penſions in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendam;</hi> who can blame <hi>an Holy zeal,</hi> if it <hi>provokt them to a juſt Indignation,</hi> who will not pardon their Paſſion, if it tranſported them beyond the juſt bounds? Thus tis uſual to run from
<hi>one extream to another,</hi> as we ſee ſome of the Fathers, by their
<hi>over-vehement diſputes againſt</hi> Pelagius, Eutyches, &amp;c. make way for the contrary errors: there being no other means to get a crooked ſtick ſtraight, but by bowing it as much the other way; though I hope no wiſe man will plead to have it alwaies kept ſo. Let not therefore any ſuffer themſelves to be deluded, and impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed upon by ſuch Quotations, or the practiſe of ſome good men in thoſe impoveriſht perſecuted ages, which onely can <hi>juſtify and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe</hi> their actings; who ſo they might but <hi>run counter to Rome,</hi> and <hi>undermine the high-fed Abbots, and gorbellied Monks,</hi> cared not how ſlaviſhly they ſtooped to live beggerly upon the Alms of their Hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, eſpecially when they found this a pleaſing Doctrine, plauſible with the covetuous multitude, who for the moſt part are willing to go the cheapeſt way to Heaven, and therefore cryed it up, as the <hi>true Apoſtolical manner.</hi> This ſelf-denial of theirs, and <hi>Compli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance with the preſent exigences</hi> has begot ſuch dangerous opinions in the minds of ſome, and by the ſubtle contrivance of Satan, willing to improve any advantage, brought ſuch a ſnare upon their Succeſſours, that many poor innocent perſons often urge <hi>their example</hi> for a pattern, and would <hi>fain reduce all to that model,</hi> never conſidering what a vaſt difference our Gracious God, who diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Times and Seaſons has put between theirs, and ours, both in reſpect of Preachers, and Hearers. But if the people of this Nation (by Providence) ſhould be reduced to ſuch extremities, I hope their Miniſters could be content cheerfully, and without repining to ſuffer with them: <hi>in the mean while, reaſon, and gratitude require they ſhould partake in the common hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe.</hi>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:40451:15"/>Now I ſay, if ſuch conſiderations did not prevail with me I ſhould be ready to tax the imprudence of thoſe eminent Worthies in betraying the <hi>Priviledges and Revenues of the Goſpel,</hi> which Chriſt himſelf, by an irrepealeable Charter, has ſetled upon his Miniſters.</p>
               <p>I dare not deny but ſome holy men have ſlighted Honours, and that Portion due to their Calling out of ſincere Principles, and a good meaning, who yet have lived to repent their errour, (though not able to redreſſe it) when they have ſeen how much the Church has thereby ſuffered, and religion been damni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luther Ep. p.</hi> 13.</note> Witneſſe
<hi>Luther</hi> who ſadly complains, <hi>Ego pro meo ſtipen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dio Annuo tantum novem antiquas Sexagenas habeo, praeter has ne obo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus quidem aut mihi, aut Fratribus è Civitate accedit.</hi> A brave Reward for ſuch matchleſſe deſerts! and if ſo happy an Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of
<hi>Europes</hi> Reformation, ſo valiant a Champion, who ſingly oppoſed the United Power of <hi>Rome</hi> and Hell, found no better uſage, what might other Punies expect, if they were left to the frozen charity of this griping Age. Certainly they had all need make it part of their dayly Letany, to be delivered from ſuch unmerciful Taskmaſters. Nor was this his fate only, but
<hi>Calvin, Beza, Muſculus, Saravia,</hi> &amp;c. oftentimes bitterly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moane the pitifull allowances of the Reformed Clergy in moſt foraign Countries. Though too many may thank themſelves; for if it be lawful to ſpeak my thoughts, I fear ſuperſtition in ſome few, <hi>weakneſſe, and affecting the name of deſpiſing the World in moſt,</hi> have been the principal inducements to relinquiſh that which their <hi>Bountiful Maſter</hi> beſtowed upon them, and Goſpel Liberty allowed them to challenge. Are we not commanded to honour the Lord with our ſubſtance, which muſt be performed <hi>in well Stewarding it,</hi> not in a careleſs contempt of our unque<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ionable Inheritance. Let no man therefore hope to build any ſtrong argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon this <hi>Sandy Foundation,</hi> or to juſtifie their Sacriledge by ſuch Writings, and Practice.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:40451:15"/>
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Sacriledge condemned in a ſerious Expostulation, with the Authors of it.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>NOw before <hi>I</hi> diſmiſſe this, <hi>I</hi> cannot but a little expoſtulate matters with our late Church-Robbers; who, tis feared, did never impartially weigh that of <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.22. when ſo they might ſly from Popiſh Idolatry, valued not what <hi>Sacred ſpoiles</hi> they committed. And <hi>I</hi> wiſh any that deny a <hi>Relative Holineſſe</hi> in Things, and Places would explain to us what the Apoſtle meant by that word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Sacriledge,</hi> that ſo we may correct all the Gloſſaries yet publiſhed, which <hi>I</hi> cannot find in the leaſt to ſmile upon, and countenance their Proceedings. Methinks theſe men ſhould never read the 47 of <hi>Gen.</hi> without drawing a bluſh in their cheeks, to ſee a prophane <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> ſparing the
<hi>Lands of the Prieſts,</hi> and taking ſpecial care to provide for their maintenance, allowing them a Portion from the Publick (the Quantity of Bread, Wine, and Fleſh ſee at large in <hi>Herodot. Euterp.</hi>) when all the reſt of <hi>Egypt</hi> was morgaged, and his other Subjects muſt either pinch with Famine, or pay dear for Grain. And from this paſſage
<hi>Aqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nas</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Com in</hi> 13. <hi>c. Ep. ad Rom.</hi>
                  </note> collects <hi>Sacerdotal Immunity</hi> to be agreeable to natural Equity. The Roman Orator
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>L.</hi> 3. <hi>de Nat. Deo.</hi>
                  </note> has a remarkable ſtory concerning <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> that taking all the <hi>Conſecrated wealth</hi> out of the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the Gods, he expoſed it to ſale in the open Markets, and meeting with good ready mony Chapmen raiſed an incredible ſum; but the Tyrant having better conſidered of it, ſoon after by Proclamation, ordered all to be reſtored upon ſevere Penalties, <hi>fearing more the guilt of Sacriledge, then the reproach of Injuſtice.</hi> And well might this be dreaded, if he had known all.
<hi>Plato de Leg. Dial.</hi> 9. thought none would be ſo wretched as to attempt ſuch a thing, eſpecially a Citizen: but if any did, he pronounces him <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Incurable,</hi> and awards preſent Death. The Roman
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:40451:16"/>1.2. Tables ranked ſuch amongſt the moſt Capital offenders, <hi>Sacrum, Sacrove commendatum qui clepſerit, rapſeritve, Parricida eſto.</hi> And under the Law there were Attonements appointed for the greateſt ſins, Perjury, Uncleaneſſe, Murther, and Sacriledge through ignorance, <hi>Lev.</hi> 5.15. but <hi>preſumptuous knowing ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſeems unpardonable,</hi> there being <hi>no expiation ordered</hi> for it. You know whoſe Language tis, <hi>Will a man rob his God?</hi> Mal. 3.4. Certainly, the ſo much <hi>condemned Jews</hi> will riſe in Judgement againſt <hi>this generation,</hi> who (though they filched now and then in Tithes and Offerings) yet in their greateſt preſſures never toucht the Revenues of the Prieſts, nor do any of the Prophets (no meal-mouth'd flatterers) charge them with this ſin: but the Levites portion, the 48. Cities aſſigned them by <hi>Joſhuah,</hi> (increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in after ages, as it ſhould ſeem by the Liſt, 1.
<hi>Chron.</hi> 6. to above 60.) though of greater emolument, and far more conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble (put all together) then what our Engliſh Clergy ever enjoyed, continued entire, and without diminution, or diſturbance to that Tribe, till the final ſubverſion of the Jewiſh State.</p>
               <p>Should we grant theſe Lands had at firſt been given out of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, tis not a blemiſh in the Donours intention that will make void the Act. If ſo there would have been colour enough to plunder the Treaſury of the Temple, becauſe the proud Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſes (and many ſuch like) caſt in their Offerings, <hi>Mar.</hi> 12. In the 16 of <hi>Numb.</hi> we have the Genſers of <hi>Corah,</hi> and his accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plices <hi>(men of the Lords anger and indignation)</hi> offered in a rebelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſinfull manner, yet commanded to be imployed in ſome holy uſes, and not prophaned, becauſe they were once hallowed in being dedicated to the God of Iſrael. And this Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mends as a pattern to Chriſtian Magiſtrates to be imitated in paralel caſes. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 54. Should we grant the preſent Incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bents had never ſo much misbehaved themſelves, profuſely laviſhing the Churches Patrimony, perverting it to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane uſes, proud backs, and pampered bellies. Yet how had Chriſt offended? what had he done, that you ſhould deprive him of his portion and Inheritance, thoſe ſmall fragments which former Covetuouſnes had ſpared? <hi>For know Ye ſons of Sacriledge, that what you took,
<note place="margin">Cooks Com. <hi>in Magn. Char.</hi>
                     </note> from the Church, you took from him,</hi> it being the Tenour of all the old grants
<hi>Magna Charta,</hi> and others, <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſimus
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:40451:16"/>Deo—</hi> For <hi>Quod datum eſt Eccleſiae, datum eſt Deo.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It has made me tremble many a time, when I have read in the old Charters the <hi>dreadfull execrations denounced</hi> againſt thoſe that ſhould lay hands on thoſe <hi>Devoted Things,</hi> recorded in <hi>Spelm. Counc.</hi> and <hi>Monaſt. Angl. Paſſim. &amp;c.</hi> bure I am
<hi>Hehemiah</hi> one of the beſt, and greateſt Reformers in the world could not bear the alienation of one poor Chamber belonging to the Prieſts
<hi>c.</hi> 13.7, 8. ſo farre was he from preying upon any thing himſelf. And yet no Reformation could content ours but an utter depriving the Embaſſadors of Chriſt of their faireſt encouragements. If our eyes had not beheld, and our eares heard it, could it be imagined, there ſhould be any in theſe Goſpel-dayes to repine at the wealth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred upon the Clergy, and to uſe Language much like that of <hi>Foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix</hi> Treaſurer to
<hi>Julian,
<note place="margin">Magdeburg. <hi>Cent.</hi> 4.</note> ſee in what plenty theſe ſervants of the Son of Mary live.</hi> Well I had almoſt ſaid that the ſin of Sacriledge in taking away the Churches Patrimony cryes lowder in the eares of Heaven, then ever did their pride, and luxury in abuſing it. Yet am I none of thoſe that will once open my mouth in defence of looſeneſs, debauchery, and ſuch Immoralities, <hi>which my Soul ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horres equall to Hereſie.</hi> But if wealth be ſo apt to corrupt them, ler all the Lawes already enacted be impartially executed, and if that be not judged ſufficient, let as ſevere ones be added as the <hi>Wiſdome of our Senators ſhall think fit</hi> to meet with growing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders, and abuſes, I beleive theres none will decline,
<note place="margin">Veſſii <hi>Hiſt. Pelag. l.</hi> 5.
<hi>Part</hi> 2.</note> whatever lawfull Authority ſhall impoſe. Only tis hoped <hi>that peice of Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gianiſme</hi> is not now revived, that tis impoſſible to be <hi>great and good, Rich &amp; Humble.</hi> Tis true the poor bladders of mans tainted nature are too prone to ſwell with a little wind, but God can keep the heart low, under the higheſt honours, ſober in the greateſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence. Have we not <hi>Joſeph</hi> the ſecond perſon in <hi>Aegypt, David</hi> a King, Daniel and <hi>Nehemiah</hi> Courtiers, and yet their hearts right with God, their Integrity ſtill retained. Nor is it poverty of eſtate, but of ſpirit to which Chriſt promiſes the bleſſing, <hi>Mat.</hi> 5. There may then be good uſe made of this unrighteous <hi>Mam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> for as wine is not evil, but drunkenneſs, no more are riches evil, but Covetuouſnes. Let not any therefore be cheated by ſuch pitifull Sophiſmes, countenanced only by ſome few wreſted Texts of Scripture, and miſunderſtood paſſages of Antiquity.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:40451:17"/>
               <p>Let me but ask any conſiderate perſon, what we have
<hi>gained by all our</hi> 20. <hi>years wandrings? One of the beautifulleſt Iſlands, and flouriſhing Churches in</hi> Europe, hath been almoſt ruined by <hi>our Giddineſse. Let zealous ignorance</hi> now confeſſe its miſtake, and by a <hi>dutiful Conformity</hi> hereafter redeem its errors. Have you comfort to look back upon the Deſolations you have made, ſo many magnificent Churches Levelled to the ground, ſo many converted into Magazines of War, Dens of Thieves, and Stables for Horſes, which the poor <hi>innocent Beaſts</hi> have already ſmarted for. I dare not go about to fathom the Depths of Divine Judgements, thoſe waies are unſearchable, and thoſe paths paſt finding out: but if we will believe ſome curious Obſervers, theyle tell us, that the <hi>Prodigious Diſeaſe,</hi> which has of late ſo much <hi>raged amonſt Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, had its Original in the Houſe of God,</hi> beginning at the Guards in St. <hi>Pauls.</hi> And our eyes have beheld in theſe late Revolutions in how eminent a manner the Righteous God has frowned upon the great <hi>Sticklers in Church Lands,</hi> declaring in the face of all the World, how much <hi>his ſoul abhors the covetuous.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now ſince God has ſmiled upon us, to reſtore our Rulers as at the firſt, tis hoped our <hi>wiſe Senators</hi> will be careful to wipe away that ſtain, and blot, which lies upon our Reformation for alienating Monaſtick Revenues, and not adde ſin to ſin, and iniquity to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.
<hi>Moſt Honoured Patriots,</hi> you are the great Repreſentatives of the Nation, whoſe Repure ought to be dear unto you. Be pleaſed then to conſider, <hi>Will it not be a reproach to a rich, and ſlouriſhing Kingdom, to have a ſtarved indigent Clergy, in a Land of Plenty expoſed to Beggery?</hi> An injury and diſhonour to the memory of your <hi>Religious Anceſtours, and Predeceſſors,</hi> who not out of ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant zeal, and blind ſuperſtition, but conſcience, but honour to the God of their ſubſtance, Conſecrated ſome portion of their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtates to his ſervice, and confirmed the Donations of others, not only by <hi>naked Votes, but repeated oathes?</hi> Now to have all theſe Monuments of their Devotion at once ſwallowed up by their Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious Poſterity. Or will any be ſo mad for the future, as to become Benefactors, when there is ſo little Security in <hi>the Publick faith of a Nation.</hi> Certainly this was one of the deadlieſt blows that for many years has been given to Religion; what an hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drance has it proved to the happy progreſſe, and ſucceſſe of the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:40451:17"/>Goſpel, what an advantage to the Kingdom of Satan, making us ſtink in the Noſtrils of all the neighbouring Countries, alienating the hearts of ſundry well-affected, weakning the hands of Friends, and ſtrengthning Enemies? And if the Romiſh Emiſſaries could but have perfected their
<note n="*" place="margin">Campanell<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> Deſign, and compaſſed what they ſo much tug'd for in our late Troubles, to ruine the Univerſities, deprive the Clergy of a ſetled Maintenance, and bring them to a <hi>ſordid Benevolence,</hi> they had done their work. <hi>How many hopeful perſons intended for Labourers in Chriſts Vineyard,</hi> have been here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by diſcouraged, their <hi>worldly Parents diverting them to more gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full imployments,</hi> many Congregations left deſtitute of able Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,
<hi>Blue Aprons,</hi> and <hi>Buff Coats</hi> ſtepping up in their rooms, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by ſuch an Inundation of Errours have brake in upon us, that it requires <hi>skillfull Pilots to keep the Ark of our poor Church from Sinking.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="clergy's honours" type="apology">
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:40451:18"/>
            <head>THE CLERGIES HONOURS.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The Honour of the Sacred Function vindicated by Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, Reaſon, Equity and Fathers.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſecond Head to be treated of, is the Reſpect and Honour due to this Sacred Function, which the Spirit of God is not ſparing, or backward in aſſerting, knowing the malice of Satan, and the depraved Nature of man prone enough to vilifie it. And therefore that none might plead igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, we have repeated Precepts ſcattered up and down in ſundry places. In the 2. <hi>Philip.</hi> 29. the Preachers of the Goſpel are commanded to be had in honour; and 1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.12. to be eſteemed, and Reverenced <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> exceeding abundantly, the Original being ſcarce to be expreſſed by a Tranſlation. Now the grand deſign of all this is, that Chriſt may be advanced, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect ſhown to the Servant, redounds to the Maſter, who will one day own it, inaſmuch as ye did it unto one of theſe <hi>Little Ones,</hi>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:40451:18"/>ye did it unto me. The Honour and Preferments you conferred upon them, I take as done to my ſelf. I wonder what anſwer our Clergy-Haters will return to ſuch clear Texts, certainly they muſt borrow that Gloſſe of the <hi>Learned Canonist, Statuimus,</hi> i. e.
<hi>Abrogamus:</hi> for their practiſe puts no better a Comment upon thoſe words of S. <hi>Paul, Honour</hi> thoſe that are over you, <hi>i. e.</hi> deſpiſe them, reviſe them, and take away their maintenance. It has oftentimes ſaddened my ſoul, to ſee many who pretend to higher Diſpenſations, a more eminent degree of Sanctity then their Brethren, to place much of their Religion in ſcorning and revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling the Embaſſadors of Chriſt, as if they did him ſervice when they caſt dirt in the face of his Miniſters. But he will at laſt give them ſlender thanks for their prepoſterous zeal.</p>
               <p>We have the Great Apoſtle of the Gentiles for an example, that boaſting does not alwaies misbecome us: and doubtleſſe, if ever it were ſeaſonable, now is the time, when this <hi>Art of Arts the Government of Souls,</hi> is ſo much trampled upon.
<note place="margin">Scholiast. Pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar.</note> Now if the Dignity of a Calling may be judged by the uſefulneſſe of it, which is
<hi>Pindars</hi> Argument for his <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; Where is any that dares ſtand in competition with this? Other Profeſſions are variable like the Moon, ſometimes dark, and ſometimes ſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, at certain fits and ſeaſons ſerviceable: this never out of date, never to be diſpenſed with. A Souldier is loved, or rather feared in War, but diſregarded in
<hi>Peace;</hi> a Phyſitian's ſeldom courted but in ſickneſſe, and by crazy diſtempered bodies; and for Lawyers, they are principally lookt after, when men are diſpoſed to wrangle; but theres no Age, no Seaſon, no State of Life that does not require, at leaſt need, the aſſiſtance of a Divine.</p>
               <p>Again, if that Profeſſion which can produce the moſt Worthy Perſons engaged in it (as <hi>Scal.</hi> argues) ſhould carry the Bell, the day is ſurely their own. In our Corporations here, if a King be but made free of ſuch a Company, the Society preſently vaunt they have gained much credit by it: but how many Emperours, Princes, and Nobles, may be inſtanced in, that have not only liſted them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, but actually exerciſed the Office of the Miniſtery.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Spelm. Ep. Ded. ant. Con. Cambd. Brit.</hi> p. 98.</note> 
                  <hi>Capgrave</hi> reckons up at leaſt a Score of our Britiſh Kings and Queens, that left their Scepters, and betook themſelves to Religion in thoſe fertile Ages of Royal Saints. Peruſe the holy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:40451:19"/>we have <hi>Melchiſedock</hi> a King, and a Prieſt, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.1 <hi>David</hi> a King and a Prophet: and
<hi>Solomon,</hi> the Wiſeſt of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tals, glorying more in the name of a Preacher, then all his Royal Titles. But why ſtand I upon theſe, when Jeſus Chriſt the King of Kings, the Eternal Son of God, thoughtit not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him, telling us expreſly, <hi>Luke</hi> 4.18. that he was ſent into the World, on no other errand, then to <hi>preach the Goſpel.</hi> Here upon earth, a great Perſonage, that had but one only Child, would be loath to imploy him in any baſe unworthy calling: and may we not here ſafely conclude this to be an Honourable Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, which the moſt Wiſe God put the <hi>Son of his Boſom</hi> to. Let me ſpeak <hi>a proud word then</hi> (at leaſt ſome will judge it ſo) <hi>the Miniſtry is an Imployment, that the Nobleſt Peer, nay the greateſt Prince upon earth, need not be aſhamed of. Nor let any one bluſh to be of that Profeſſion, which</hi> Adam, Moſes, David, Solomon, <hi>nay</hi> Chriſt himſelf hath honoured.</p>
               <p>I ſhall not take notice of thoſe <hi>Rhodomontado Vaunts</hi> of the brag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging <hi>Canoniſts,</hi> who compare the Clergy to the Sun, and the Lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the Moon; Though backed by an eminent
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Bartol. Confil.</hi> 18. <hi>ſi Aliqua Coll.</hi> 2.</note> Civilian, who pronounces the Sacerdotal dignity greater then any Secular. Nor doe many of the ancient Fathers come farre behind them, who have very ſwelling expreſſions to this purpoſe. Hear but
<hi>Ignatius</hi> St. <hi>John</hi>'s Diſciple,
<note place="margin">Ep. ad Smyrn.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>; the Prieſthood tranſcends every thing amongſt mortals. And
<hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſtyles the Clergy Chriſts Deputies or Vice-ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, preſently adding,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Hom.</hi> 17. <hi>on St. Mat.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>&amp;c.</hi> As much as the Heaven is more honourable then the Earth, and Soules then bodies, ſo much is the Spiritual Function more excellent then the Civil. But theſe ſtraines are ſomewhat Hyperbolical, and muſt be underſtood in a qualified ſenſe, with ſome graines of allowance.</p>
               <p>Come to thoſe that ſpeak modeſtly and ſoberly. For the Jewes <hi>Joſephus</hi> is my Authour, that Intereſt in the ſacred Function, was an unerring argument, of a ſplendid Original,
<note n="*" place="margin">Joſ. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>it. juxta init.</note>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Caſaubon</hi> ſtops not there, but will have it to be the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Exercit. in Bar.</hi> 1. <hi>N.</hi>
5.</note> 
                  <hi>only Nobility</hi> (when the Line of <hi>David</hi> was eclipſed) all others though never ſo powerfull, never ſo wealthy
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:40451:19"/>being lookt upon as no better then
<hi>Plebeians.</hi> Deſcend to Goſpel times, <hi>Clericatus eſt Dignitas,</hi> ſaith <hi>Panormitan,</hi> any Relation to the Church entitles a man to honour. And he that reades the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſts, Baſilica,</hi> or our own <hi>Lambard,</hi> will find the meaneſt Clergy man of no ſmall account amongſt the Ancients; the principal part, <hi>viz.</hi> the
<hi>Biſhops,</hi> being all the <hi>Saxon</hi> period ranked among the
<hi>Greater Thanes,</hi> and in the <hi>Norman</hi> daies equal to the
<hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons,</hi> as will in its proper place be farther cleared. For Reaſon, and common equity do ſeeme to ſuggeſt that their condition is honourable, who are immediately ſet apart to the <hi>ſervice of the great God.</hi> We ſee how thoſe are valued that attend upon the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of Princes, and what large Priviledges are granted by the
<note n="*" place="margin">Dig. &amp; Cod. Paſſim.</note> Imperial Edicts to earthly warriors, and ſhall thoſe that fight under the Banner of the King of Heaven, for ſuch a Title is given them, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi>
2. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>the ſpirituall militia,</hi> be trampled upon, and eſteemed as the <hi>Droſſe,</hi> and <hi>Refuſe</hi> of the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? Tis ſtrang to ſee how diſdainfully many in our Age think of them, and how unwilling they are to place their ſonnes to this Function, as if it were <hi>a ſtain to their blood.</hi> When yet we read of
<hi>Eſay</hi> of the Royal Line of Judah, and in our own Nation we find
<hi>Ethelwolfe</hi> (as <hi>Rog. Hoveden</hi>) <hi>Ethulf,</hi> as
<hi>Monaſt. Ang.</hi> calls him) a profeſt Clergy-man, conſecrated Biſhop of <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> yet cl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt ſonne to K. <hi>Egbert,</hi> (no petty Prince) and after his Fathers death, ſecond Monarch of the united Heptarchy A. 837. Come lower we have <hi>Henry de Bloys</hi> brother to K
<hi>Stephen</hi> Biſhop of the ſame See: <hi>Geoffry Plantagenet</hi> Son to <hi>Hen.</hi> 2d. Biſhop of <hi>Lincoln.</hi> And that I may not waſte time in ſuch inſtances, which might without number be produced;
<note place="margin">Godwin.</note> 
                  <hi>Cutbert</hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſhop of <hi>Durham</hi> of the blood-Royall of the Kings of <hi>Ireland.</hi> Nor did <hi>Michael</hi> the proud Emperour of <hi>Ruſſia</hi> take it to be any diſparagement in this laſt age, to make his Father <hi>Theodore</hi> Arch-Biſhop of
<hi>Moſco.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Poſſevin.</note> Nay the Princely ſtock of <hi>Judah</hi> did not look upon it as any imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, any ſlur, or
<hi>Alloy</hi> to them, to mingle the Royall and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotal blood, for 2
<hi>Chron.</hi> 22.11. Tis recorded, that <hi>Jehoiada</hi> the Prieſt Married the Daughter of King <hi>Jehoram,</hi> and 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 23.31. A Kings Mother is ſaid to be the Daughter of a Prieſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:40451:20"/>
               <head>CHAP. II. A <hi>large Tribute of Honour and Reverence paid by the very</hi> Pagans <hi>and</hi> Mahometans <hi>to their Prieſts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>SEarch the Pagan Records, you'l find they thought no Honour too high, no reward too great for thoſe that attended the Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of their Idols. I am almoſt afraid to write what I meet with in approved Authours, and ſhould be ready to diſtruſt them my ſelf, but that I am ſatisfied they were no Parties, nor prompted by Intereſt. Ile begin with
<hi>Tacitus,</hi> who tells us that amongſt the old <hi>Germans
<note n="*" place="margin">De Morib. German.</note> Sacerdotibus, juxta ac Regibus honor habitus eſt.</hi> Now the Grandeur of the world conſiſts principally in Apparel, Dyer, and Houſes, in all which the Prieſts exceeded. We read in <hi>Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bo l.</hi> 12. that the Prieſts of
<hi>Cuma-Pontus</hi> twice in a year wore a Diadem. <hi>Oroſuss l.</hi> 4.
<hi>c.</hi> 6. relates that the Preiſts of <hi>Hercules Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi> were ever clad in purple, and walk'd in publick adorned with Crownes. Goe to the barbarous <hi>Indians,</hi> there <hi>Varenius</hi> aſſures us that in
<hi>Japan</hi> the Preiſts are <hi>clad in Silk down to the Ancles,</hi> and the <hi>Bonzius,</hi> or Chief Preiſt <hi>regalibus afficitur honoribus. Froius</hi> in his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles addes that they all dwell magnificently, and have very large incomes. But of this <hi>Vitruvius</hi> is the moſt proper Judge, who <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 8. acquaints us, that the high prieſt among the <hi>Trallians</hi> in habited a <hi>Stately Royal Palace.</hi> Then for their food
<note n="*" place="margin">Roſinus Rhodigin. Cicer. Orat. de Aruſp. Reſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Dapes Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liares, Obſonari pollucibibiter, Epulonum Collegium,</hi> with their Pontifical Feaſts grew into a proverb for their Prodigality. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed ſo univerſally great, and Reverend was the Reputation of the Prieſthood, that none on earth might vy with it, being the higheſt any Mortal was capable of, the next and immediate Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to a Deity. Under the Law of Nature we do not meet with many Inſtances of believing Kings, only Melchiſedeck King of <hi>Salem,</hi> in whoſe perſon, both Kingdom, and Prieſthood were united, <hi>Gen.</hi> 4. Unleſſe we ſhould adde <hi>Jethro,</hi> who is promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuouſly ſtyled Prince and Prieſt of
<hi>Midian, Exod.</hi> 2. Now this combining together of the <hi>two Functions,</hi> was afterwards com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:40451:20"/>imitated by the Heathens: amongſt whom there was ever little difference between Prince, and Prieſt; whence ſome conjecture, that under this laſt Notion the former received Tithes, for that they were uſually paid him, may be gathered from 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.15.
<hi>Servius</hi> upon the 3. <hi>Enn.</hi> is poſitive for a generall uſance, <hi>Majorum haec erat Conſuetudo ut Rox eſſet etiam Sacerdos, vel Pontifex.</hi> Whereupon <hi>Diogenes</hi> in <hi>Stobaeus</hi> laies it down amongſt the Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fications of his <hi>Compleat King,</hi> that he muſt be <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, a good Souldier, a Judge, and <hi>a Priest. Strabo</hi> is expreſſe <hi>L.</hi> 5. that in <hi>Aritia</hi> the Kingdome was united to the Prieſthood of <hi>Diana,</hi> in
<note n="*" place="margin">Hirt. Bell. Alexandr.</note>
                  <hi>Cappadocia,</hi> to the Temple of <hi>Bellona.</hi> And <hi>Juſtin,</hi> amongſt many Fables of the <hi>Jews,</hi> has this truth, <hi>L.</hi> 36. that <hi>mos erat apud Judaeos ut eoſdem &amp; regis, &amp; ſacerdotes habeant,</hi> twas a received cuſtome with them for the ſame perſon to bear both Offices. <hi>Dion. Lib.</hi> 37. enlarges it to all <hi>Syria,</hi> that twas their manner to confound the Titles of King and Prieſt. The old
<hi>Ethiopians,</hi> and
<note n="*" place="margin">Marſil. Ficin Praef in Triſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megiſt.</note> 
                  <hi>Egyptians</hi> choſe their Kings out of, at leaſt
<note n="*" place="margin">Plato L. de Regn.</note> permitted the Election of them to the Colledge of their Prieſts; who ever enjoyed the next place of Dignity and power to their Soveraign,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Diodor. Sicul. L.</hi> 2.</note>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. If theſe generals will not ſatisfie, let us come to particulars, and twill eaſily be made appear, that the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Potentates in the World did not think the Prieſthood below them. Thus <hi>Midas,</hi> King of <hi>Phrygia,</hi> was conſecrated to <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheus, Juſtin L.</hi>
11. The <hi>Lacedemonian</hi> Kings did alwaies ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice in perſon,
<hi>Herodot. in Erat. Zenophon</hi> records the like of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byſes, Curtius</hi> of <hi>Alexander,</hi> and <hi>Halycarnaſſ:</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>L.</hi> 2.</note> ſpeaking of
<hi>Romu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus,</hi> ſaith, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, all that concerned the gods were managed by himſelf. In imitation of whom <hi>Julius, Auguſtus,</hi> and all the ſucceeding Emperours, both <hi>Pagan</hi> and Chriſtian, till
<hi>Gratians</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Zozimus.</note> daies, retained the Title of <hi>Pont. Max.</hi> as may be ſeen in their ſeveral Edicts, and Coyns. <hi>Heliogabalus</hi> was not content with a ſingle one, but to make his perſon more Sacred, muſt be created Prieſt of the
<hi>Phaenicians.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Hierodian. l.</hi> 5.</note> Nor muſt the poor <hi>Indians</hi> be omitted, for in <hi>Malabar</hi> their very Kings do not diſdain the Office of the <hi>Bracmans Lopez. Hiſt. Ind. L.</hi> 1.
<hi>c.</hi>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:40451:21"/>14. And if youl conſult the Epiſtles of
<hi>Xavier</hi> (the late Canonized <hi>Indian</hi> Apoſtle) youl find the
<hi>Bouzii</hi> to be generally the ſons of Princes and Nobles;
<hi>Almeida</hi> mentioning one that in his time was Counſellour to the King.</p>
               <p>Come to the <hi>Mahometans</hi> we have the proud
<note n="*" place="margin">Gabriel Sionita</note> 
                  <hi>Sultan</hi> himſelf ſo far honouring the <hi>Mufti,</hi> that as often as he comes into his preſence, he riſes from his ſeat, and according <hi>to their mode,</hi> put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting his hand to the breaſt, bows the head in token of Reverence, an honour which he ſhews not to any other Subject, and will hardly vouchſafe the like to the mightieſt Monarch upon earth. Neither do the inferiour Degrees want their due eſteem: for after their <hi>Mufti,</hi> they have their <hi>Cadeliſchers,</hi> ſomewhat reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling the Chriſtian Patriarchs, next their <hi>Cades</hi> anſwerable to our Biſhops, then their
<hi>Santons &amp; Taliſmans</hi> ſuitable to our Presbyters and Deacons, the loweſt of whoſe number is highly reſpected by the people.
<note place="margin">Elma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>in. Hiſt. Arab.</note> 
                  <hi>Id.</hi> Then for the old
<hi>Saracens</hi> tis a matter ſufficiently known that with them for ſome
100 of years the ſame Perſon was both Prince and Caliph.</p>
               <p>I might multiply innumerable inſtances to this purpoſe, but I ſhall not weary my Reader. Now let not any <hi>envious Momus</hi> imagine, that all this while I drive on a deſign to have this revived, and made a pattern for Chriſtians, no, my only meaning is to put our Clergy-haters to the bluſh, if they <hi>have ſo much of vertue left as the Colour,</hi> when they ſee how by the <hi>common conſent of Nations,</hi> which
<hi>Tully</hi> calls the Law of Nature, the higheſt Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour was ever given to the Prieſt. The Prince of Philoſophers lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it down for an Axiom, that twas a work moſt proper for the worthieſt:
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ariſtotle.</hi> 7. <hi>Polit. c.</hi>
9.</note> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. No Peaſant, no Artiſan muſt defile theſe Sacred things, <hi>quia par eſt Optimum ab Optimo coli, &amp; Summum à Summo,</hi> there muſt be ſome reſemblance and Analogy between the Maſter and the Servant. And therefore, if we will <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leive Trigautius,</hi> amongſt the wiſe <hi>Chinois, olim Rex, hodie ſoli litant Magiſtratus primarii, Regnique Proceres:</hi> No Inferiour perſon muſt come neer the Altar.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:40451:21"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. Englands <hi>Reſpect to the Clergy.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>FOr their Nobility in our own Nation, <hi>Spelman</hi> and
<hi>Lambard,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>pelm. C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>nc. Ep. ad <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eg.</note> confeſſedly the Ableſt Pair of our <hi>Saxon</hi> Antiquaries) do avouch, that the <hi>Saxons</hi> ever reputed the Biſhops equal, and in ſome points Superiour to their Greater Thanes, whom Poſterity call Barons, and (as may be ſeen in
<note n="*" place="margin">Archaion.</note> 
                  <hi>Lambard</hi>) the Laws of <hi>Ethelbert, Ina,</hi> and <hi>Aethelſtan</hi> do rate them accordingly. Nay in all the ancient Charters, the firſt place was ever given to the Spiritual Lords. In a Donation of <hi>Ethelbert</hi> A. 605. to the Monaſtery of S. <hi>Peter</hi> in <hi>Canterbury,</hi> the firſt witneſſe ſubſcribing is <hi>Auſtin</hi> the Biſhop, and after him ſeveral Dukes, and Earls. In a Charter of King <hi>Ina's</hi> A. 725. to the Monaſtery of <hi>Glaſſenbury:</hi> after the Biſhops
<hi>Beorthwald,</hi> and <hi>Fordred,</hi> we have <hi>Waldhere, Ethelherd, Umming</hi> and <hi>Winchelin,</hi> the greateſt Peers in the Nation, putting their names. Preſently after, in a Grant of <hi>Offa's</hi> to the Abby of
<hi>Worceſter,</hi> A. 780, <hi>Brordran, Berhtand, Eadbald</hi> and
<hi>Eadbald,</hi> two Princes, and two Dukes follow the Biſhops.
<note place="margin">Monast. Angl. &amp; Spelm. Conc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>poſſim.</note> And at the ſame Kings Conſecration of St. <hi>Albans</hi> A. 793. no leſſe than ten Dukes, beſides other Nobles, give place to the Prelates. Come down an Age
<hi>Lower</hi> in the Donation of <hi>Edgar</hi> to the Covent of
<hi>Glaſſenbury,</hi> the Biſhops lead, and <hi>Elphere, Oſlac, Ethelwine,</hi> three Dukes bring up the Rear. And to make an end in a Charter of <hi>Edward</hi> the Confeſſors, to the Monaſtery of
<hi>Wincheſter,</hi> imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diatly after the King ſubſcribed
<hi>Plegmund,</hi> and <hi>Fritheſtan</hi> the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, being followed by
<hi>Ethelweard</hi> the Kings Brother, <hi>Aethel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtan,</hi> and
<hi>Aelfweard,</hi> the Kings two Sons, <hi>Ordluf, Oſred, Brorh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tulf, Ordgar,</hi> and <hi>Heethferth</hi> Dukes: many more of this Nature might be produced out of the ſame Authors, and others, as ſtanding monuments of the Clergies eminent Reputation, &amp; the Reverence our Religious Anceſtours bare to their Function. And that this may not be thought to proceed meerly from the courteſie of England, as in ſome other Caſes tis familiar: We have it confirmed by Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:40451:22"/>31. <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>c.</hi> 10. where in all Degrees, and Offices are pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced in Aſſemblies and Conferences, and there the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> as <hi>Primus Par Regni,</hi> the firſt Peer of the Kingdom, is ranked before all the Nobility, ſeated at the Kings right hand, next and immediatly after the Royal Blood, and the Vice-Gerent, and the reſt of the Biſhops follow him in their due Precedency according to the Dignity and Anciancies of their Reſpective Sees. And tis farther obſervable, that they are ever named before the Temporal Lords in
<hi>Magna Charta, Charta de Foreſt.</hi> &amp;c. Nor were they ever excluded from the greateſt imployments of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and Truſt in the Nation. And to evidence that this is not ſpake without book, I ſhall ſubjoyn a Catalogue of Church-men (collected out of <hi>Malmesbury, Harpſfield, Godwin, Spelman, Iſaac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon,</hi> &amp;c.) that have borne all, at leaſt the moſt Honourable Offices of State, and (however beſpattered by ſome) diſcharged them with much integrity and repute; <hi>England</hi> owing more of its happineſſe to men of this Calling, then any other. Though it cannot be denied, but ſome miſcarriages may here and there be found, yet as few as can be expected in ſuch a multitude: and if a man were diſpoſed to carp, he might without much ſweat, produce two for one in critically examining any other Profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. I ſhall begin with the Metropolitan, to whom this Primacy juſtly appertains, and take the reſt in order.</p>
               <p>
                  <floatingText xml:lang="eng">
                     <body>
                        <div type="church_honours">
                           <div n="Canterbury" type="diocese">
                              <head>CANTERB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RY.</head>
                              <p>WE find fewer of this See upon the Civil Stage then any other; moſt Offices being lookt upon as below the Archi-Epiſcopal Dignity, and therefore a Nobleman upbraided <hi>Hubert</hi> with it, when A.
1199. (according to <hi>Spelman, Godwin</hi> 93.) he was made Chancellour of England, Chief Juſtice, and High Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of all the Dominions under King
<hi>Rich.</hi> 1. Afterwards King <hi>John</hi> entruſted the ſame Prelate with the Government of the whole Realm at his departure into Normandy.
<hi>Walter Reynalds,</hi> Chancel. A. 1310. <hi>John Stratford</hi> Chancel. under <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. and when the King invaded France, no perſon thought ſo fit in his abſence to have the Government of the Nation entruſted to him, <hi>Simon Iſlip</hi> of the Privy Council to <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>John Stafford</hi>
                                 <pb n="43" facs="tcp:40451:22"/>to <hi>Hen.</hi> 5. <hi>John Moorton</hi> to <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. and <hi>Edw.</hi> 4. But why ſtand I upon this, when in truth it has been ſeldom known, that any of them have been omitted.
<note place="margin">Fox Martyr.</note> Nor was this proper only to the times of Popery: Come to the Reformation, we find
<hi>Cranmer</hi> of the Privy Council to <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. and <hi>Edw.</hi> 6.
<hi>and very active in civil mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters: yet a man ſo averſe to Rome, ſo inſtrumental in planting the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, ſo laborious, ſo holy, that a great
<note n="*" place="margin">Brightman. Com.</note> Apocalytpical man (and no friend to the Hierarchy) takes him to be that Angel pointed at by the Spirit of God.</hi> Revel. 14. <hi>that had power over the fire.</hi> Under the renowned Queen <hi>Elizabeth, John Whitgift</hi> of the Council, and the Government of the Principality of Wales given up to him.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="York" type="diocese">
                              <head>YORK.</head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Walter Gray</hi> Chancellour under King
<hi>John,</hi> had the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Realm entruſted to him under
<hi>Hen.</hi> 3. <hi>William de Melton</hi> ſucceſſively Treaſurer and Chancellour of England, A. 1317. <hi>William de Zouche,</hi> Vice-Gerent to King <hi>Edw.</hi> A. 1346. <hi>John Kempe</hi> A. 1425. twice Chancellour, and
<hi>Tho. Young</hi> Lord Prefident of the North, A. 1561.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="London" type="diocese">
                              <head>LONDON.</head>
                              <p>The Epitaph on the Monument of <hi>William Biſh.</hi> of London (ſometime ſince to be ſeen in St. <hi>Pauls</hi>) ſpake him one of the Privy Council to the Conquerour. <hi>Mauritius</hi> Chancellour under the ſame King. <hi>Euſtachius de Fauconbridge</hi> one of
<hi>Rich.</hi> 1. Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtices, Chancellour of the Exchequer.
<hi>Treaſurer</hi> of England, and twice Embaſſ. into France. <hi>Hen. de Wingham</hi> Chancel. under <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>Ralph Baldoc</hi> under
<hi>Edw.</hi> 1. <hi>Rich. Bintworth</hi> under <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. <hi>Robert Braibrook</hi> under <hi>Rich.</hi> 2. <hi>Rich. Cox,</hi> Dean of
<hi>Weſtminſter</hi> (whom I crave leave to n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>me here as belonging to the Dioceſſe) of the Privy Council to <hi>Edw.</hi> 6. And Bancroft ſent Embaſſadour to Embden to treat with the King of Denmarks Commiſſioners, A. 1600.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="Durham" type="diocese">
                              <head>DURHAM.</head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Geoffry Rufus</hi> Chancel. of England, A. 1140.
<hi>Rich. de Mariſco</hi> A. 1217. <hi>Antony Beak</hi> of the Privy Council A. 1294. <hi>Rich. de Bury</hi> Chancel. A. 1334. and Treaſurer A. 1336.
<hi>Thom. Langley</hi> Chancell. A. 1406. <hi>Thomas Ruthal</hi> of the Council to <hi>Hen.</hi> 8. <hi>and as his Monument at</hi> Weſtminſter
<hi>teſtifies, Secretary to Hen.</hi> 7. <hi>Rich. Neyle</hi> of the Privy Council A. 1627. And here I muſt not
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:40451:23"/>omit that known paſſage of
<hi>Neubrigenſis,</hi> who brings in K. <hi>Rich.</hi> making himſelf merry with the Biſh, boaſting what a feat he had done, <hi>è vetuſto Epiſcopo novitium Comitem mirus ego artifex feci,</hi> to make a new Count of an old Biſhop, a Priviledge, till the late In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terruption, continued to that See.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="Winchester" type="diocese">
                              <head>WINCHESTER.</head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Swithun</hi> Chancellour of Engl. under K.
<hi>Egbert,</hi> A. 860. <hi>Will. Giffard</hi> Chancel. under the Conquerour,
<hi>Rufus,</hi> and <hi>Hen.</hi> 1. <hi>Peter de la Roche,</hi> Lord chief Juſtice under K. <hi>John. John Sendal</hi> Chancel. A. 1316. <hi>Will. Edendon</hi> Treaſurer under <hi>Edw.</hi> 3d. <hi>Will.</hi> of
<hi>Wickham</hi> (Founder of New Coll. in Oxon) Principal Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary,
<note place="margin">Vita Wainflet.</note> keeper of the Privy Seal, Mr. of the Wards, and Treaſurer of the Kings Revenues in France, A. 1360. <hi>Will. Wainflet</hi> (Found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Magdalene Coll. Oxon) for his great wiſdom, and Integrity long Chancel. of Engl. under <hi>Hen.</hi> 6.
<hi>Rich. Fox</hi> (Founder of C. C. C. Oxon) one of the Privy Council to
<hi>Hen.</hi> 7th. (as Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent a Prince, as this Nation has known) and continually imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed either in matters of Counſel at home, or Embaſſies abroad.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="Ely" type="diocese">
                              <head>ELY.</head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Will. Lang-champ.</hi> Chancellour A. 1189, then chief Juſtice and Protector of the Realm, when <hi>Rich.</hi> 1. undertook his voyage to the Holy-Land. <hi>Euſtachius</hi> Chancellour A. 1196.
<hi>John Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tham</hi> Chancellour A. 1326, (as <hi>Spelm.</hi>) 1317. as
<hi>Godwin</hi>) <hi>Simon Langham</hi> A. 1361. firſt Treaſurer, then Chancel. of Eng. <hi>John Barnet</hi> Treaſurer A. 1366. <hi>John Fordham</hi> Treaſurer A. 1385. <hi>Will. Gray</hi> Treaſurer A. 1469.
<hi>John Alcock</hi> Chancel. A. 1486. and <hi>Tho. Goodric</hi> Chancel. under
<hi>Edw.</hi> 6.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="Lincoln" type="diocese">
                              <head>LINCOLNE.</head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Robert Bluet</hi> Chancel. under the Conquerour A.
1092. <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> under <hi>Hen.</hi> 1. cheif Juſtice of Engl.
<hi>Galfridus</hi> Chancel. A. 1180. <hi>Hugh de Wells</hi> Chancel. A. 1209.
<hi>Walt. de Conſtantiis</hi> Chancel. under <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. And Dr.
<hi>Williams</hi> Dean of Weſtminſter, and after Biſhop of this See, made Lord Keeper by the Learned King <hi>James.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="Coventry and Lichfield" type="diocese">
                              <head>COVENTRY &amp; LICHFIELD.</head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Roger de Wiſeham</hi> Keeper of the Great Seal, A. 1245. <hi>Walter de Langton</hi> Treaſurer, A. 1226. <hi>Roger Northbrough</hi> Clerk of the Wardrobe, afterwards Treaſurer, A. 1322.
<hi>Geoffry Blyth,</hi> Lord
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:40451:23"/>Preſid. of Wales, A. 1512.
<hi>Rowland Lee</hi> his Succeſſour the ſame A. 1535 and <hi>Rich Sampſon,</hi> A. 1537.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="Salisbury" type="diocese">
                              <head>SALISB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RY.</head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Oſmond</hi> Chancel. of Engl. alwaies of the Privy Council, and ſeldome ſpared from Court, under the Conquerour.
<hi>Roger</hi> Chancel. A. 1107. and under King <hi>Stephen</hi> A. 1136.
<hi>John Waltham</hi> Maſter of the Rolls, Keeper of the Privy Seal, and after Treaſurer of Engl. under <hi>Richard</hi> the Second. <hi>Nicholas Bubwith</hi> Treaſurer A. 1407. <hi>William Ayſcoth</hi> Clerk of the Council A. 1438.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="Bath" type="diocese">
                              <head>
                                 <hi>BATH</hi> and <hi>WELS.</hi>
                              </head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Robert Burnel</hi> firſt Treaſurer, then Chancellour of Engl. and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies of the Council under <hi>Edward</hi> the Firſt. <hi>John Drokensford</hi> Keeper of the Wardrobe, A. 1309. <hi>Robert Stillington</hi> firſt Keeper of the Privy Seal, then Chancel, A. 1465.
<hi>Oliver King</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Secretary, A. 1492. <hi>John Clerk</hi> Maſter of the Rolles, A. 1523.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="Exeter" type="diocese">
                              <head>EXETER.</head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Leofricus,</hi> Firſt one of the Privy Council, then Chancel. of Engl. under the Conquerour, though <hi>Spelman</hi> reckons him of Bath at that time. <hi>Will. Brewſter</hi> of the Privy Council, under
<hi>Hen.</hi> 3d. <hi>Walter Stapledon</hi> (Founder of Exeter Coll. Oxon) firſt of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy Council then Treaſurer under <hi>Edw.</hi> 2d. <hi>John Grandeſſon</hi> of the Privy Council to <hi>Edw.</hi> 3d. <hi>John Voyſeye</hi> Lord Preſident of Wales under <hi>Henry</hi> 8th. And
<hi>Gervaſe Babington</hi> Vice-Preſident of Wales A. 1597.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="Norwich" type="diocese">
                              <head>NORWICH.</head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Henry</hi> the Second by a a ſpecial Commiſſion makes the Biſhops of Norwich, Wincheſter, and Ely, Lord Chief Juſtices, in my Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors words Archi-Juſtitiarios (<hi>Radulfus de Diceto</hi>) And tis added Clergy-men were pitch'd upon as the likelieſt perſons, not to op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the poor, nor reſpect the face of the Rich.
<hi>John Salmon</hi> Chancel. A. 1319. <hi>Robert Baldoc</hi> Chancel. A. 1324.
<hi>John Wakering</hi> Keeper of the Privy Seal, A. 1416.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="Hereford" type="diocese">
                              <head>HEREFORD.</head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Thom. Cantilupe</hi> Chancel. A. 1275. <hi>Thom. Charlton,</hi> Treaſurer A. 1329. <hi>John Gilbert</hi> A. 1386. <hi>Thom. Milling</hi> of the Privy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil to <hi>Edw.</hi> 4th. <hi>Charles Booth</hi> Chancellour of the Marches of Wales A. 1517.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="Worcester" type="diocese">
                              <pb n="46" facs="tcp:40451:24"/>
                              <head>WORCESTER.</head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Galfridus Gifford</hi> Chancel. A. 1267.
<hi>Walter Reynald</hi> firſt Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurer, then Chancel. under <hi>Edw.</hi>
2d. <hi>John Barnes</hi> Treaſurer A. 1362. <hi>Hen. Wakefield</hi> Treaſurer A. 1376. <hi>Nicholas Heath</hi> Lord Preſid. of Wales and Chancel. of Engl. under Q. <hi>Mary.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="Chichester" type="diocese">
                              <head>CHICHESTER.</head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Ralph Nevil</hi> Chancel. A. 1222. (<hi>Spel.</hi>
26) who addes that he was appointed by Parliament. <hi>John de Langton</hi> Chancel. under <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. and 2d. <hi>John Stratford</hi> A. 1360.
<hi>Adam Molins</hi> Clerk of the Council, A. 1451. and that incomparably learned Prelate, and induſtrious Preacher <hi>Lan. Andrews,</hi> Privy Counſellour of Engl. and Scotl. under a Prince that knew the worth of Learning, and advanced it accordingly.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="Rochester" type="diocese">
                              <head>ROCHESTER.</head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Walter de Merton</hi> (Founder of the Colledge that beares his Name) 2: Chancel. A. 1274. <hi>John de Shepey</hi> Treaſurer, A. 1358.</p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="Oxford" type="diocese">
                              <head>OXFORD.</head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Hugh Curwyn</hi> Chancel. of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
                              </p>
                           </div>
                           <div n="St Davids" type="diocese">
                              <head>St. <hi>DAVIDS.</hi>
                              </head>
                              <p>
                                 <hi>Adam Houghton,</hi> Chancel. A. 1376.
<hi>Linwood</hi> the famous Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noniſt, Keeper of the Privy Seal, A. 1440. and imployed in Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſies to the Kings of Spain, Portugal <hi>&amp;c.</hi> I might here ſubjoyn, ſeveral Deanes, and Arch-Deacons promoted to the ſame Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,
<note place="margin">Stow.</note> and take notice, that till the Diſſolution of Abbyes, the Prior of Chriſt-Church in London, was euer a Member of the Court of Aldermen: and that the Dean of Weſtminſter is by his Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter allowed no ſmal Influence upon the Government of that City. But I ſhall not nauſeate the Reader with any more hard Names, only obſerve, that in the Catalogue of Chancellours, recorded in <hi>Spelmans Gloſſary,</hi> amounting to about 170, near 100. of them were <hi>Clergy men, more then all the other Profeſſions put together can make up</hi>
                              </p>
                           </div>
                        </div>
                     </body>
                  </floatingText>
               </p>
               <p>Theſe then are the Honours, which (if any humane Teſtimony can make a thing certain) an uninterrupted Cuſtome, (equall to Law) which Wiſe Antiquity gave them through all the <hi>Saxon, Danes,</hi> and
<hi>Norman</hi> times without controul, or diſpute, till with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in theſe 20 years, ſince which <hi>England</hi> has groaned under this ſin of deſpiſing the Embaſſadours of Chriſt, and it has been <hi>no ſmall
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:40451:24"/>ſtep to Preferment to rail upon them,</hi> murmure, and decry their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement, and to rank the great <hi>Truſtees of Souls with the vileſt Peaſants in the Nation.</hi> As if there were no better way to ſhew <hi>love</hi> to their Redeemer, then by <hi>hatred to his ſervants,</hi> and <hi>reſpect</hi> to the Majeſtie <hi>of God muſt be evidenced by powring contempt upon ſuch as Repreſent his Perſon.</hi> Thus <hi>Corah,</hi> and his Accomplices grand grievance, and complaint againſt <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> was, that they were too high, took too much upon them, <hi>Numb.</hi> 16. They were advanced, and honoured above the reſt, this was the main eye ſore; but the revenging hand of God would not bear it. Nay have we not had more of the ſame Language, <hi>All the Congregation is holy, and one may preach</hi> as well as another. Thus would theſe <hi>ſons of confuſion</hi> have brought all to a <hi>Munſter Diſorder,</hi> by taking away the <hi>Diſtinction of Callings.</hi> The Wiſe God appointed it other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe under the Old Teſtament, when every one was not admitted to the Prieſthood. I cannot but think there were 1000 in Iſrael that knew how to <hi>kill, flay, and dreſſe an Ox, Sheep, or Goat, as artificially as the ſons of</hi> Levi, yet none attempted it (in reference to the Altar) without a rebuke. And was <hi>Moſes</hi> a more prudent ſteward then Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>the Wiſdom of the Father?</hi> Would it be ſuffered in Humane Societies, any well regulated Corporation, that every man who conceived himſelf fitter to diſcharge an Office, manage a Trade, husband an Eſtate, ſhould preſently ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude another legally poſſeſt, and invade his Propriety? Grant this, and <hi>farewell Government, wellcome</hi> Babel.</p>
               <p>Let me ſpeak it once for all, tis <hi>folly to expect the proſperity of the Nation,</hi> whileſt the <hi>Clergy are in miſery;</hi> whileſt the Sacred Function is with <hi>black ingratitude</hi> reviled, to whoſe <hi>learned La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours</hi> we owe the Tranſlation of our Bibles, and who (under God) were the Principal inſtruments of freeing us from that Egyptian Darkneſſe our fore-fathers ſate in. Is not this like the Deere
<hi>Plutarch</hi> ſpeaks of, who browſed on that Buſh in a Clam, that he was glad to creep under in a ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orm? Certainly they are not to be eſteemed worthy the name of Chriſtians, or Friends unto the Goſpel, (whatever pretences they make) that deſpiſe, and vilifie the Miniſtry, then which nothing beſpeaks a more vile, and reprobate Heart. <hi>Ignatius</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">Epiſt, ad Tral.</note> deals roundly with ſuch, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, they are down-right
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:40451:25"/>Atheiſts, and make nothing of Chriſt, ſaies that holy man; and tis much to be ſuſpected (if they would ſpeak their thoughts) that too many (with <hi>Leo</hi> 10.) look upon Religion as no other then a Fable, and (with <hi>Servetus)</hi> make our Meſſiah the third Impoſtor. We know that under the Law, preſumptuouſly to riſe againſt the Prieſt, was puniſhable with no leſſe than death, <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. For theſe are the Embaſſadours of the King of Heaven, and how
<hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred</hi> ſuch perſons are by the Law of Nations, all Hiſtories do abundantly witneſſe, and that ſmall Indignities offerd them, are highly reſented the <hi>Ammonites</hi> are a laſting Teſtimony 2. <hi>Sam.</hi>
10.
<note place="margin">Florus.</note> and proud <hi>Corinth</hi> for no other reaſon burnt to Aſhes by the enraged Romans.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>The Clergies moderate engaging in ſome Civil Affairs pleaded for, and justified.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>BUt tis feared the former Diſcourſe has given offence to ſome <hi>prejudiced parties,</hi> therefore to remove that ſtumbling block, and to make way for what follows, twill be requiſite a little to enquire into that perplext, and long-debated Point, <hi>Whether and how far Spiritual Perſons (with a Salvo to their Function) may inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meddle with Temporal Matters.</hi> And that this has bin no new thing, or peculiar to England (which was never eſteemed the <hi>Paradiſe of Prieſts,</hi> as the report goes of <hi>Leige</hi>) is manifeſt to every one that is the leaſt acquainted with Sacred, or Prophane, Ancient or Modern ſtories. If you examine the Pagan Records; Amongſt the old <hi>Gauls</hi> and <hi>Britains,</hi> the
<hi>Druids</hi> upon the matter managed all af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs: <hi>De omnibus ferè Controverſiis publicis privatiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> conſtituunt, &amp; ſiquid admiſſum Facinus, ſi caedes facta, ſi de haereditate, de Fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Controverſia, iidem decernunt.</hi> All Actions Real, and Perſonal, all Cauſes about Life and Death were brought before them as
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Caſ. Com.
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 6.</note> one aſſures us, who had reaſon to know them. NOr did the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy of the wiſe <hi>Egyptians</hi> vary, for <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <hi>Aelian</hi>
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Var. Hiſt. l.</hi> 14 <hi>c.</hi>
34.</note> witneſſes. And that the Perſian
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:40451:25"/>
                  <hi>Magi</hi> had the higheſt Seats of Judicature, were ever Privy Counſellours, and intereſted in publick Tranſactions Philoſtratus
<note n="*" place="margin">L. 1. de Vit. Apollon.</note> informs us. Twere eaſie to make this good by a particular enu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meration of all other Countries; but I leave the Heathens and proceed to the <hi>Mahometans,</hi> with whom what prodigi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Power the Ancient <hi>Caliphs</hi> of
<hi>Babylon</hi> had, and others ſtill retain, any one that will but take the pains to look into <hi>El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macinus Hiſt. Sarac.</hi> publiſht by
<hi>Erpenius</hi> may ſoon receive ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction.</p>
               <p>If we look amongſt Gods own People, before the Prieſthood was confined to a Tribe, ſome 2500 years, the <hi>Firſt-born</hi> was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted both with Religious Worſhip, and the Adminiſtration of Juſtice, <hi>Moſes</hi> being Prieſt as well as Ruler. And that he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed the Prieſts Over-ſeers of all things, Judges of Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſies, and Puniſhers of Malefactors: Joſephus, who ſaw the Precept reduced to Practice, tells us expreſly <hi>L.</hi> 2. <hi>contr. App.</hi> Then who knows not that <hi>Ely</hi> and <hi>Samuel,</hi> the Lords Prieſts were at the ſame time Civil Judges in Iſrael. <hi>Chytraeus</hi> makes three Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtories among the Jews, of all which the Prieſts were principal, and eſſential Members, 1. a Triumvirat in every City, wherein mony matters, and lighter treſpaſſes were decided,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Grot. in</hi> 5 <hi>Ma.</hi> 21.</note> theſe <hi>Grotius</hi> ſtyles <hi>Pedaneos Judices.</hi> 2. The little Synedrium conſiſting of 23. wherein Capital Cauſes were determined in the Gates of every City. 3. The Council of State, or Grand Senat of 70 Elders which ſome make to conſiſt of 71 taking in <hi>Moſes,</hi> others of 72.6. out of each Tribe, the High-Prieſt being commomly of the number) with the Elders excelling in wiſdom and I earning, choſen out of the Levites, and Aſſiſtants out of all Iſrael. Now that the Prieſts and Levites were elected into this Great Sane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drim as well as the Princes, if I ſay before them
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Exercit.</hi> 13. c. 5.</note>
                  <hi>Caſaubon</hi> will bear me out, who makes it appear out of their beſt Authors, <hi>quod hujus Concilii ea fuit Inſtitutio ut ſifieri poſſit,</hi> è ſolis Sacerdotibus &amp; Levitis conſtaret. The Conſtitution of this ſtanding Council was ſuch, that as neer as might be, the endeavour was it might conſiſt only of the Prieſts and Levites: whence <hi>Joſephus</hi> and <hi>Philo</hi> oftentimes under the title of Prieſts underſtand the Sanedrim.
<note n="*" place="margin">Philo de vit. Moſ.</note>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. To which I might adde that Political Axiom mentioned by
<hi>Joſephus</hi> as derived from <hi>Moſes,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:40451:26"/>The King was ever to take the advice of the Prieſt. See <hi>Schickard de Ju. Reg. Theorem.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>Come down to <hi>David,</hi> whoſe Government was a Pattern to all his Succeſſours. His Raign was peaceable and flouriſhing, nor did he want Statesmen of the moſt raiſed abilities for his imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. Yet did not this Wiſe, this Holy Prince think it incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with the Sacred Function (which yet St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> tells us was <hi>Operoſius Miniſterium</hi> in ſome reſpect then that of the Goſpel) to engage Levites in his weightieſt Secular Charges. Thus we find <hi>Hathaliah,</hi> and his Brethren appointed Officers on this ſide Jordan, not only in all buſineſſes of the Lord, <hi>but in the ſervice of the King.</hi> And
<hi>Jerijah</hi> another in holy Orders is made Ruler (Plenipotentiary) over the Reubenites, the Gadites, and the half Tribe of Manaſſeh for every matter pertaining to God, and tis added <hi>the Affairs of the King likewiſe,</hi> 1. Chron. 26.30.32. Nor was he ſingular in it, but is imitated by good <hi>Jehoſaphat,</hi> who made the Levites and the Prieſts Judges of all the Controverſies in Iſrael, not excluding matters of blood.
2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 19.8.10. Now run over the Catalogue of all the Kings of
<hi>Iſrael,</hi> there are hardly any to be paraleld, I am ſure none that went beyond theſe: None whoſe Government did more proſper with righteouſneſs, Juſtice, and Tranquillity. And though under the reſt of the Kings we have no expres mention of the ſame practice, yet all things con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered, we have more reaſon to conclude it held then the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: for we find <hi>Jehoiada</hi> the Prieſt chief Counſellour to
<hi>Joaſh,</hi> 2. <hi>King.</hi> 11. Look into Later times, after the Babylonian Capti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, the Prieſts command all, and poſſeſſe the Scepter for ſome 100 of years; the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Joſeph. L.</hi> 13. <hi>c.</hi>
9.</note> 
                  <hi>Aſſamonaean</hi> Race being abſolute Princes till
<hi>Pompey</hi>'s Conqueſt. I might farther remark, that many Civil Cauſes are by name reſerved to the Levitical Cognizance, as Inquiſition for Murther, falſe witneſſe, &amp;c. <hi>Deut.</hi> 21. Yet do not the Preachers of the Goſpel pretend the leaſt to theſe priviledges, though, methinks, making fit allowance to the difference of times and perſons, the model preſcribed by God himſelf may ſafely be followed in ſome circumſtantials.</p>
               <p>But leaving <hi>Moſes</hi> let us come to Chriſt, and ſee how Matters ſtood under the Goſpel. Here though we have no inſtances in the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:40451:26"/>New Teſtament of Honours conferred upon the Apoſtles, yet have we Propheſies (unfullfild till then) that the world ſhould be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, Kings become Nurſing-Fathers, and the feet of ſuch as brought glad tiding be beautiful; which
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Com. in</hi> 49.
<hi>Eſai.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Calvin</hi> and others apply to the bounty and Munificence of Princes to the Church. For the firſt 300 yeares, what could rationally be expected from profeſſed enemies, whileſt the Perſecutig fury laſted, whileſt every Country <hi>flamed
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Taedâ lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cebis in illâ, qua ſtantes ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, qui fixo gutture fuman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> Juven.</note> with</hi> living <hi>fires, and diſmal ſights of burning Chriſtians: in this calamitous deplorable eſtate, no other honour could be lookt for ſave that of Martyrdome.</hi> But no ſooner was Gentiliſme aboliſhed, then we have a new <hi>ſmiling face of affaires,</hi> under the happy Raign of <hi>Conſtantine, the Churches Patron, and the Glergies Friend.</hi> And henceforth the Primitive Piety was not wanting, who thought no Honours, no powers miſplaced upon their ſpirituall Fathers, for whom they judged nothing too dear. All Hiſtories ring of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantines</hi> Kindneſs to the Clergy; by whom the moſt weighty af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires of the Empire, in his daies were happily tranſacted. And moſt of his Succeſſors wrote after the ſame Copy.</p>
               <p>It were eaſy to muſter a little army of holy Fathers engaged in ſecular imployments, We read in <hi>Zozomen l.</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 32. that <hi>Epiphanius</hi> Biſhop of the Metropolis of Cyprus a perſonof ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar vertue, Prudence, and Piety <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, was buſied in Political matters. <hi>Theodoret l.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 30. reports the like of one <hi>Jacobus</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Niſibis,</hi> or <hi>Mygdonian Antioch,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Theodor. <hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 13.</note> that he was <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, Biſhop, Governour and Captain of the ſame City. Nay the warlike habit of <hi>Euſebius</hi> Biſhop of
<hi>Samoſata</hi> is commended by the ſame Authour, the Church receiving benefit by it. And <hi>Baronius</hi> mentions <hi>John</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarch of
<hi>Alexandria,</hi> A. 610. that twice in a week his manner was to ſit and Judge between thoſe that were at variance, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concile them: Once when none came to him, he departed weep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that all the day he had done no good; but <hi>Sophronias</hi> replied that he had more need rejoyce, having brought the City to ſuch order and peace, that they were more like Angels then men, have<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing no differences left. A rare example to the <hi>immortal credit of an Eccleſiaſtical Judge,</hi> Sir <hi>Thomas Moore</hi> commanded it to be ſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red up as a wounder when he had cleared one
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Sir</hi> Thomas Moores
<hi>life.</hi>
                  </note> Court, but here's a populous City, (hardly ſhort of any in this nation) reduced to a <hi>perfect Vnity.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:40451:27"/>
               <p>But I ſhall paſſe by ſuch obſcure Names, whom twere endleſs to reckon up, &amp; ſelect only a few, whoſe <hi>eminent Labours</hi> have <hi>Eterni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed them to Posterity.</hi> Ile begin with St.
<hi>Ambroſe,</hi> who floriſhed <hi>A.</hi> 378. and to his conduct, and prudence was the entire goverment of the great City of <hi>Milain</hi> entruſted. S. <hi>Auſt.</hi> complaining that he was a long time kept from acceſſe to him,
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Confeſ l.</hi> 6. <hi>c</hi>
3</note> 
                  <hi>ſecludentibus me ab ejus aure, atque ore Catervis negotioſorum hominum, quorum infirmitatibus ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viebat,</hi> whole troopes of Suitours about him, to diſpatch their worldly buſines. The next ſhall be
<hi>Cyril</hi> Patriarch of <hi>Aelxandria,</hi> who beſides the overſight of the Clergy, had the
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Soc. l.</hi> 7. c. 7.</note> management of Temporal affaires in the City. Though tis confeſſed the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian paſſes ſome cenſure upon it, but the Reaſon is eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered, becauſe his <hi>Darling</hi> Novatians were a litle retrench'd by it. The Third ſhall be the great <hi>African</hi> Light St.
<hi>Auſtin,</hi> who Ep. 147. has this paſſage. <hi>Homines quidem ſuas ſeculares cauſas apud nos finire cupientes, dum iis neceſſarii fuerimus, ſic nos Sanctos &amp; Dei ſervos appellant, ut negotia Terrae ſuae peragant, aliquando aga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus negotia &amp; ſalutis ipſorum, non de Auro, non de Argento, non de fundis &amp; pecoribus, pro quibus rebus quotidie ſubmiſſo Capite ſaluta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mur, ut Diſſentiones hominum terminemus.</hi> He was every day ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licited to make up ſome breaches about Cold, Silver, Land, Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Yet where ſhall we find a more painful Preacher then this Father, where any more engaged in conteſts with Hereticks, or any that left a larger Legacy of his learned Labours to the Church? My laſt inſtance ſhall be <hi>Gregory</hi> (with whom ſome cloſe the good Popes) who makes ſad moan,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Greg. mag. Ep.</hi> 5.</note> 
                  <hi>ſub colore Epiſcopatus ad ſaeculum retractus ſum, in quo tantis terrae curis inſervio, quantis me in vità Laicâ nequaquam deſerviſſe reminiſcor.</hi> He was never in all his life, ſo incumbred with worldly buſineſſe as after he came to be a Biſhop. But afterward she addes,
<hi>etſi cogamur ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renis negotiis intendere, mens tamen noſtra ſaeculari varietate non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectetur, ſed tota in unum currat, atque conſluat finem.</hi> Though he was forced to do this for the good of his people, yet he took no pleaſure in it, and his mind was taken up with better things. For all agree that theſe muſt not be undertaken out of love to them, but Chriſtian Charity <hi>Aust. de Civ. d. l.</hi> 19. <hi>c.</hi> 19. but compaſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on towards the Oppreſſed <hi>Greg. de Paſt. Cur. p. ſec. c.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p>Now theſe Imployments were conferred upon them, not as
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:40451:27"/>Biſhops, but as Subjects more eminently Qualified, withal the advantages of humane Literature: But <hi>Three</hi> there are in which they did principally engage, and which may ſeeme moſt agreea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to their Coat. Firſt, to be in <hi>Commiſſion of the Peace,</hi> and to ſpeak impartially, who fitter for ſuch a work then they, whoſe buſines, whoſe ſtudy tis to reconcile thoſe that are at variance. And this was the great Deſign of the Ancients, though it began at firſt in a way of Charity, yet being found profitable twas upon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture deliberation by the Chriſtian Emperours confirmed, judging no perſons more likely to advance the publick ſervice in this ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity, then here and there ſome choice Eccleſiaſticks, whoſe in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection would both quicken, and awe the Laity. This being then an approved Maxime, <hi>None ſo proper to make Peace, as they whoſe duty tis to Preach Peace.</hi> All I wiſh is, that the covetuous feares of ſome intereſted perſons, jealous <hi>Leaſt ſuch a Chriſtian unexpenſive ending of differences ſhould keep their Courts, too empty &amp;c. give not a check to the Reviving ſo Primitive, ſo hopefull a cuſtome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, To be of the <hi>Privy Council,</hi> where frequently Caſes of Conſcience, relating to State-matters may ariſe. As ſuppoſe there be a conſultation about a Warre with Foraign Nations, the lawfullneſs, or unlawfullneſs whereof muſt be judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>in Foro Conſcientiae,</hi> and the thing will not bear ſo much delay as to Summon the Prelates together for advice, nor Reaſon of State allow it to be ſo much publiſh'd. For want of ſuch Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Counſellours, Princes may oftentimes be raſhly entangled in unjuſt Maſſacres, and innocent blood be ſpilt. Now to prevent this, the Godly Prudent Princes, both of our own, and other Nations, have ever admitted ſome Spiritual Perſons to their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil Tables, and Cloſet-debates. Tis recorded of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Euſeb. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>it. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 35.
<hi>l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 56</note> that he would never diſpence with the abſence of ſome of his Biſhops, not at meales, <hi>making his Court as twere a Church,</hi> not in his journeyes, nay that he took them along with him in his War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Expeditions. And <hi>Pet. Bleſenſis</hi> in his 84.
<hi>Ep.</hi> to <hi>Alexander</hi> 3. excuſing the Biſhops of
<hi>Wincheſter, Ely,</hi> and <hi>Norwich,</hi> proves at large, that tis lawfull for Prelates to be in the Courts and Councils of Princes for ſundry important Reaſons.</p>
               <p n="3">3ly. To be imployed in publick <hi>Treaties and Negotiations of Peace,</hi> and this both the Antient, and Modern Practiſe will ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifie, that none have been more frequently, or more ſucceſſefully
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:40451:28"/>uſed in ſuch Meſſages, then the Embaſſadours of Chriſt. Solemn Embaſſies cannot be expected before the Magiſtrate imbraced the Goſpel. But in the very beginning of the fourth Century, we have <hi>Maruthas</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Meſopotamia</hi> ſent
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Scrat L.</hi> 7. <hi>L.</hi> 7.
<hi>c.</hi> 8.</note> Embaſſadour from the Emperour of Rome, to the King of Perſia. Preſently after <hi>Theodorick</hi> diſpatcht
<note n="*" place="margin">Eunod. Ticin Vit. Epiphan.</note>
                  <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Ticinum,</hi> or <hi>Pavia,</hi> to
<hi>Gunebald</hi> King of the <hi>Burgundians,</hi> who at his requeſt releaſed great numbers of poor Chriſtian Captives. Then we have S.
<hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe</hi> ſent by <hi>Valentinian</hi> to <hi>Maximus,</hi> that commanded the Bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſh Armies, to deſire peace, which he happily effected to the great contentment of his Maſter, <hi>Amb. Ep.</hi> 27. <hi>L.</hi> 5. where he likewiſe mentions a former Embaſſy. I might adde
<hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> imployed to treat with <hi>Gainas, Baronius: John</hi> Biſhop of Rome commiſſioned by
<note n="*" place="margin">Nicepho.</note> 
                  <hi>Theodorick</hi> to
<hi>Juſtin</hi> the Emperour, with multitudes of others. For the Moderns, the time would fail me to ſpeak of our own and the Neighbour Nations: for this continued the Univerſal Practiſe of Chriſtendom, <hi>till Sincerity gave place to Hypocryſie,</hi> and that new Definition of an Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour came up, that he was, <hi>Vir bonus peregrè miſſus, ad mentiendum Reip. causâ,</hi> a Good man ſent to <hi>Lye</hi> abroad for his Countries ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice. <hi>Then twas high time for theſe holy men to reſign up theſe im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments to others, that could ſwallow ſuch Camels.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus we have both Antient and Modern uſance on our ſide, the uninterrupted practiſe of the world for above 5000 years be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and under the Law, in the pureſt times ſince the Goſpel, all Records atteſting it both Pagan, Mahometan, Jewiſh, and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian: and none ever queſtioning it, but ſome late Innovators, though tis hoped, as we have caſt off <hi>the infallibility of Rome,</hi> we ſhall not now imbrace that of <hi>Geneva,</hi> or <hi>Scotland.</hi> We have heard <hi>Cyril, Ambroſe, Auſtin,</hi> not the leaſt amongſt the Aſiatick, Europaean, and African Fathers, with many other Worthies enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in Secular Imployments: and if it muſt be cenſured an error, <hi>Sit Anima mea cum Patribus:</hi> I am willing to caſt my Lot amongſt them; and though it be miſerable to be deceived by Authority, yet tis moſt miſerable not to be moved by Authority, <hi>Aug. de <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>til. Cred,</hi> 6.16.</p>
               <p>Well then, that this <hi>de facto</hi> has been the uſage is evident, let us in the next place a little examine the <hi>Jus</hi> of it. And for any
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:40451:28"/>
                  <hi>Fanatick</hi> to except againſt it, is a <hi>Self-contradiction,</hi> ſince their avowed Principles allowed their Teachers to follow any other Calling, either of <hi>Camp, Country,</hi> or
<hi>City</hi> without controul, or imputation. But tis the <hi>rigid Diſciplinarian,</hi> that takes moſt offence at it, and therefore to him I ſhall addreſſe my ſelf. Ile ſuppoſe him to dwell in the little Common-wealth of Geneva, to be the beſt Head-piece among them, and ſhall only put this <hi>Dilemma</hi> to him. If the Senate, or Syndic ſhould commiſſion him to decide a difference between his quarrelling Neighbours, or ſend to adviſe with him about a war with their great enemy the <hi>Duke of Savoy,</hi> or engage him to ſollicit <hi>aid of the Court</hi> of
<hi>France</hi> as a Publick Agent, there being none likely to prevail but himſelf, and the City otherwiſe in danger to be loſt. In this caſe ſhould he be heard in pleading the inconſiſtency of his <hi>holy Profeſſion</hi> with ſuch an imployment, and thereupon return a denial; if ſo, the Magiſtrate is in a poor condition, who muſt be obeyed in nothing more ſave what the others Calling enjoyns him, whether commanded or no: and his being in <hi>Orders</hi> makes the Magiſtrate looſe the ſervice of a ſubject. Sure I am, both <hi>Calvin</hi> formerly, and
<hi>Henderſon</hi> of late, did not ſcruple greater matters. Nor can neceſſity be alleadged here, for if the thing be ſimply unlawful, we muſt not upon any tearms do evill, though the greateſt good may probably enſue. On the other ſide, if he may not decline it, <hi>then theſe two are not inconſiſtent,</hi> nor doth <hi>his Function incapacitate him</hi> for ſuch a work; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p>But let Matters be made never ſo clear, tis feared the Vulgar have taken up ſuch prejudices from the inexcuſable buſineſſe of ſome Black Coats intereſting the very Pulpits in State matters, during our late Troubles (a practiſe never ſufficiently to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned) that all muſt be bound to their good Behaviour for a while, for nothing but time will ſatisfie, and ſolve that Objection. Though tis hoped all Learned, and Judicious Perſons will be more conſiderate, and diſtinguiſh between the frantick madneſſe of a few giddy pates, &amp; the ſober actings of eminent Prelates commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioned by lawful Authority, and not take advantage from former miſcarriages, to bring an irreparable injury upon poſterity. But tis a true ſaying confirmed by the experience of many 100 years,
<hi>Profectò Laici ſemper ſunt inimici Clericis.</hi> When the World was
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:40451:29"/>Pagan, the Devil taught the multitude to cry out, if any calamity happened, that the fault was in the Chriſtians, <hi>and they muſt to the Lions:</hi> but now the cunning Sophiſter has changed the note, and if any thing be amiſſe either in Church or State, preſently the blame lights on the Clergy, <hi>they muſt be ſacrificed to appeaſe the many-headed Monſter, their Lands ſequeſtred, and all Places of truſt, and honour interdicted them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But let us in the laſt place a little view the Canonical Qualifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Biſhop. 1. Tis required that he be <hi>vitae probatiſſimae,</hi> of an upright unblameable Converſation, 2.
<hi>Nullius criminis reus,</hi> guilty of no crime, 3. <hi>aetate gravis,</hi> well ſtricken in years, 4. <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrinâ Praeſtans,</hi> excelling in Learning, with many other of the like nature. Now if theſe are not kept, they have the more to anſwer for, whom it concerns: if they be, will not any one that reads it conclude, no perſons more fit for the weightieſt affairs? For all Politico's make Integrity, Prudence, and Learning the prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal Ingredients to an accompliſht Magiſtrate, a compleat <hi>Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuoſo;</hi> ſo that if Aptitude be reſpected, I may ſafely affirm there are none better qualified for Counſel than the Clergy, whoſe Education has enabled them to look into all the <hi>Idea's,</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dels</hi> of Government, Search the depths and myſteries of Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires, moſt of which are lockt up in ſtrange Languages, and 'tis not every Capacity that can gain the Key. Then for true Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks (<hi>the late</hi> Florentine <hi>Reaches let others learn</hi>) theres as much to be found in the Hiſtorical part of the Scripture, as any books in the World; ſo that Divines may well be good Statiſts. And is it not pity their Country ſhould be deprived of ſuch admirable Abilities? Doubtleſſe thoſe of the contrary perſwaſion do not weigh the Conſequences of their Opinion, clearly tending to disjoyn the Church from being a part of the Common-wealth, which for 1300 years &amp; better have been happily united, if thoſe that are once in Orders muſt no longer be lookt upon as Citizens, but incontinently forfeit all their Priviledges; Of which more hereafter.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:40451:29"/>
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Some Scriptures, and Canons ſeemingly contradicting the former Poſition, explained.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>YEt for all this I confeſſe many good men are ſtrongly perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that Eccleſiaſticks ought wholly to be excluded from civil matters, an opinion much pretending to Humility and Self<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denial, and receiving ſome countenance, and colour from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the practiſe of the three firſt Centuries, and ſome Canons of Councils, which muſt be the ſubject of our next conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration.</p>
               <p>The Text that is moſt inſiſted upon is 2. <hi>Tim.</hi>
2.4. which being miſ-tranſlated by the vulgar Latine, <hi>militans Deo,</hi> begat greater prejudices in the minds of many.</p>
               <p>Firſt then one might take notice, that the Sentence is general, and belongs to every one, though in a more peculiar manner tis referred to the Preachers of the Goſpel, yet none can plead ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption: but others are willing to ſlip their necks out of the collar, and the Clergy only muſt be tyed to it, whom for the preſent we will grant to be principally concern'd. The ſtreſſe of all lies upon <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, which
<hi>Theophylact</hi> expounds by <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, the tumults and confuſions of this life. <hi>Cor. a Lapide</hi> ſaies, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> are ſuch imployments as concern food and raiment: and inſtances in theſe
<hi>mercatura, agricultura, &amp; artes mechanicae.</hi> Now who does not readily approve of this, and judge it very improper, that a Preacher ſhould be a Merchant, a Plowman, or a Mechanick, do not both Common and Canon Law forbid the ſame? <hi>Eſtius</hi> has much to the like purpoſe,
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. <hi>quae quis exercet ut habeat unde vivat,</hi> and quotes to this ſenſe a ſaying of <hi>Ambroſe, Indecorum eſt homines curare de cibo, qui militant Deo:</hi> this rather flies in the face of them that permit their Preachers to put on blew Aprons, and make them ſuch ſordid allowances, that they muſt either work with their
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:40451:30"/>hands, or ſtarve. Seeing tis not comely that the Lords Warri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ors ſhould buſie themſelves about inferiour matters, that tend to get a livelihood: And ſo <hi>Valla</hi> renders it, not
<hi>negotiis,</hi> but <hi>nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiationibus.</hi> When Chriſt imployed Fiſher men to preach his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel, weak inſtruments to confound the Powers of the world, though he furniſht them with ſuitable abilities, that they needed not to ſtudy, yet he made them leave their Nets, and not uſe them as an ordinary Profeſſion. <hi>Calvin</hi> ſaies that by the affairs of this life, the Apoſtle meant the care of governing and ordering a family, and ſuch ordinary imployments. If then we keep ſtrict and cloſe to the Letter, I ſee no remedy, but all muſt run into Cloyſters, and ſhake hands with the World: and we know what a concluſion the <hi>Rhemiſts</hi> draw hence, and what they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn as a ſpecial impediment to Church warfare. So that if from this the Clergy be denied, intermedling in any ſecular affairs, the next ſtep muſt be to forbid their marrying, which unavoidably brings with it many incumbrances and family-neceſſities, but this ſmells ſo rank of the Monk and Hermite, that I hope twill not be ſwallowed by any Proteſtant, and <hi>I did not believe the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Lake would ſo eaſily have mixed its waters with Tyber.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Apoſtle here makes a compariſon between prophane, and ſpiritual warfare, and the better to underſtand the genuine ſenſe we muſt conſider what Military Diſcipline did require. <hi>Vegetius L.</hi>
2. ſaies, that by the laws of war, he muſt not have any private affaires committed to him, nor mind his own gain. Hence we read the Romanes ſeverely proceeding againſt <hi>Poſthumius</hi> for imploying his ſouldiers to till his ground.
<note place="margin">Florus.</note> 
                  <hi>Vid. Legem Honorii &amp; Arcadii Tit. Nemo Miles.</hi> And <hi>Leo</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour ſaies expreſly, thoſe that are armed and maintained by the Common-wealth, muſt only mind publick affairs, and not till the ground, keep Cattle, or traffick,
<hi>L. Milites. C. de Re militari L.</hi> 12. All avocations were inhibited, and ſuch Matters as tended to the publick good injoyned. And why ſhould not the ſame analogy hold here, and ſuch affairs be permitted to the Clergy as tend to the good of the Church, and the glory of their great Commander.</p>
               <p>Next we are urged with the Apoſtles practiſe, who were ſo tender of any interruption, that they denied to attend upon Tables, and make proviſion for the poor, Tis true, in the Infancy
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:40451:30"/>of the Church, when the Goſpel was to be publiſh'd all the world over, the work great, the labourers exceeding few, not one to every Country, the leaſt diverſion at ſuch a time would prove a conſiderable hinderance, and diſtraction to them. But when the Lord of the Harveſt has increaſed the number, and plentifully furniſh'd his peaceable ſetled Church, every Village being now ſupplyed, and if the complaints of ſome be true, the nation ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſtock'd, that there is hardly imployment, much leſſe mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance for the multitude: In this caſe to make no difference of times, where the mercifull Providence of God has made ſo vaſt a diſtinction, ſeemes little agreeable to reaſon. But if from this, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion muſt be taken preſently to forbid every petty interruption and diſturbance, how came St. <hi>Paul</hi> to contradict himſelf, and to follow his Tent-making, labouring with his hands for a lively<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, which muſt needs take up a good part of his time, and hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his praying, and preaching. Adde to this, that the 7 <hi>Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons</hi> appointed by the Apoſtles to ſucceed them in the care of the Collections, were according to <hi>Epiphanius</hi> of the 70 Diſciples, yet for the publick benefit their conſtant preaching was now and then diſpenced with to attend on Tables.</p>
               <p n="3">3ly. We are threatned with ſeveral Canons roaring againſt it, but tis ſuppoſed upon ſearch, they will be found
<hi>falſely charged,</hi> and prove only <hi>bruta fulmina.</hi> And here I cannot but admire the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſty of the Primitive Church, and the charity of the people, the earneſtneſs of Princes in commiſſioning Spiritual perſons to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe all emergent differences, and the forwardneſs of the op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed in flying to their impartial Tribunals for Juſtice; wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the holy Fathers in proceſs of time thought it wiſdome to take off their Clergy from thoſe affaires, by ſundry ſevere Canons in many Councils.
'Twere eaſie to reckon up ſeveral prohibiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to this purpoſe out of
<hi>Balſamon, Zonaras, Bininus &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It would be an infinite task to give particular anſwers to each Canon, and therefore I ſhall lay down ſome generall Rules, which may much conduce to the better underſtanding of them all, and if well applyed may help to ſolve moſt.</p>
               <p>Firſt, Tis clear, the great deſign was to forbid
<hi>ambitious ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing after, and voluntary engaging</hi> in ſecular matters, for ſordid ends, and covetuous principles. And this may probably be col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:40451:31"/>becauſe we find a diſpenſation given, when impoſed by the ſupreame Magiſtrate: In the Council of
<hi>Sardis</hi> tis granted upon the motion of <hi>Oſius, Si relligioſi Imperatoris literis vel invitati, vel vocati fuerint,</hi> and undertaken in obedience, as cauſes of Piety and charity, overſeeing Widowes and Orphans, provided it extend not to the notorious neglect of their relligious callings. Thus <hi>Juſtin Martyr, Apol.</hi> 2. calls the Biſhop the great Steward of all the Poor, the contributions of the faithfull being laid down at his feet, and by him diſtributed. And <hi>Ignatius</hi> to <hi>Polycarp.</hi> that he was the great Truſtee of the widowes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Tis not ſo much a <hi>totall prohibition, as a prudent Reſtraint,</hi> leaſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimoſities, and jealouſyes ſhould ariſe in the Laity, by too much enchroaching upon their Courts, and therefore the wiſedome of ſundry Councils, confined the Clergy to ſuch matters as were properly of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical cognizance.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Third ground and reaſon of theſe interdictions, was not the unfitneſs and incapacity of Spiritual perſons, but out of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to their <hi>eminent callings,</hi> leaſt they ſhould be diſparaged by vile and mean imployments, and expreſſe mention is made of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did offices about Princes and Noble-men, as Stewards, Bailiſes <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But when by the favour of Princes, their imployments were honourable, and their temporary diverſions, did bring abundant re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence to the Church; we ſee thoſe that had the principall hand in enacting theſe Canons themſelves engaging. Now can it be ſuppoſed, if this had been the meaning, they would have been guilty of ſo groſſe a contradiction, and no future Council re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove it. <hi>Cyprian</hi> much confirmes me in this opinion, who <hi>l. de Lapſis,</hi> is perſwaded that God ſent the great perſecution under
<hi>Decius</hi> only to awaken the Chriſtians, who were grown exceeding corrupt, eſpecially the Clergy, for he complaines that the Biſhops themſelves abandoned their holy Functions, &amp; dealt in matters of the world, haunting Marts and Faires for filthy lucre ſake. And much to the ſame purpoſe we find in our own <hi>Bede, Gildas &amp;c.</hi> Now to beat down theſe enormities were ſo many Canons levelled.</p>
               <p>But to make peace between quarrelling nations, to compound differences amongſt Chriſtians and ſuch like, tending to the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God and the glory of the Goſpel, which may be often practiſed without Detriment to their ſpiritual charges, I never
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:40451:31"/>find theſe expreſly forbidden, or ſuch as ingaged in them, as <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril, Auſtin, Chryſoſtom, Gregory, Bernard &amp;c.</hi> condemned. For if St. <hi>Paul</hi> became all things to all men to gain a Soul, will not that example bear his Suceſſours out, if they go to the utmoſt verge of their Chriſtian liberty, ſtill keeping on this ſide ſin, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve Kingdomes, the Churches peace, and prevent the effuſion of Chriſtian blood: Their abſence ſome daies from their private charges will be abundantly recompenced by ſuch happy conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences.</p>
               <p n="4">4ly If the utmoſt rigour muſt take place, and no diſpenſation be granted, how ſhal we reconcile the ſevere Edicts of ſome Councils, whereby the Clergy are ſtrictly injoyned to take no care of their Families, but only and wholy to be intent upon reading, praying, and preaching (<hi>Carthagin.</hi> 4) with that of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounces ſuch a one worſe then an Infidel. All ſober men will allow them to provide, but not ſo as to neglect their holy Functi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and this holds as well in Civil, as Family affaires.</p>
               <p>Thus being out of Canon-ſhot, we may ſecurely proceed.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="clergy's titles" type="apology">
            <head>THE CLERGIES TITLES.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>IS the Obſervation of ſome that man comes into the world with his Face downwards, looking from God, and ever ſince his Nature was tainted by the fall, there remaines in him an indiſpoſition to good, and tendency to evil. Nov becauſe openly to fall fowle upon Religion it ſelf, would be cenſured as down right Atheiſm, therefore the devil has
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:40451:32"/>taught many a no leſſe effectuall, but much more ſecure way to begin with the Preachers of the Goſpel, to ſlight and vilifie them, to deny them any reverend or honorable title:
<hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> is expreſs to this purpoſe (in <hi>Pſal.</hi> 13) that Hereticks have learn'd from Satan not to give any names of honour to the Clergy, and all this under a ſpecious pretence of keeping them humble, that they may not grow proud. A hopefull deſign! and like well to doe the work: when we ſee <hi>Servus Servorum Dei,</hi> under the diſguiſe of this lowlineſs take more upon him, then Majeſty it ſelf, making euen Emperours kiſſe his Toe, and hold his Stirrup. But the ſpirit of God is not ſparing in aſſerting their juſt rights, and he might have done well, to forbear, if there had been any ſuch dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of puffing them up, they are ſtyled, the Lords Meſſengers, <hi>Hag.</hi> 1.13. <hi>Coworkers with God,</hi> 1 Cor. 3.6. <hi>Embaſſadours of God,</hi> 2 Cor. 5.20. Nor is any thing more common, then to entitle them <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi>
5.13. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.7.24. appellati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of honour given every where to Secular Dignity, and cannot be rendred into any vulgar language without borrowing from the Civil.</p>
            <p>Nay let me ſpeake it with reverence, never did Court-flattery atribute more ſwelling names to the proudeſt Potentate on earth, then the ſcripture does to Preachers of the Goſpel, ſtyling them Angels and Starres <hi>Rev.</hi> 1. Light of the world, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. and high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then which tis impoſſible to go, Gods, St. <hi>John</hi> 10.34. And
<hi>Hierom</hi> notes, that when St. <hi>Paul</hi> tearmes himſelf the Apoſtle of Jeſus Chriſt, he ſpeakes as loftily, as if he ſaid
<hi>Praefectus Praetorio Auguſt. Caeſar:</hi> Lord cheif Juſtice of
<hi>Auguſtus, Magiſter exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus Tiberii Caeſ.</hi> Generall of
<hi>Tiberius</hi> Armies. So that here I can not but complain with the learned
<hi>Mede</hi> of the Title <hi>Miniſter,</hi> as very incommodious, and improper for the Preachers of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, begetting an erroneous conceit in the vulgar, as if they were their ſervants, who may more truely be called their Maſters to teach them, and this is farther promoted by thoſe, who in their common diſcourſe uſe the language of <hi>ſerving</hi> ſuch or ſuch a <hi>Cure.</hi> But is it not a Soleciſme to call the ſhepherd the Sheepes Miniſter, or ſervant? To prevent this, he rather recommends the word <hi>Prieſt,</hi> being only the Evangelical Presbyter contracted: or if the long engroſſing of that by the Papiſts, have made it odious
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:40451:32"/>to nice eares, let Presbyter in the full ſound be retained, a word as ſoon, and as eaſily underſtood as Miniſter. But tis a difficult task to alter ſo rooted a cuſtom, and we may ſooner ſuggeſt what is expedient to be done, then find out a way to Reform it. Though it neerly concerns the Clergy in ſuch an Age as this to be cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, that they give not the leaſt occaſion, which may contribute to their own debaſing.</p>
            <p>I am not good at Heraldry, and therefore ſhall not take upon me to blazon the ſeveral Coats belonging to ſpiritual Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities. Only I cannot but remark, that the Canon Law calls Patriarchs
<hi>Super-Illuſtres,</hi> Arch-Biſh. <hi>Illuſtres,</hi> Biſhops
<hi>Spectabiles,</hi> Doctors <hi>Clariſſimos.</hi> Nay
<hi>Chaſtanaeus</hi> proves out of the <hi>Clemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines,</hi> that the Title of <hi>Sereniſſimus</hi> belongs to the Biſhop. But I ſhall not follow the wild extravagancies of theſe men, whoſe ſordid flattery giving too much to the Clergy, has made others unwilling to give any at all, at leaſt not their Due.</p>
            <p>Let us paſſe on to thoſe we can better rely upon. <hi>Leo Africa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> aſſures us, that the <hi>Moores</hi> call many of their Eccleſiaſticks Scriphs, <hi>i. e.</hi> Noblemen. The Hebrews had no higher name then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to ſpeak Honour and reſpect, frequently applyed to God himſelf, to Kings and Princes both of their own and other Nations, the <hi>Philiſtine</hi> Lords being called by it, <hi>Joſh.</hi>
13. yet you find <hi>Obadiah,</hi> Controller of the Kings Family, and one that feared God, accoſting the poor Prophet <hi>Elijah</hi> in that Language, 1.
<hi>King.</hi> 18.7. and his ſervant <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſaluted with the ſame ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation, 2. <hi>King.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>The moſt Honourable name the <hi>Greeks</hi> had was
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and yet how familiar is this in the New Teſtament: and if Antiquity may come in to explain it, there are no expreſſions more frequent to writers both of the firſt and middle ages concerning Biſhops, then <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, which if a man ſhould render moſt holy and Honoured Maſters, twould hardly conſiſt with the State attributed to them, even in thoſe early daies, where the Conſecration of a Biſhop is ſtyled ſitting on a Throne. Now the Modeſty of the Ancients did receive theſe Titles of Honour without ſtain of pride, or blemiſh to their Humility, having Chriſt for their pattern, who approves his Diſciples calling him Lord and Maſter. Goſpel meekneſſe may well ſtand
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:40451:33"/>with an Honorable Title, and no wiſe man will be puft up with an aery ſound. Tis the affecting of it then that Chriſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns, when he forbids any to call his Diſciples Maſter. <hi>Mat.</hi>
23. otherwiſe, if the letter be urged, all of us muſt turn Quakers, and ſhake hands with civility. <hi>Honour thoſe that are over you,</hi> Phil.
2. and what leſſe honour then in a word.</p>
            <p>Now does God command, and ſhall we ſcruple to give it, and cenſure them that receive it? What Barbarous impiety is it, to ſet ſo low a rate upon Learning and Religion, make them ſo ſervile, that no Appellation of Reverence or eſteem muſt be given the Profeſſours of them? Is it for the honour of England to grudge a ſmall title to the Paſtours of Souls, which all the Governours of our Bodies, and Eſtates enjoy without regret, which any common Artizan, that can but ſcrape together a little wealth, and is promoted to Office, is ſaluted with, and we ſaw of late was given to Brewers and Coblers, &amp;c. Is it for the Honour of England to court and reſpect the Embaſſadours of men, and to ſlight thoſe that repreſent the perſon of Chriſt, and rank them with the baſeſt Peaſants? Nor is this due to their perſons only; for let them be never ſo vicious, their Profeſſions may challenge it. For Jeſus Chriſt ſaith
<hi>Cyprian. L.</hi> 3. <hi>Ep.</hi> 19. yielded honour unto the Prieſts of the Jews, though they retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed neither the fear of God, nor knowledge of him, teaching us lawfully and fully to honour true Prieſts, by his behaviour unto falſe. And <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſpeaks roundly, <hi>Hom.</hi> 2. <hi>in Ep.</hi> 2. <hi>ad Tim.</hi> This is the cauſe of all evil, that the authority of Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Rulers is decayed, and no honour, no reverence, no fear yielded to them. He that is religiouſly affected to the Prieſts, will with greater piety reverence God: and he that deſpiſeth the Prieſt cometh by degrees to this, that he waxeth contumelious a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God himſelf.</p>
            <p>I know many are ſcandalized at the Lordlineſſe of our Biſhops, for no other reaſon then that it comes too near the Roman garb. But is it not a piece of folly, that every thing which carries with it the face of order, and decency muſt preſently be decried as ſuperſtitious and Antichriſtian: and all that defend it charged as friends to <hi>Rome, Caſſandrian,</hi> Grotian Papiſts. I muſt profeſſe, tis my perſwaſion, that the peeviſhneſſe of many Reformers car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:40451:33"/>them farther from Rome, then neceſſity required, and many profitable commendable things have been diſuſed by us, becauſe practiſed by them: but is it charitable is it rational to conceive that Church ſo full of errors, that it had not one dram of truth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining, that once pleaſant Garden of Chriſt ſo overrun with weeds, that it had not one good flower in it? I reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber Valentinus Gentilis made it a great argument againſt the Reformed Chuches, for that they agreed with the Papiſts in the Doctrine of the Trinity. But we muſt not tearm every thing Superſtitious that is believed or practiſed by the Church of Rome, no more then we do every thing Ceremonial, that we read of in uſe amongſt the Jews, who we know had cuſtoms Moral, as well as Levitical. I ſhall never therefore raſhly condemn any thing as Popiſh, meerly becauſe I find it amongſt them, unleſs Scripture, Antiquity, or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon induce me. Sure I am, <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> and <hi>Jewel,</hi> were never ſuſpected adherents to that party; yet ſee what Titles the former gives the later in the Preface to his Treatiſe of Ubiquity, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where in his Epiſtles.</p>
            <p>But I ſhall not waſte time and paper in contending for this, ſince if the <hi>Subſtance</hi> be once recovered (the Revenues, and Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction) this <hi>Shadow</hi> will ſoon follow.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="clergy's privileges" type="apology">
            <head>THE CLERGIES PRIVILEDGES.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The ancient Immunities of the Clergy, with their preſent State in other Nations.</hi>
               </head>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:40451:34"/>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Prudent Piety of the firſt Chriſtian Emperours for the better incouragement of Religion, and Learning, conferred many large Immunities and Exemptions upon Church-men, freeing them from Subſidies, Impoſitions, and ſundry Services where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with the reſt of their Subjects were burdened.
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Eccle. Hiſt. L.</hi> 10.
<hi>c.</hi> 7. <hi>Z<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>zom. L.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 9.</note> 
                  <hi>Euſebius</hi> and <hi>Zozomen</hi> record ſeveral Priviledges granted by <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> that thoſe who miniſter in holy Religion, be wholly free and exempt from all publick burthens. Nor were the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Franchiſes</hi> of our <hi>Britiſh</hi> Church ſhort either for number or extent, being all confirmed by Magna Charta without reſtraint. My Lord <hi>Cook</hi> acknowledges that the Clergy had more and greater liberties then other of the Kings Subjects, which to ſet down would ask a Volume; ſome few he recites, as that they were diſcharged from <hi>Purveyances, Tols, Cuſtoms, Diſtreſſes</hi> by the Sheriff in the old inheritance of the Church, with others of the like nature. But moſt of theſe are now loſt, and their condition reduced below the meaneſt Calling in the Nation. It would make a man mourn and weep, as often as <hi>He looks</hi> back upon the Charity of our Saxon Anceſtours, who in their greateſt Impoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons ever excuſed Eccleſiaſticks, no part of that inſupportable Tax of
<note n="*" place="margin">Spelm. Gloſ. V. Daneg.</note>
                  <hi>Danegelt,</hi> under which the Kingdom ſo much groaned, being paid by them, and till after the Conqueſt they were ever privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged. For
<note n="*" place="margin">Spelm. Con.</note> 
                  <hi>Ethelwolfe</hi> in a full Convention of his States at Wincheſter, A. 855. enacted that Tithes and Church-Lands throughout all his Dominions, ſhould be free from civil burthens and exactions, as much as Royal Tributes great and ſmal. But how ſtrangly has the Caſe been altered of late? How unequal were Contributions and Quarterings during our Inteſtine Wars? What heavy burthens did the poor Clergy bear? no Redreſſe to the bittereſt complaints being found from their Lay-Judges, who only made ſport at their miſery and oppreſſion, as if nothing were too bad for Black-Coats. Now thoſe daies, through mercy, are over, and muſt be forgotten, but ſtill to be wounded by the hand of their friends, and to receive the ſame hard meaſure from pretended well-wiſhers, that <hi>ſtrikes to the very heart.</hi> When no regard is had of all their paſt ſufferings, <hi>First-Fruits,</hi> Tenths (no ſmall ſtanding Revenue of the Crown, amounting as ſome com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:40451:34"/>to neer 40000. <hi>per an.</hi>) which they joyfully diſcharge, but they muſt ſtill be left to the arbitrary diſproportionat Impoſitions of every domineering inſolent Officer. The Conſideration hereof has convinced many (formerly of a different perſwaſion) that tis not onely uſeful, but expedient, but neceſſary to the Church to have ſome of its own order in power to protect them, and hear their juſt grievances. But what farther concerns our own Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, being ſo learnedly handled by the immortal <hi>Spelman,</hi> and the General ones ſo fully Collected by
<note n="*" place="margin">De Stud. pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vileg.</note>
                  <hi>Rebuffus</hi> and others, I ſhall not here inſiſt upon them.</p>
               <p>The grand Concern at preſent which I principally deſign, is, how far they were priviledged as to publick Aſſemblies, and State Conſultations. And that <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> with many other ſucceeding Emperours made uſe of their Advice both at home and abroad, imployed them in Embaſſies, and other Important Transactions has been allready demonſtrated. It now remains to ſee how they fared in other Places. And firſt, if ſuch an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument could hope to ſway with Chriſtians, it ſhould ſoon be proved, that thoſe, who attended the worſhip of the Heathen gods, were admitted into the Pan-Aetolium, and Amphictyonian Council, amongſt the <hi>Athenian</hi> Areopagites, and Roman Senators, that the old
<hi>Gauls</hi> divided their States
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Caeſ. Com. L.</hi> 6</note> in
<hi>Druidas</hi> (who had <hi>omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um Rerum immunitatem</hi>) <hi>Equites, Plebem,</hi> as the
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Strabo L.</hi> 17.</note>
                  <hi>Egyptians</hi> did into Prieſts, Soldiers, and Artificers. But leaving
<hi>Gentiliſme,</hi> I ſhall haſten to Chriſtendome. And here once for all premiſe, that by the Fundamental Conſtitutions of moſt Nations in
<hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope, Three Eſtates are generally ſetled,</hi> whereof <hi>the Clergy,</hi> or Prieſthood <hi>is ever one.</hi> Now to make this good, though I might produce variety of Inſtances, yet I ſhall content my ſelf with the ſingle Teſtimony of <hi>Calvin,</hi> knowing that it will go farther with many then a Jury of others. This we find expreſſely aſſerted in that
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Inſtit. L.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 20.
<hi>Sect.</hi> 31.</note> Piece which ſome cry up next to the Writings of the Apoſtles, <hi>in ſingulis Regnis tres</hi> ſunt <hi>Ordines,</hi> which how to make up without the <hi>Spiritualty</hi> is beyond my skill. In our neighbour Nation of <hi>France</hi> the practice is notoriouſly known, the antient ſtyle of the Royall edicts alwaies running, as 'tis recorded of
<hi>Pepin A.</hi> 744. <hi>per conſilium Sacerdotum,
<note n="*" place="margin">Thuan. paſſim.</note> &amp; Optimatum ordinavimus, &amp; per conſilium Sacerdotum, &amp; Opti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matum Ordinavit Carolomannus.</hi> It might farther be noted, that
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:40451:35"/>Six Prelates here are <hi>Peeres</hi> of the Kingdome, Three of them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtyled <hi>Dukes</hi> &amp; three
<hi>Counts,</hi> though the whole number of the <hi>Pairie</hi> exceed not 12. As likewiſe that the Biſhop of <hi>Paris</hi> has a peculiar Indulgence of being preſent in every Court of that Royal City without exception.
<note place="margin">Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ppinus.</note> Look into <hi>Hungary</hi> there
<hi>Thwroczius</hi> informes us, that by the Fundamentall Lawes of K.
<hi>Stephen,</hi> the Biſhops <hi>in Concilio Regis Primi aſſiſtunt. Poland</hi> comes behind none in its Reverence to the Clergy, where the Arch-Biſhop of <hi>Gneſna</hi> is <hi>Primas Regni,
<note place="margin">Stanisl. Krzis. tanowick De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrip. Pol.</note> &amp; Princeps primus,</hi> whoſe Jurisdiction is not limited to the Spiritualty alone, but has the chief place in the rank of the Senators aſſigned him, the greateſt Authority in all Conſultations. And when at any time there happens an <hi>Inter-regnum</hi> (as it frequently may in thoſe <hi>Elec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> Kingdomes) it belongs to him to Summon a Dyet, to give Audience to Foraign Embaſſadors, and to appoint a time, and place for the choice of the new King. After him follow the reſt of the Eccleſiaſticks, who in the * <hi>Aſſemblies take place of all the Secular Nobles.</hi> My Authour farther enlarges this to have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from the Piety of the <hi>Poliſh</hi> Kings towards the Church, that the Sonnes of it, ſhould for ever have the higheſt Place in all Conventions, with many other Priviledges, which to this day they enjoy in his own words <hi>(No Clergy-man neither, but a Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yer) maximo illius Regni Commodo, Emolumento, Adjumento, addo &amp; Ornamento, Id. Cromerus</hi> addes, that there is ever a Royal ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Council</hi> aſſigned the King, of which number there are alwaies Two Arch-Biſhops and Seaven Biſhops. Then how conſiderable a number in all the <hi>German</hi> Dyets, the Eccleſiaſticks are
<note n="*" place="margin">L. de Comitiis
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mp.</note>
                  <hi>Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinius</hi> is a witneſs beyond exception, who reckons up 34. Biſhops that have their votes there, beſides Abbots, Priors &amp;c. who paſſe for Religious Perſons. And in the Septemvirate, we find no leſſe then 3 Clergy men, <hi>Ments</hi> Arch-Chancellour of <hi>Germany, Coln</hi> of France, and <hi>Triers</hi> of Italy. I ſhall wholy out of this Catalogue omit <hi>Spain</hi> and <hi>Italy,</hi> as being ſuch known Vaſſals to the Pope, where the Clergy rule the roaſt. But one word daſhes all this, <hi>they</hi> are <hi>Papiſts,</hi> which is argument enough to many to condemne a thing, though back'd by never ſo ſtrong reaſons. Let us examine how matters ſtand with others, who have no correſpondence with <hi>Rome. Andreas Bureus,</hi> in his deſcription of
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:40451:35"/>
                  <hi>Sweden,</hi> acknowledges that the Eccleſiaſticks were heretofore the <hi>prime men</hi> in the Senate, till the Covetuouſnes of <hi>Guſtavus</hi> the firſt, deſpoiled them of their Revenues. Yet ſince the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation they ſtill to this day retain their ſuffrages in all publick Dyets of the Kingdome.
<note place="margin">Burei Deſcrip. Suec.</note> And when the new Crowned King makes choice of his Counſellours the Arch-Biſhop of
<hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pſal</hi> is ſtill the firſt; who is allowed a greater proportion of Attendants, when he comes to the King, then any Noble-man in the Nation, no leſſe then 40. Horſe being permitted him, whereas others Reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue muſt not exceed 30. And in the great Aſſembly, A. 1600 convened at
<hi>Lincopen,</hi> we find mentioned both Biſhops and other Eccleſiaſticks. For <hi>Denmark, Pontanus</hi> recites 7 Biſhops, as the Eccleſiaſticall Nobility, who have Votes in all grand meetings. <hi>Jonas ab Elvervelt</hi> diſtributes the ſtates of <hi>Holſtein</hi> into Three Orders, 1 King, and Princes, 2 Prelates, 3 the Families of the Nobles, and he makes the Biſhops of <hi>Lubec,</hi> and <hi>Sleſwick,</hi> the 2 <hi>prime Peeres</hi> in all the Dyets.
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>MS in Arch. Bodl. entit.</hi> the man, of
<hi>hald. Par. Scot.</hi>
                  </note> In Scotland anciently the Biſhops and Prelates were eſſential members of Parliament, and had their Seates on the Right Hand of the Prince. And in a Parliament held at <hi>Edinburg</hi> A.
1597, a Vote paſſed for reſtoring the Clergy to their Original Priviledges, as the 3 Eſtate of the Kingdom, the Learned King <hi>James</hi> condemning that Act of Annexing their Temporalties to the Crown, as
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Baſil. Dor.</hi> l. 2. p.
43.</note> vile and pernicious. Then for <hi>Geneva,</hi> who is ſo much a ſtranger to the conduct of that Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as to be ignorant, what a ſtroke <hi>Calvin</hi> and others had upon the Senate or grand Counſel, which gave occaſion to the complaint of ſome, that they had expelled
<hi>one Biſhop,</hi> and <hi>admitted many.</hi> If remoter Countries be regarded amongſt the Abiſſines, the Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy is Paramount,
<note n="*" place="margin">Dreſſer. Orat.</note> imployed in affaires of all natures, and we read in <hi>Damianus a Gôes</hi> of
<hi>Zaga-Zaba</hi> an Ethiopian Biſhop Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roy of <hi>Bagana,</hi> ſent Embaſſadour to the King of <hi>Portugal.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In <hi>Muſcovy</hi> their Supreame Convention, which the Inhabitants call <hi>Zabore,</hi> conſiſts of the great Duke, 20 Nobles, and as many Eccleſiaſticks, the common People being wholy excluded.
<note place="margin">Gaguin</note> And when they are met together to deliberate, the Patriarch, and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticks are firſt conſulted, and deliver their Opinion.</p>
               <p>I ſhall conclude this Paragraph, only reminding that neither
<hi>Pagans,</hi> nor <hi>Mahomatans</hi> are ſo inhuman, ſo diſcourteous towards
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:40451:36"/>their Prieſts, as to deny them this Liberty. For <hi>Tully</hi> acquaints us, that it was by the appointment of the gods,
<note place="margin">Orat. pro Dom. ſuâ.</note> that the
<hi>Pontiſices</hi> ſhould not only take care of Religion, but <hi>ſummae Reip. praeeſſe Voluerunt.</hi> Nay at this very day the Barbarous Turks never ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude their Mufti, but allow him free entrance into all their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cills, and Divan.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>The Clergies Antient Priviledges in this Kingdom, and their Reſtitution preſſed by many Arguments.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>TIs Recorded to the Glory of <hi>England,</hi> that her Bounty and Liberality to the Church in Stately Fabricks, and Revenues, her Favour and Indulgence in large Priviledges, and Immunities have come ſhort of no Nation in the World. I might produce many inſtances to that purpoſe; but for the preſent ſhall ſingle out one, as more <hi>eminent and glorious</hi> then the reſt, viz. <hi>Admitting them to all publick Debates, and Aſſemblies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I'le begin with the <hi>Saxons</hi> who had many ſolemn meetings, 1. their <hi>Scire-Gemots,</hi> which ſome learned Antiquaries reſemble to our <hi>County-Courts,</hi> or <hi>Sheriffs-Torn,</hi> in which all Cauſes, both Criminal and Civil concerning Church, or State were handled. The Perſons bound to be preſent, were the Sheriff, the Biſhop, and all the Nobles of the County: till at laſt upon their Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Petition Eccleſiaſticks were diſpenſed with by the Statute of Marlborough 52.
<hi>Edw.</hi> 3. unleſſe urgent neceſſity requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it.</p>
               <p>Secondly, Their <hi>Folc-mots,</hi> a kind of Annual Parliament, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly held the beginning of <hi>May,</hi> in which all the Princes of the Kingdom, Biſhops, and Magiſtrates aſſembled, and the Laity took the Oath of Allegiance, and confirmed their own mutual U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion before the Biſhops. The Original of this is intimated to be as high as King
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>L.L. Edv. Conf. c.</hi> 35.</note>
                  <hi>Arthur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly. Their <hi>Wittena-Gemots,</hi> or Mycel-Synoth, the Grand Convention of the Wiſemen. Theſe whoſoever deſires to look
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:40451:36"/>farther into, may have recourſe to
<hi>Spelmans</hi> Laborious Gloſſary, <hi>V. Gemot.</hi> Now out of none of theſe were the Clergy excluded, but ever reckoned an eminent Principal part of each, their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, Votes, and Approbation demanded before any Laws were conſtituted.</p>
               <p>For proof of this we ſhall look back above 1000 years, to
<hi>Ethel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert,</hi> who preſently after <hi>Auſtins</hi> arrival, A. 605. calld a grand Aſſembly, <hi>tam
<note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Spelm. Con. p.</hi> 126.</note> Cleri, quam Populi..</hi> In the Laws of King <hi>Ina,</hi> which
<hi>Florentius Wigorn. dates</hi> A. 686. <hi>Spelman</hi> 692.
<hi>Lambard</hi> 712. we read that they were written by the perſwaſion and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of his Biſhops <hi>Hedda,</hi> and <hi>Erkenwald:</hi> and though
<hi>Spelman</hi> excerps no more then concern the Church (as being only proper to his deſign) yet <hi>Lambard</hi> mentions many <hi>Civil</hi> matters there de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined. And when the Great League and Union between the <hi>Britons, Saxons,</hi> and <hi>Picts</hi> was concluded we have it ratified <hi>per commune Conſilium, &amp; Aſſenſum</hi> Omnium Epiſcoporum,
<hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerum, Comitum, &amp; omnium Sapientum Seniorum &amp; Populorum,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Bed. Hiſt. l.</hi> 1.</note> &amp; per Praeceptum Regis Inae.</hi> In the Laws of K. <hi>Ethelſtan</hi> about the year 924. (<hi>Spelm.</hi> 922.) theres no mention of any other Counſellours for their enacting, but his Arch-Biſhop. <hi>Ulfhelm,</hi> and the reſt of his Biſhops, who were at ſeaſt the Prime Perſons there, though the Body of the Laws concerns
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Lamb.</hi> p. 45.</note> ſecular affairs, <hi>Spelman</hi> ſelecting only Eccleſiaſtical, yet in the Title he owns others paſſed. In the Laws of <hi>Edmund</hi> about A. 946. the King had a full meeting of Eccleſiaſticks, and <hi>Laicks</hi> at
<hi>London,</hi> in which were preſent <hi>Odo</hi> and <hi>Wulſtan</hi> the Arch-Biſhops,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Id. p.</hi> 57.</note> none of the reſt being once named. Again A. 948. to a great Convention of the Eſtates at
<hi>London</hi> under <hi>Edred</hi> Writs of Summons are iſſued out to the Arch-Biſhops and Biſhops, and yet there <hi>agitur de Negotiis Regni,</hi> civil matters are treated of. <hi>Ingulph. p.</hi> 87 S. <hi>Spel. Con. p.</hi>
428.</p>
               <p>Come to the <hi>Danes,</hi> A. 1021. we find a Publick Aſſembly called at <hi>Wincheſter</hi> by <hi>Canutus,</hi> which an Old MS. ſtiles a Parl. wherein were preſent <hi>Wulſtane,</hi> and
<hi>Adelnode</hi> the Arch-Biſhops, with other Biſhops, Dukes and Earls: and though there may be a miſtake in tearming it a Parl. the name being not known in that Age,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Spel. Conc. p.</hi> 534.</note> yet the ſubſtance may be true as to the Members of the Convention. And that none of theſe were <hi>Hali-Gemots</hi> or <hi>Chirc-Gemots,</hi>
                  <pb n="64" facs="tcp:40451:37"/>(which the Moderns tearm
<hi>Convocations</hi>) will appear, becauſe the uſual Title of them is
<hi>Magna Servorum Dei Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quentia.</hi> LL. Inae A. 727. &amp; alibi paſſim.</p>
               <p>Now during theſe 2. Periods there's no mention of
<hi>Baronies,</hi> but all the <hi>Church Tenure, Pura Elemoſyna, Frank Almoign,</hi> and the Biſhops ſate only as Eminent Prelates by virtue of their Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual Dignities. For there being hardly any Laws but ſome way or other concerning Religion, and the good of Souls, therefore in the enacting of them the Counſel, and advice of the Clergy was ever required by our prudent Anceſtors.</p>
               <p>Thus much for the Grand Aſſemblies, ſtyled uſually by
<hi>Spel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Pan-Anglica,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">LL. <hi>Edg.</hi>
                  </note> and
<hi>Pan-Britannica;</hi> the more private this Statute of <hi>Edgar</hi> will put beyond all diſpute, injoyning, <hi>ex omni Comitatu his quotannis Conventus agitor, cui quidem illius Diaeceſis</hi> Epiſcopus, <hi>&amp; Senator interſunto, quorum alter Jura Divina, Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mana alter Populum edoceto.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Titl. of Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour.</hi> p. 2. c. 5. S. 5.</note> Nor can
<hi>Selden,</hi> who ever ſits upon the Clergies skirts, if he gets the leaſt advantage, deny that the Biſhop was joyned with the Ealderman. This was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards confirmed by <hi>Canutus</hi> the <hi>Dane. Spelm. Gloſ. v. Alderm.</hi> Much more might have been ſaid of this, but that I am prevented by a learned pen, whoſe Piece I had not the fortune to ſee till my Collections were finiſhed, and finding we jumpt in many things, am now forced to wave them.</p>
               <p>Hitherto the Saxon and Daniſh Government: paſſe we down to the Normans, and here we have <hi>Will.</hi> ſolemnly with an oath ratifying the Laws of S. <hi>Edward,</hi> and this of <hi>Remark</hi> is added,
<hi>Siquis ſanctae pacem Eccleſiae violenter infregerit, Epiſcoporum eſt ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitia Lam. p.</hi> 139. <hi>parag.</hi> 6. And in ſundry old Royal Precedents of writs, we read ſuch clauſes as theſe, <hi>Nolumus quod libertas Eccleſiae per nos, vel miniſtros noſtros quoſcun<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> aliqualiter violetur; &amp; Jura, &amp; libertates Eccleſiaſticas illaeſa volentes in omnibus obſervari. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtr. in Brev. Orig. paſſim.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And here we come to that great Change in the State Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, the Biſh. who had been ever reputed, and enjoyed the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges of <hi>Thani majores</hi> among the Saxons, are now tranſlated to Barons, which gave occaſion to that groundleſſe error of ſome <hi>to Date their firſt Sitting in Parl. hence,</hi> as if the Conquerour to curry favour with the Clergy, the better to ſettle his new gotten
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:40451:37"/>Kingdom, conferred this honour upon them. But certainly if there were truth in this, the Clergy are much too blame and very ungrateful, who returned nothing but complaints and murmurings for ſo great a Favour: and all the Writers of that age muſt be corrected, for repreſenting him as a profeſt Enemy of the Church. To clear up this, I ſhall give but one inſtance. In an old Record, entituled, <hi>Liber St. Albani,</hi> we read this paſſage of <hi>Frederick</hi> the Abbot, that to obſtruct the March of <hi>Will.</hi> he felled all the trees about him, and laid them croſſe the waies; whereat the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour was ſo enraged, that after wards, ſending for him upon Security, he demanded of the Abbot the meaning of that cutting down the woods, who reſolutely anſwered, I have done but as becomes me; and if all the Spiritual Perſons throughout the Kingdom had done their endeavours againſt thee, as they might, and were in duty bound to have done, thou wouldſt never have been able to enter the Land thus far. The Duke replied, is the Spiritualty of England of ſuch power? <hi>If I live and enjoy that which I have gotten, I will make their Power leſſe.</hi> Add to this that Stratagem of the Kentiſhmen in ſurrounding the King, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing him to a compoſition under the conduct of <hi>Stigand</hi> the Arch-Biſh. which ſo netled him, that he never was <hi>heartily reconciled, and proved as good as his word to the Abbot,</hi> oppreſſing the Clergy all his raign, bringing them under Knights ſervice, and ordering how many Souldiers each Biſh. ſhould maintain for him, and his Succeſſours, the Church till his daies being free from Bondage. <hi>Let no man then dream that ſuch an enemy as</hi> Will. <hi>did as an Act of Grace, and Favour, erect them into Baronies, which was ever lookt upon as a grievance, and glorious Piece of ſlavery.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This was a ſhrewd ſhaking, yet ſtill they preſerved their Votes in all Aſſemblies, and upon ſummoning Parl. Writs are directed Archi-Ep. Ep. &amp;c. All ancient Charters and Grants ſubſcribed, (after the mode of thoſe times) <hi>teſtibus Archi-Ep. Ep.</hi> In a Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe entituled, The Form and Manner of keeping Parl. <hi>(Ms in Arch. Bodl:)</hi> which <hi>Selden</hi> allows to be as long ſtanding as
<hi>Edw.</hi> 3. but <hi>Cook</hi> adds neer 200 years more, and raiſes it to the Conquerours time, which the Title pleads for) we are told that 40 daies before Summons are to be iſſued out to the Arch-B. P. and other great Clerks, that held by County or Barony. Nay the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:40451:38"/>Clergy in each Shiere had two Proctors repreſenting them which had more authority then the Biſh. in things to be granted or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied in Parl. We are farther informed, that the King may hold a Parl. for the Commonalty of the Realm without Biſhops, Earls, or Barons, ſo they had Summons, although they come not. But on the contrary, if the Commonalty of the Clergy, and Tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralty being warned, either do not or will not come: in this caſe, what ever the King doth with his Liſhops, Earls and Barons, is of none effect. For to all Acts of neceſſity the Commonalty of Parl. muſt conſent, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Proctors of the Clergy, Knights of the Shiere, Citizens and Burgeſſes, for their Perſons repreſent the Commonalty of <hi>England,</hi> and the States do repreſent but their <hi>own perſons.</hi> Id. I have ſeen another ancient Mſſ. (in Bibl. Cotto.) confirming the ſame, with this title, <hi>Modus tenendi Parl.</hi>) and citing other large Priviledges of the Clergy.</p>
               <p>But why ſtand I upon this, when Mr. <hi>Prin</hi> himſelf, whoſe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony I the rather mention, he being known a profeſt enemy (though as he has lived to retract his Anti-Monarchical, ſo tis hoped he may his Ante-Epiſcopal Principles) in his Hiſtorical Collections of the Ancient Parl. of <hi>England,</hi> acknowledgeth, that during all the <hi>Saxon</hi> times from about A. 670, till King <hi>John.</hi> About 1200. the great Council of the Nation, or Parl. conſiſted only of the King, Princes, Biſhops, Dukes, and Nobles, no lower Houſe being then known, which our beſt Antiquaries conceive took its original about the time of <hi>Hen.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>I ſhall put a Period to this, with the Teſtimony of our Engliſh Papinian, my Lord <hi>Cook,</hi> who aſſures us, <hi>that</hi> 24
<hi>Spiritual Perſons ought</hi> ex debito Juſtitiae, to have a Writ of Summons ſent them every Parliament.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>This Premiſed; I ſhal now ſpeak a bold word, if the
<hi>proudeſt</hi> Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary can produce inſtances of any Solemn Meetings, <hi>Wittina-Gemots,</hi> or Parliaments for 1000 years paſt, whereunto the Clergy were not ſummoned, any Statutes publickly enacted du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:40451:38"/>all the Chriſtian Saxon, Daniſh, and Norman times without their Aſſiſtance, or Advice, by my conſent the Cauſe ſhall be given up. As for the Precedent of their Excluſion under
<hi>Edw.</hi> 1. at S. <hi>Edmundsbury,</hi> which ſome triumph in, if there be any truth in the Natrative (as may well be queſtioned) we know twas done in a <hi>Pet,</hi> a <hi>tranſport</hi> of the <hi>Royal</hi> Diſpleaſure for their obſtinat adhering to <hi>Rome,</hi> and non compliance with his Demands, who yet the next Parl. about a year after makes an Apology for his extravagancies (doubtleſſe with an eye to that Act) charging all up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the preſent exigences of his Affairs.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Walſingh. Vit. Ed.</hi> 1.</note> And why ſhould this be urged more againſt the Clergy, then that other is againſt the Lawyers, who were ſhut out of the Laymens Parl. under
<hi>Hen.</hi> 4. where yet we find the Biſhops, and among others <hi>Tho. Arundel,</hi> ſtoutly reſiſting, and preſerving the Clergies Temporalties, <hi>which thoſe Church-Robbers gaped after; who, ſo they might ſpare their own Purſes,</hi> were content to <hi>ſpoile their God to relieue their King. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, if envy it ſelf could have found out the leaſt colour of Law to deny them this Priviledge, it had never been reſerved for our unhappy Age.</hi> Many times have they been ſtruck at, many great blows received, as at <hi>Clarendon</hi> under <hi>Hen.</hi> 2. where their wings were much clipt, yet ſtill they are permitted,
<hi>Intereſſe Judiciis Cuxiae Regis cum Baronibus quouſque perveniatur ad Diminutionem mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brorum, vel mortem;</hi> ſtill their Votes are ſafe.</p>
                  <p>Do but look into Magna Charta, which all our Kings at their Coronation are ſworn to maintain, we ſhall find in favour of the Clergy,
<hi>We have granted to God, and by this our preſent Charter con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed for us and our Heirs for ever, that the Church of</hi> England <hi>ſhall be Free, and have all her whole Rights, and Liberties Inviolable.</hi> All the Nation being content to ſtand <hi>accurſed</hi> if <hi>this Grant</hi> were at any time infringed or diminiſhed, and any thing that ſhould be done contrary to this was <hi>ipſo facto</hi> declared void. 26 <hi>Edw.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi>
2.</p>
                  <p>Now it becomes us to examine, what thoſe Rights were the Church enjoyed at the ratifyng that Charter and through all ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Ages hath practiſed, until our late Unnatural Diviſions, and let us not <hi>put our Princes upon a neceſſity of Perjury,</hi> which, (ſome are of Opinion) can hardly be avoided, unleſſe either that <hi>Oath</hi> be wholly omitted, which few true Engliſh Hearts wiſh for,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:40451:39"/>or ſome Alteration made, which, of how Deſtructive conſequence it may prove in time, let others judge. What is the
<hi>Clergies hard Fate to day, may be others to morrow.</hi> And we had a late ſad ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, the doore being once open, how farre the Houſe of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons went in turning the Temporall Lords after them. I am not ignorant, that many foule big crimes were objected to them, that it might paſſe the curranter, but the plain Truth is, their <hi>Grand</hi> (I had almoſt ſaid) their only Fault was <hi>Loyalty</hi> to their Prince. The <hi>Sons of Faction</hi> ſaw there was <hi>no comming at the Scepter,</hi> till they had removed the
<hi>Croſier,</hi> ſo that through the ſides of <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> no leſſe then Monarchy was ſtruck at. But the better to diſguiſe the buſines, ſome <hi>Criticiſmes of Law</hi> were laid to their charge, and upon this nicety muſt the firſt, and one of the main Branches of <hi>Magna Charta</hi> be broken, which our Anceſtours ſo Beligiouſly kept, ſo often afferted with their deareſt blood: Little imagining that ever Proſterity for ſo ſlight a matter would have made ſo wide a breach in it, after above 30 <hi>ſolemne Confirmations</hi> in ſucceſſive Parliaments. For this muſt the poor Clergy looſe their <hi>Birthright,</hi> &amp; be <hi>eternally diſabled from Vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting within thoſe Walls,</hi> for which they can plead above 1000. yeares <hi>Preſcription;</hi> their Title being never once queſtioned, till the inconſiderate Zeal of ſome Male-Contents about 19 years ſince in <hi>May</hi> 1641. unhappily moved that
<hi>black Bill:</hi> whereunto through the neceſſity of the times, full of Tumults, and uproares, the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ali <hi>Aſſent,</hi> to purchaſe Safety, with an <hi>unwilling willingneſs</hi> was yeilded, I cannot ſay
<hi>given,</hi> to ſo great a diſtreſſe was Majeſty then reduced. I paſſe by thoſe un-Parliamentary irregularities, which ſome take notice of, the Repulſes it mett with, but being to ſerve the preſent Intereſt, by ſubtle contrivances at laſt twas carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And from this Critical Epoch may we date the riſe of our late Embroilements, and wild Confuſions, under which miſerable <hi>England</hi> has ſo long grooned, and the whole world ſtood amazed at. All the wealth which the Piety of our Fore-Fathers had been ſo many age<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> in heaping up, all the Priviledges which their Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence had ſo deliberately con ferred, being in a few dayes Paſſion ſwallowed up. Well, admit the preſent Biſhops, did <hi>unadviſedly</hi> runne into a <hi>Praemunire,</hi> could no Perſonall Fine, or Puniſhment expiate their <hi>Delinquency?</hi> Muſt their <hi>Innocent Succeſſours</hi> ſtill
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:40451:39"/>ſmart for it? Muſt ſo many
<hi>merits</hi> of their worthy <hi>Predeceſſours</hi> be buried in the Grave of ungratefull Oblivion? It were an eaſie mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to produce a large Catalogue of <hi>Eminent Prelates,</hi> who by their <hi>prudent Advice</hi> have oftentimes prevented Bloodſhed, preſerved Peace, ſaved a
<hi>ſinking Kingdome,</hi> and a dying <hi>Religion.</hi> Many good works have they done amongſt us, many Colledges, &amp; Schools erec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, and endowed, many material Churches by their munificence, and <hi>living Temples</hi> of the Holy Ghoſt built by their miniſtry, and for which of theſe muſt they now be thus hardly dealt withall? Thus disfranchis'd? That they who heretofore carried the princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall ſtroke in Cabinet Councils, and publick Dyets, are acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged in a Recorded Statute, an
<note n="*" place="margin">8 <hi>Q. Elizab. c.</hi> 1. <hi>Cooks. Inſt. p.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 74.</note> 
                     <hi>High</hi> and one of the
<hi>greateſt Eſtates</hi> of the Kingdome, muſt now for ever be excluded the two great Aſſemblies of the Nation, as not concern'd in the civil Peace, and be denied Repreſentatives to enact thoſe Lawes, to which they profeſſe, and yeild moſt cordial Subjection, a Priviledge granted to the
<hi>meaneſt Mechanick in a Corporation,</hi> the <hi>arranteſt Bumpkin</hi> in a County, that can but <hi>zweare has Vorty Zhillings</hi> a year: Every other Profeſſion being admitted, only Religion and Learning voted out of doores. But if this holds, what a fair ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage will the <hi>Romaniſts</hi> have to upbraid us, with a Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Religion, when the profound Myſteries of the Trinity, the knotty Controverſies of Predeſtination, Free-will, Perſeverance <hi>&amp;c.</hi> muſt be ſtated by thoſe, ſome of whom many times poſſibly may be better acquainted with the nature of a <hi>Hawke, or Hound, Buying, or Selling Commodities,</hi> then ſuch ſublime Speculations. (Pardon the Expreſſion, which the Iniquity of former times drew from me, and is not intended to reflect upon any worthy Patriots, whereof this Nation can boaſt as large a number as any of its neighbours) I ſay, let it be ſeriouſly conſidered, how we ſhall an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere that <hi>Cavil,</hi> when the moſt competent Judges of ſuch mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters are clean caſheered, no regard being had of their Ripe Abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, and exquiſite knowledge.</p>
                  <p>Not to mention the <hi>Popiſh Lords,</hi> who are grown ſo
<hi>numerous,</hi> all of a <hi>Judgment,</hi> and watchfull to lay hold on every opportunity to <hi>merit</hi> by promoting the <hi>Catholick</hi> Cauſe, and one Pocket may carry a great many Suffrages, whereby much danger may enſue, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les timely <hi>ballanced</hi> by the <hi>Lawn-Sleeves.</hi> The crafty Ieſuite is
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:40451:40"/>not ignorant of this, who keepes a Jubile to ſee what a wound is given to the Reformation, how much <hi>ground he has got</hi> by deba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing our Engliſh Clergy, whom of all the world he formerly moſt dreaded, but if their <hi>Plumes be thus pul'd,</hi> their
<hi>Revenues</hi> impaired, their <hi>Priviledges abated,</hi> he then hopes to deal well enough with them. And we muſt look to ſee every ſtone moved,
<hi>Rome, Geneva &amp; Munſter joyning,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Cook.</hi> 4. <hi>Inſt.</hi>
                     </note> to compaſſe the continuance of this <hi>miſery.</hi> But let not them deſpaire who have <hi>Caeſar</hi> on their ſide. We know that by the Law of the land the <hi>King</hi> is <hi>Guardian</hi> to the <hi>poor Orphan Church</hi> which is everſaid to be <hi>infra aetatem,</hi> in its minority,
<hi>&amp; in Cuſtodiâ Domini Regis,</hi> and now is the time for Majeſtie to appeare both for the Churches Honor, and its own Security. For of late yeares there hath been an <hi>unhappy Notion</hi> ſtarted, and kept up by ſome (no well-wiſhers to the Scepter) that the Three I ſtates of this nation conſiſt of King, Lords, and Commons., which how farr it may countenance former <hi>Actings,</hi> and indanger future Diſturbances, I humbly ſubmit to the prudence of thoſe that are better able to determine. But the Conſequences of that opinion ſeeme directly to aime at the
<hi>Levelling</hi> of Soveraignty, and makeing it accountable to the other Two (in their eſteeme) Co-ordinate Eſtates. Now Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoring the
<hi>Spiritualty</hi> the only <hi>True Legal</hi> 3 <hi>Eſtate,</hi> is the hopeful'ſt <hi>expedient</hi> to remove that Deſtructive Principle out of the mindes of the fickle multitude. So may the <hi>Crown</hi> be ſafe, and the <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> no longer trampled upon. And certainly tis high time for men to relent of their mercileſs Cruelty towards learned Induſtry. The old Rule was <hi>Nulli ſua Pietas debet eſſe damnoſa:</hi> but now that Complaint is again fulfild in our eares, the Publiſhers of Salvation whoſe feete ought to be beautifull, are reputed as the Filth of the world, and the off-ſcouring of all things; ſo that in the bitternes of their ſoules they may well cry out, if their hopes were only in this Life they were of all men moſt miſerable. I take no pleaſure in upbraiding an ungratefull Nation: But is, this the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward of their unwearied Paines, inceſſant Studies, early Riſing, and late watching, beating their Brains, waſting their Bodies, and contracting incurable Diſeaſes? Is this the Thanks for their Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity to the poore, neglecting their Families, Relations, and Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaintance for the glory of God, and the good of their Country? muſt they onely have Diſcouragements heaped upon them, bread,
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:40451:40"/>water and Rags (if ſome had their will) thought too good for them, a ſmall Income, a common Priviledge grudged them after ſo many yeares <hi>Labour, Sweat, and Coſt. Is this for the Honour of our Reformation, and becoming the Goſpel?</hi> Doubtles the prophane world will be apt to conclude that Chriſt is a hard maſter, that ſuffers his Servants thus to be trampled upon, and few will beleeve that Godlines hath the promiſes of this life, or that Wiſdome hath kept its word, Riches and Honour are with me <hi>Prov.</hi> 8. when other Callings run away with all the Rewards, and the greateſt Deſervings, the higheſt Ingenuity, the moſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary Holines in This, meet with nothing but Frowns, Contempr, and Debaſings.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="clergy's jurisdiction" type="apology">
            <head>THE CLERGIES JVRISDICTION.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The Nature of Jurisdiction explained, and the Regal Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy aſſerted.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>E come in the laſt place to <hi>Juris diction,</hi> which may be defined a coercive Authority in exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall judicature relating to the execution of Lawes. This we grant primarily to reſide in the <hi>civil Magiſtrate,</hi> to whom the Sword is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, the eſtabliſhing of Lawes belongs, and whoſe right it is to appoint Judges in all cauſes, Here then is the
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:40451:41"/>Fountain of all Jurisdiction, which branches it ſelf into <hi>two ſtreames, Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Temporal.</hi> And that originally it proceeds hence is manifeſt, becauſe Appeales <hi>are ultimately made hither.</hi> Thus we find S. <hi>Paul</hi> Act. 25. appealing from the high-Preiſt, to <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſar,</hi> as from an Inferiour Judge, to the Soveraign; the laſt <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pellation ever denoting ſupreame Jurisdiction.</hi> Thus amongſt us, if a man takes himſelf to be wrong'd in one of our Country Courts, he may remove the <hi>Action to Weſtminſter Hall,</hi> and if Juſtice be denied there, in caſes of grand import, the laſt <hi>reſerve is the Parliament;</hi> as the <hi>Higheſt Court of Judicature in the Nation.</hi> The Church of <hi>Rome</hi> was not ignorant of this, who ſtrugled more in matters of Appeal, then any other, as being the faireſt flower in her Garden, and this once cropt, you ſee how ſoon her power withered. This might farther be proved from the example of
<hi>Joſhuah,</hi> comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the People to be circumciſed, from
<hi>Jehoſhaphats</hi> appointing the Prieſts to judge between blood and blood, from whence the <hi>Royal Supremacy</hi> &amp; <hi>Jurisdiction</hi> in their reſpective Dominions doe invincibly follow. Nor did the Ancients ever queſtion it. For <hi>Aſer Menevenſis</hi> ſtyles King <hi>Alphred,
<note place="margin">Lamb. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaion.</note> Omnium Britanniae Jnſulae Chriſtianorum Rectorem,</hi> and the Confeſſour entitles himſelf <hi>Vica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium Summi Regis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We doe then in al humility, acknowledge the ſupreame Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Magiſtrate, not only in Civil (which the <hi>French Pragmatique Sanctions</hi> challenge) but in Church matters, and far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,
<note place="margin">Tertul. Apol.</note> that a Magiſtrate as ſuch, whether Chriſtian, or Pagan it matters not, ought in all things to be obeyed, that are not contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the word of God, and then paſſive Obedience becomes the Goſpel, Reſiſtance being in no caſe lawful. We doe look upon the King <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp; with <hi>Menander</hi>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. And I ever thought there was much of truth ſhadowed out in that Poeticall fiction, that Majeſty came down from Heaven, whence the ancients made it the Daughter of Honour and Reverence. Nor dare I condemne thoſe ſwelling Titles every where in the Civil Law given to, and own'd by Chriſtian Emperours, as <hi>Numen, Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culum, Sacratiſſimus Imperator,</hi> which ſome zealous eares amongſt us would account little leſſe then Blaſphemy. But any that have acquaintance with the Jewiſh cuſtomes, and Language will ſoon reſolve them, that twas an uſual thing with holy writers, to ſtyle
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:40451:41"/>every thing <hi>Divine</hi> that did excell and was eminent, <hi>v. Druſius</hi> in <hi>Gen. &amp; Briſſon. de Formul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And let not any one imagine that this is any derogation from the Honour of God, or the Pride of Princes hereby heightned, the deſigne only is to mind them, whoſe Perſon they repreſent, whoſe Servants they are, and that they ought to imitate his Juſtice Mercy, and Bounty. Old <hi>Homer</hi> cals Kings <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, nouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the boſome of
<hi>Jupiter,</hi> and from this divine Originall, ſome derive their miraculous Vertues, which we ſee <hi>Hereditary</hi> to ſome <hi>Royal Families.</hi> Thus the <hi>Curing the Kings Evil</hi> with our Princes, and if we will beleive <hi>Car. Tapiam</hi> the Releiving perſons
<hi>Poſſeſt</hi> by the King of <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I have dwelt the longer upon this ſubject, that none may ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect what enſues to have the leaſt aſpect towards <hi>Rome:</hi> not on the other hand let any faſten ſuch <hi>odious Conſequences</hi> upon this Doctrine, as ſome malicious Jeſuites have done, as if we made our Princes Popes, and gave them an unlimited power of impoſing in matters of Religion at pleaſure. We never aſſert that our Kings have power to make
<hi>New Formes</hi> of worſhip, <hi>New Articles</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> but to take care that all things within their <hi>Dominions</hi> be ordered according to the revealed will of God. And as much,
<note place="margin">
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſſer Primord. Eccle. Brit.</note> as this comes to St. <hi>Auſtin, Eleutherius</hi> to <hi>Lucius (vicarius Dei eſtis in regno veſtro</hi>) and the Ancients have ever with one voice, attribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to Princes, and none queſtioned, but ſome late
<hi>Paraſites</hi> of the Roman Ante-Chriſt.</p>
               <p>This laid down weel fall roundly to work and that ſome ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction to curb prophane, and erroneous perſons, to keep the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy from Sacraments, and in caſe of obſtinacy to forbid the faithfull ſociety with them, that ſuch moderate Power not excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the bounds of
<hi>Exco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>munication</hi> dos by a <hi>divine right</hi> belong to Spiritual perſons both Chriſts commiſſion <hi>Mat.</hi> 18, and the Apoſtles practiſe 1 <hi>Cor:</hi> 5.4 ſufficiently warrant, and none ever queſtioned but an envious <hi>Selden,</hi> and ſome <hi>Phyſitians,</hi> who wanting other <hi>Practiſe</hi> made the Church their <hi>Patient?</hi> Set aſide theſe, and the former Poſition has hardly mette with any adverſary.</p>
               <p>All the difficulty is, how farre <hi>Civil Jurisdiction,</hi> by the favour of Princes permitted to them, may with a <hi>Salvo</hi> to the Sacred Function be exerciſed. For tis owned that <hi>Temporal</hi> power can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:40451:42"/>be challenged by <hi>Eccleſiaſticks</hi> as their due, but is a <hi>right Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perial,</hi> and <hi>Royal,</hi> yet Princes to whom it properly belongs both may, and have often delegated the exerciſe of it, even to their Clergy. Moſt of the Firſt Chriſtian Emperours having experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced the integrity and prudence of the
<hi>Eccleſiaſticks</hi> left it to the liberty of the Plaintif, that entered the Suite, either to make the <hi>Biſhops Judges,</hi> or to have recourſe to the Civil Magiſtrate, Thus <hi>Conſtantine, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>alons, Gratian, Valentinian, Theodoſius, Arcadius, Martian, Leo, Anthemius,</hi> and
<hi>Juſtinian:</hi> As may be ſeen in the Imperial Edicts yet extant.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>The Original of Eccleſiaſtical Courts.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF we ſhould trace up the Original of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Courts,</hi> we ſhall find them grounded upon the counſel of the Apoſtle,
1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6. where he adviſes the Chriſtians, when any contentious Suits ariſe amongſt them (as in all Societies ſuch muſt be look'd for) that they ſhould not to the diſhonour of Religion, betake themſelves to
<hi>Pagan Tribunals for Juſtice,</hi> but let <hi>their brethren decide matters.</hi> But who theſe were, is a great <hi>Quaere,</hi> the 4.
<hi>v.</hi> ſeemes to put it upon thoſe that were leaſt eſteemed, which can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the Preachers. But <hi>Theophylact</hi> carries the ſence thus, that tis an anſwere to a tacit objection, that ſome would be apt to ſay there is not a wiſe man in the Church, that can Judge. Well, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit according to that opinion, there be not one prudent perſon found, yet rather appoint thoſe that were never ſo contemptible, and little eſteemed in the Church your Judges, then go to the Heathen Tribunals. But <hi>Ambroſe</hi> on the place, is more expreſs, that Miniſters are appointed Judges. And if the Vote and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of Antiquity, which is commonly none of the worſt Expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tours may be taken, matters will be yet more clear; Many ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered paſſages there are in <hi>Igratius, Tertullian, Cyprian, &amp;c.</hi> look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this way, but being under the <hi>Laſh,</hi> they are fain to whiſper only, and durſt not ſpeak out.</p>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:40451:42"/>
               <p>I ſhall not much ſtand upon thoſe Canons, that paſs under the name of the Apoſtles, where we read that the Biſhops ought to meet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very 2 daye of the week, to judge cauſes, and a Tribunal is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to them, with power of deciding all controverſies. Nor yet upon that of <hi>Clemens</hi> Ep. <hi>ad Jacob. Fr. Dom.</hi> where tis expreſs, If any of the Brethren have differences among themſelves, let them not goe to the Heathens for Juſtice, but let the Presbyters of the Church decide it. Now both theſe, however cenſured by ſome as ſpurious in reſpect of the titles they bear, yet cannot be denied to be very ancient. And in the 2 Ep. of
<hi>Marcellinus, Quaecunque contentiones inter Chriſtianos ortae fuerint ad Eccleſiam deferantur, &amp; ab Eccleſiaſticis determinentur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We have indeed but few genuine peices remaining, of thoſe poor perſecuted times, wherein the diſtreſſed Believers were glad to make hard ſhifts, and fearfull to do any thing that might cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate jealouſie in the minds of thoſe cruel Tyrants, whereas openly to profeſſe the declining of their Tribunals, had been crime e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough. Yet St. <hi>Hierom</hi> (a curious ſearcher into old records) ſaith, Prieſts from the beginning were appointed Judges of cauſes <hi>l. de</hi> 7 <hi>Ordin. Eccleſ.</hi> And when they could uſe freedome, then we have them ſpeaking aloud. For St.
<hi>Ambroſe</hi> pleads the Apoſtolical Commiſſion <hi>Ep.</hi> 24.
<hi>ſecundum ſacrae formam praeceptonis, qua eum Apoſtolus induebat.</hi> S. <hi>Auſtin</hi> ſeconds him, and ſaith this task was impoſed upon Spiritual perſons by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> to decide <hi>tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>multuoſiſſimas perplexitates cauſarum alienarum de negotiis ſaecula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus, De Opere Monachatus. c.</hi> 29.</p>
               <p>I ſhall conclude this with a teſtimony of <hi>Calvin,</hi> whom all know to be no friend to the Epiſcopal Hierarchy, yet even he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledges 4 <hi>Inſtit. c.</hi> 11. §. 10. That the Primitive Chriſtians, to prevent wrangling ſuits were wont to commit their differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces to be decided by their Biſhops: and this held till the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate received the Goſpel.</p>
               <p>But that which carries the greateſt weight with me, is the Univerſal Practiſe immediatly after the Scepters of the earth ſtooped to Chriſt: for I cannot imagine that ſo great a novelty would have been imbraced without any contradiction, and not have been reproved by ſo many Eminent Worthies juſt eſcaped out of the flames of perſecution, the School of Holineſſe. Tis
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:40451:43"/>more than probable then that by virtue of the Apoſtolical precept, of ending ſuits among themſelves to prevent ſcandal (it being the main imployment of the Miniſtery to make peace between thoſe that are at variance) in the Primitive times the whole management of differences was entruſted to the Clergy, as being perſons of the greateſt ſincerity and ability. Now <hi>Conſtantine</hi> at his entrance upon the Government, finding it ſo, wiſely con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered how much the Authority, and Reverence of Religion did conduce to the expediting of Cauſes, and diſcovery of captious actions. For this was not done unadviſedly, ſundry weighty rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons being ſubjoyned, as will appear, if the Laws be peruſed. As firſt, becauſe twas hoped it would tend much to allay the heat of wrangling, choak the malicious ſeeds of contentions, 2ly Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the Judgments of Biſhops were lookt upon as true, uncor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, and piercing, whereby the Sophiſtry, tricks, and ſhifts of the Law might be prevented, and poor men, entangled in the tedious laſting ſnares of vexatious actions, might have a ſpeedy iſſue put to their affairs. Now the good Emperour conceived they might well be intruſted with his own moſt important Nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiations, and his Subjects eſtates, to whom God had committed the care of their precious Souls: therefore upon theſe prudential conſiderations, being ſatisfied in the uſefulneſſe and integrity of Spiritual perſons, he made their Juriſdiction Authentick, giving it the Royal ſtamp, allowing no appeal from the ſentence of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, but making it as concluſive as his own, leaving it free to any
<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>Zozom. L.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 9. <hi>Niceph. L.</hi>
7. <hi>c.</hi> 46. who adds that this priviledge laſted to his time under
<hi>Andronicus</hi> A. 1300. <hi>Valens</hi> and <hi>Valentiman,</hi> A. 365. enlarged it, and entruſted them with the rate of Commodities ſold in the
<note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>Cod. Leg.</hi> 1. <hi>de Ep. Aud. Tit.</hi> 7.</note> Markets. But their Juriſdiction has been in ſeveral Ages very various, ſometimes en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, ſometimes clipt, as the Emperours were more or leſſe favourable to the Church, who ever kept the Soveraignty in their own hands. <hi>Conſtantine</hi> was then the firſt that paſſed the <hi>Royall Grant</hi> in favour of the Clergy, permitting the cognizance of all civil matters even between Laymen to the Epiſcopal Tribunal, if either Party did require it, though the other denied his conſent, and their appeal was to be obeyed by all the Magiſtrates, whenever
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:40451:43"/>made, though the action was already commenced in another Court.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Arcadius</hi> and <hi>Honorius</hi> did a little retrench this unlimited power, yet ſtill allowing it, by the joynt conſent of both parties, and making the Biſhops, as twere, <hi>Referees. L. ſiquis ex conſenſu. c. de Audientiâ Epiſcopal.</hi> and their deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to be binding and final without any appeal. This was af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards ratified by
<hi>Theodoſius</hi> and <hi>Juſtinian l. Epiſc. c. eodem.</hi> Nay
<hi>Juſtinian</hi> repoſed ſo much confidence in them, that he made them
<hi>Overſeers</hi> of the Secular Judges, <hi>Novel. Conſt.</hi> 56. This then has been the avowed Catholick Practiſe of all ages, and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions where the Goſpel has gaind footing. For the greateſt enemies the Church had, could never yet deny, but that the Biſhops have had their Tribunals for above theſe 1300 years erected by <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> confirmed by
<hi>Arcadius</hi> and <hi>Honorius, Theodoſius,</hi> and
<hi>Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lentinian</hi> 3, Only ſome curiouſly mince the matter, and allow them power to hear Cauſes, and to become Referees, and Um<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires, by conſent of both Parties; but yet they will not hear talk of any coercive Juriſdiction, though many Eminent Civilians attribute it to them: and
<hi>Accurſius</hi> interprets <hi>Audientia Epiſcopalis,</hi> a tearm frequent in the <hi>Code</hi> by <hi>Juriſdictio.</hi> Nay tis evident, there was no Caſe whatſoever, except only Capital (for <hi>Eccleſia ſanguinis Iudicium non profert</hi>) but might be decided by the Epiſcopal Tribunal: and <hi>Conſtantine</hi> forbad the Greateſt Prince in the Empire to revoke what once the Biſhops had decreed, <hi>Euſeb. Vit. Conſt. L.</hi> 4.
<hi>c.</hi> 27. In proceſſe of time the Magiſtrate having encroached upon, and almoſt outed the Clergy, <hi>Charles</hi> the Great revives that good old Law of <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> confirming the ſame Juriſdiction to all Biſhops, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peating the Charter word for word <hi>Car. Mag. in Capit. l.
6. c.</hi> 28. And here methinks this very name, fills me with hopes, that
<hi>Charles</hi>'s are <hi>born for the good of the poor oppreſſed Church:</hi> and that God hath miraculouſly raiſed up to us, as true a Nurſing Father, as ever bare that name, or our Iſland produced. And truly, who can expect leſſe from the <hi>Son of ſuch a Father,</hi> who dyed the
<hi>Church</hi>'s, Nay the <hi>Clergies Martyr:</hi> for if he could have diſpenſed with his <hi>Conſcience,</hi> and <hi>Coronation Oath,</hi> to ſacrifice them, and their Revenues to the coveruous fury of a prevailing Adverſary, <hi>the</hi> 30. <hi>of Jan.</hi>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:40451:44"/>need not have been noted with ſuch
<hi>Black Letters in our Brittiſh Almanacks.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. III. <hi>The Ancient <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion of Spiritual and Civil Courts in this Iſland. Corruptions no ſufficient Argument for their utter Subverſion. Replies to ſundry Objections from the example of Chriſt, the Apoſtles, and Primitive Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stians.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe exerciſe of Juriſdiction by the Clergy in this Nation, may be deduced out of the beſt Records extant, from the time the Goſpel was publickly owned among us. Theres nothing more frequent in our Engliſh Annals, then Eccleſiaſtical, Spiritual, and Chriſtian Courts. I ſhall not multiply proofs, but content my ſelf with two, the firſt out of
<hi>Brompton,</hi> where amongſt the old Laws of <hi>Ethelſtan</hi> we read,
<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Chron. Joh. Brompton. c.</hi> 24</note>
                  <hi>Epiſcopo jure pertinet omnem rectitudinem promovere Dei viz. &amp; ſaeculi, &amp; debent Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pi cum ſeculi judicibus intereſſe judiciis.</hi> And the ordering of all meaſures and weights in each reſpective Dioceſs is there made of Epiſcopal Cognizance, the Standard being left in the Biſhops hands. The next is of <hi>Spelman. Comes praeſidebat foro Comitatus non ſolus ſed adjunctus Epiſcopo, ut Alter alteri auxilio eſſet, &amp; conſitio, praeſertim Epiſcopus Comiti, nam in hunc illi animadvertere ſaepe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuit &amp; errartem cohibere. Gloſſ. v. Comes.</hi> So much confidence did the Antients repoſe in the Clergy, that the guidance and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſight of moſt temporal affairs was entruſted to them, and a check upon the Laity. Thus lovingly with all ſweetneſſe, and Candot for 4. or 500. years, during all the Saxon times, and till that unhappy diviſion by the Conquerour, who defaced this beautiful, this regular compoſure, did Church and State Officers ſit toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, in the morning determining Eccleſiaſtical affairs, and in the afternoon Civil.
<hi>No jarrs, no claſhings</hi> of Juriſcictions were then heard of, <hi>no Prohibitions iſſuing out from one Court to obſtruct the
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:40451:44"/>courſe of Juſtice</hi> in another, thereby hampering the poor Client, that he knows not which way to turn himſelf. And I am perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded theres no better expedient to prevent laſting vexatious Suits, and to relieve the oppreſſed; Then again to reconcile theſe two Juriſdictions, that according to the Primitive uſage, as well Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual, as Temporal Judges may be appointed in all Courts, that
<hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> may not quarrel, but walk hand in hand. Though I know this deſign does not well reliſh with many of the <hi>Long Robe,</hi> and tis feared the attempting ſome ſuch thing purchaſed our late Arch-Biſhop no few enemies, and was one ſpecial cauſe of haſtning his ruine. Yet <hi>Selden</hi> (a Lawyer too) <hi>L.</hi> 2. <hi>de Synedriis,</hi> proves, that for the firſt 4000 years and better the civil and Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Courts continued united, and the firſt Diſtinction pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from Pope <hi>Nicholas, Grati. Diſtinc.</hi> 96. <hi>c. cum ad verum.</hi> So that the making Eccleſiaſtical Government independent, and ſeperate from the civil is but a late Popiſh, and Conſiſtorial Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
               <p>Tis true, it cannot be denied but there have been groſſe Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions in theſe Eccleſiaſtical Courts, many perſonal infirmities in the Judges, for who ever lookt upon them as other then fleſh and blood: Though none but Prophane <hi>Chams</hi> would lay open, and ſcoff at the nakedneſſe of their ſpiritual Fathers, and like flies ſtick only to gald backs, and ſore places, never taking notice of the many eminent deſerts, and ſervice both Church and State have received from men of that Coat. How different was the great <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantines</hi> Temper? who profeſt he would put off his Royal Robes to hide a failing in a Biſhop.
<hi>Theodoret. L.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 11. If ſome have miſcarried let them ſmart for it, and let not the Calling ſuffer. Would it be accounted a piece of Juſtice, if ſome <hi>Lawyers be corrupt,</hi> preſently to raile at, and overthrow the whole Profeſſion, as incorrigible, pull down their Courts, as not capable of Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation. <hi>But grant they have erred, let that calling which is innocent throw the firſt Stone.</hi> I muſt needs ſay better reaſons muſt be ſhown, then ever were yet produced, before I change my judgment, That there are none fitter to <hi>advance deſigns of Peace, and publick Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quillity, to adminiſter juſtice, and hear the cries of the oppreſſed, then theſe men of God. Facilius enim Dei timore ſententiam Legis veram promunt. Ambro.</hi> Certainly, if this had been ſo abominable,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:40451:45"/>ſo Anti-chriſtian I cannot perſwade my ſelf, that the Learning of <hi>Jewel,</hi> the Humility of <hi>Hooper,</hi> and the ſweet Innocency of <hi>Cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dale,</hi> would have uſed this Authority and Juriſdiction, which we never find they did in the leaſt Scruple.</p>
               <div type="section">
                  <p>But we muſt not expect to carry it thus, a litle Squadron of Difficulties is yet to be encountred. And firſt we are urged with Chriſts example in refuſing to decide a title of Inheritance between brethren
<hi>Luk.</hi> 12. But I ſee litle reaſon that this ſhould be binding to his miniſters. Tis true we finde him ever careful not to give of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, whereas if he had taken this Jurisdiction upon him, his vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gilant Adverſaries that ever waited for an advantage againſt him would ſoone have been upon his back, and charged him with Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. For what greater intrenchment upon the royal Prerogative, then in anothers Dominion without leave, or Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſion to hear and determine cauſes? Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon prudence therefore which our Redeemer (the wiſdome of the Father) ever followed, forbad him then to intermedle. But where do we finde he tied his diſciples hands when times favoured them, and the Supream Powers thought good to imploy them. Indeed to remove all doubts and feares out of the minde of jealous Herod, he tels him, his Kingdom is not of this world, I come not to trouble or diſſolve eſtabliſht authorities, your State may be ſecure, and my Goſpel Preached, none that belong to me will raiſe commotions, or take upon them to rebel againſt their lawful Prince, my ſervants ſhall not fight for me, nor by tumults, and wars ſet up my Kingdom. And all the Apologies of the Ancients manifeſt how the Chriſtians ever prayed for, and ſubmitted to the Emperours. Let no man then think this Poſition ſtrang, that Church-Government ſhould bear ſome Correſpondence and Analogy with the State. For can it rationally be conceived, that Chriſt who was ſo carefull to enjoyn his followers, to give to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> the things that were his, would have his Goſpel bring in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novations and changes in well eſtabliſhed governments, confuſions upon lawfull Authority, eſpecially when the Model of civil affaires does not contradict, but may conſiſt with Religion. And I am
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:40451:45"/>here confirmed by the practiſe of
<hi>Moſes,</hi> who did not croſſe the Jewiſh Policy, but ſitted the Sacred Government to the Secular. And what ſad Conſequences have enſued the contraryopinion, the late madneſſe of <hi>our Fifth-Monarchy-men</hi> have abundantly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated.</p>
                  <p>Nor is all Juriſdiction forbidden in that 20. <hi>Mat.</hi>
25. The plain meaning of that text being no more then this; the Apoſtles quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relling about Precedency, Chriſt reproves them: tis clear, they dreamt as the Nation of the Jews, foold by their Rabbies, that the Meſſias ſhould have a glorious Temporal Principality, as was <hi>Solomons;</hi> and therefore contended who ſhould be the greateſt Favourites. Now Chriſt confutes that vulgar error, anſwers perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently to their thoughts, and tells them they muſt not expect to Lord it over their Brethren: that proud inſulting Tyranny, which others exerciſed, is not for them, their Government muſt be mild, humble, and conſiſt rather in obeying, then commanding. And to this purpoſe he propoſes himſelf for their pattern, who came to Miniſter unto them: yet I hope twill be granted, there was ſome difference between the Maſter, and the Servant, ſome Superiority of Chriſt over his Diſciples. Nor can that levelling Principle be deduced hence, for <hi>nihil magis inaequale, quam aequalitas.</hi> Tis farther obſervable, Chriſt inſtances in the Kings of the Gentiles, whoſe Empires were ſtained with cruelty and luxury, not the Jews, whoſe Government for the moſt part was more moderate, having ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Holy Laws to direct, ſo many Prophets to inſtruct them. But with the Gentiles twas otherwiſe: the Roman Oratour ſets out their manner. <hi>Regum ſunt haec imperia. Animadverte, &amp; dicto pare,
<note place="margin">Tully pro. Rabirio.</note> &amp; illae minae, ſi te ſecundo limine offendero, morier.</hi> This then ſeems the genuine ſenſe, the Kings of the earth Lord it thus proudly, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolently, unmercifully, you ſhall not do ſo, but command in love, in humility, in moderation, ſo that he does not ſtrike at the root of all Authority &amp; Juriſdiction amongſt his Diſciples, only ye ſhal not domineer as the Kings of the Gentiles, but in all lowlineſs rule as the ſon of man,
<hi>Dominatio interdicitu, indicitur miniſterium.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Bern.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>But the grand Objection that lies againſt it is, that we never find the Apoſtles to have taken this upon them, whoſe Practiſe ſhould be a Pattern to their Succeſſours, This argument I have often heard urged as the Great <hi>Achilles:</hi> but I wonder any ſober
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:40451:46"/>learned men ſhould lay ſtreſſe upon it. Methinks reaſon and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ſhould ſuggeſt a diſtinction of times, and inform them that many things may be judged unlawful in one age, which in another are found expedient, and neceſſary, and ſo on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. Whereas if the Apoſtolical practiſe were alwaies binding, how comes it to paſſe that many things approved by them as Community of goods, extream unction, abſtaining from blood, &amp;c. are now, in the revolution of time, diſuſed, and condemned. Nay, if there were any ſtrength in this arguing, the brainſick Anabaptiſt, and railing Quaker, would be furniſht with an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anſwerable Plea againſt our Churches; for who knows not what hard ſhift the poor Primitive Chriſtians were put to, how glad they were of private Houſes, Barns, yea Vaults, and Caves of the Earth to meet in, and ſecure themſelves from the rage of their watchful Perſecutours? Hence in ſome antient Monuments, Churches are called <hi>Cryptae,</hi> hiding places, becauſe through the violence and heat of perſecutions, the poor Chriſtians, were forced, with <hi>Nicodemus,</hi> to go to Chriſt by night: and we have frequent mention of their <hi>antelucanos hymnos</hi> in <hi>Pliny Ep.</hi> &amp;c.</p>
                  <p>But no ſooner did God reſtore a little breathing, and ſend peace, then they left their dens and holes, building and beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying Churches, and providing liberal maintenance for their Preachers. And now theres nothing more common in <hi>Nazianzen</hi> and the Greek Writers, then to ſtile them <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> from their Majeſty, being the Pallaces of the great King. For in <hi>Conſtantines</hi> daies, when the World newly divorced from idolatry, was ena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moured with true Religion, they thought they could never build their Churches-ſtarely and ſumptuous enough: but how ſtrangely now have they left their firſt love. If a man ſhould read of, or view the Ancient Piles, the Greek St. <hi>Sophia,</hi> our Engliſh St.
<hi>Pauls,</hi> the Roman St. <hi>Peters,</hi> &amp;c. The ſtupendious Church at <hi>Tyre,</hi> deſcribed by <hi>Euſebius,</hi> at <hi>Antioch</hi> by
<hi>Hierony. in Chron.</hi> at <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> by <hi>Cyril</hi> in his Catech. which the Piety and Devoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Fore-fathers erected, and compare them with our Modern whifling Structures, he would bluſh at the ſordid penuriouſneſſe of degenerating poſterity. I muſt needs ſay it has oftentimes moved both <hi>pity</hi> and <hi>anger</hi> in me, to ſee an Impropriating Patron flaunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it in a Royal Fabrick, when the Houſe of God adjoyning,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:40451:46"/>crouched under it in a tottering ragged condition—<hi>Exclamet Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licerta periſſe frontem de rebus—David</hi> was otherwiſe minded, 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 7.2. Nor would former ages have born it, who ſpared no coſt, no pains to build, no care to conſecrate theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> (as the Greek Authors tearm them) thoſe Sacred Structures. For this is no novel Invention, the practiſe we find as antient as <hi>Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gynus</hi> A. 140. whoſe Decree to that purpoſe is yet extant. <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eret. de Conſecrat. Diſt.</hi> 1. <hi>c. Omnes Baſilicae.</hi> And come but a little lower, when <hi>Conſtantine</hi> had erected that Magnificent Temple in Mount <hi>Calvary: Zozomen</hi> informs us
<hi>L.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 25. what an Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly of Reverend Prelates there met to Conſecrate it. Nor was any thing more uſual amongſt the Primitive Fathers.
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Athanaſ. Ep. ad Conſtant. Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bro.</hi> L. 1. <hi>Ep.</hi> 5. <hi>St. Auſt. Serm. de Temp.</hi> L.
56</note> Nay it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears by the Titles of ſeverall of St. <hi>Austins</hi> Sermons, that they had Solemn Anniverſary Commemorations upon the Conſecration day. But to return.</p>
                  <p>Tis confeſſed then, that in the Apoſtles daies, and the Ages immediatly ſucceeding, the poor Chriſtians were glad with any thing, and reckond the leaſt toleration a favour: but when the State of the Church was changed by thoſe great Revolutions in the Roman Empire, order and decency began to be lookt after. And is it not <hi>downright madneſſe</hi> in any to complain of their <hi>hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe,</hi> to deſire to return to that condition, which the Fury of Perſecutors enforced, as if they repined at the goodneſſe of a merciful God, who diſſolved that Cloud, and made the Sun of Proſperity to break out upon his weather-beaten Church, turning a dark morning into a glorious evening. Now if ſuch a wild rate of reaſoning be allowed, a man may as well conclude, that all the Succeeding Kings of
<hi>England</hi> are bound to lay aſide their <hi>State,</hi> and
<hi>Imperial</hi> Robes, becauſe time was, when his preſent Majeſtie, in his own Kingdom, to eſcape the malice of his implacable enemies, contented himſelf with a <hi>homely Cottage,
<note n="*" place="margin">(<hi>Nay a Loyal Oake.</hi>)</note> beſtrid</hi> a <hi>Millers Horſe,</hi> and had none but <hi>Dame Joane</hi> to wait upon him. I know the Courtiers would ſmile at ſuch Logick, though I muſt needs ſay tis little better, that our learned Sophiſters uſe againſt the Clergy.. For thus they reaſon, the Clergy enjoyed <hi>ſmall Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues, leſſe Honours, few Priviledges, no Juriſdiction</hi> under Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Pagans, <hi>therefore</hi> they are immodeſt to deſire it ſhould be otherwiſe under <hi>Believing Chriſtians.</hi> To ſpeak plainly then once
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:40451:47"/>for all, in <hi>point of Doctrine I reverence thoſe early times equal to any man, but in matters of Diſcipline, Order, and Decency, to draw Rules from a poor perſecuted Church, that was conſtrained to uſe what the neceſſity of the times would bear, not the Goſpel allow,</hi> and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fine <hi>poſterity, to their hardſhips, when the wiſe providence of God has changed the Series of Affairs, is juſt as if a man ſhould be enjoyned to wear the ſame Garments in fair weather, as he did in foul, and not to change the naſty attire he had on in a boiſterous Storm, though the clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt Calm ſucceeds it.</hi> The time then that we muſt <hi>principally eye,</hi> is that, when God gave Reſt &amp; Peace to his long afflicted Saints, when the Great Monarchs of the earth veiled their Crowns to the Croſſe; and if from thoſe daies their Civil Juriſdiction cannot be cleared, let an <hi>irrevocable Decree be paſſed againſt them.</hi> Not that I grant them wholly excluded in thoſe elder times, many footſteps of their private medling in ſecular matters being every where found, as has already been evidenced. But how could it rationally be expected, that any Precedents of ſuch Eminent Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, and Power conferred either upon the Apoſtles, or their immediate Succeſſours ſhould be produced; ſince the <hi>Jus Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num</hi> of Civil Juriſdiction belonging to the Clergy is utterly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed, and no title pleaded to it, but the Favour of the Supreme Magiſtrate: and who is ſuch a ſtranger in
<hi>Iſrael</hi> as to be ignorant, how little the Profeſſours of the Goſpel were then ſet by, when all the Great Potentates of the World ran madding after Idols, and twas no leſſe then death to own our Crucified Redeemer. So that if this be ſtrictly ſtood upon, we ſhall at laſt joyn iſſue with the Frantick <hi>Euthuſiaſts,</hi> who deny it lawful for a Chriſtian to be a Magiſtrate, there being no expreſſe command for it in the New Teſtament; nay many Texts ſeemingly againſt it, not any Example of the Apoſtles, hardly of the Profeſſours of the Goſpel, (known to be ſuch) in thoſe early times, that bare an Office. Well then, for the firſt
300 years the Church had no Kings for its nur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing Fathers, none that gave up their names to Chriſt in Soveraign authority, the wiſe God that diſpoſes of all times, and Eſtates, reſerving that mercy for theſe later daies, exerciſing them with great tryals, till the Earth was watered with the blood of Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs.</p>
                  <p>And hithero we have litttle or nothing of outward coercive
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:40451:47"/>diction, all was inward, all was Spiritual, and thus was the <hi>faith planted, the gates of Hell pul'd down,</hi> and the Pagan World redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to the obedience of <hi>Chriſt: Providence purpoſely ſo or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering it, that no fleſh might boaſt.</hi> Now all this while to ſay the truth, there was no need to have recourſe to outward Force, the Apoſtles, and their immmediate Succeſſours being furniſht with ſuch miraculous extraordinary power, which we ſee they did ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times exert to puniſh the diſobedient, as <hi>Anantas</hi> and <hi>Sap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phira</hi> with death, <hi>Elymas</hi> with blindneſſe, &amp;c. But miracles once ceaſing, and the immediate aſſiſtance of the Spirit being with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawn, to compenſate this loſſe, God turned the heart of the Magiſtrate: and Chriſtian prudence told them, that to place Covernours in the Church, and to deprive them, (thus deſerted by the Spirit) of all coercive Juriſdiction, was to <hi>expoſe their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, render their Perſons ridiculous, and their Commands inſignificant.</hi> And has not our late experience ſufficiently confirmed this, Sin being grown bold, and wickedneſſe never more improved; the Schiſmaticall prophane World making but ſport with the Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadours of Chriſt, whileſt left naked and deſtitute of all Civil Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction. Whereas in thoſe Apoſtolical primitive times, there was no fear, no danger of ſuch inconveniences, Love to Chriſt being then mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e ardent, and the cruelty of the mercileſſe adverſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry more outragious, the one <hi>ſweetly alluring the Profeſſours of the Goſpel, the other terrifying them into a dutiful Conformity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I am none of thoſe that delight <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to doat upon my own Notions, ſo that if any man will take the pains to produce clearer evidences, I ſhall readily be his Convert. Till then my judgement is, and I can ſafely ſay has been ever ſince I was able to look into Antiquity, that the Matter here contended for, is, neither under the cenſure of <hi>Inexpediency,</hi> nor <hi>Inconſiſtency,</hi> not the latter; For ſeeing tis a duty confeſſedly belonging to every Chriſtian to beat down ſin, and promote righteouſneſſe, and the end of all Juriſdiction, is to advance juſtice and reſtrain iniquity: I would gladly be reſolved what there is ſo hainous, ſo unſeemly for the Sacred Function in this Act, to
<hi>chaſtiſe the Diſturbers of the Chriſtian Peace</hi> with Spiritual: and if that prevail not with cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral Puniſhments. Certain it is, the Bleſſed Angels do not look upon it as diſhonourable to, or derogatory from their Holines, at the
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:40451:48"/>Command of God to correct the wicked even with death, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 23. and why ſhould it be thought ſo abominable, ſo unlawfull for the Angels of the Church. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. being Commiſſioned by Gods Vice-Gerent to inflict deſerved puniſhments on the work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of iniquity. <hi>Dav.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Not the former, if due Caution be uſed, that they keep within bounds, and that which was deſigned for their help, prove not their hindrance, too much taking themoff fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the weighty imployments of their Spiritual charge. And I think it may confidently be aver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, there are few of the preciſeſt, but ſpend more precious time in other petty impertinencies, which might be better placed in the publick ſervice of their Country. However, theres little fear of any exceſs in this jealous age, and under ſo Gratious, ſo Prudent a Prince, who has reaped this benefit by his long calamity, as to be the <hi>moſt Accompliſht for Government, of any Monarch in the World.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Tis an Obſervation of ſome, that God ſeldom imploys any in great Affairs, but he does exerciſe them with afflictions and tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulations:
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pez<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Com. in</hi> 29. <hi>Gen.</hi>
                     </note> and the large ſhare his Sacred Majeſty has had in theſe, encourages us to expect no ſmall things from him, eſpecially when we conſider in what an
<hi>unparaleld manner</hi> Providence reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him as a Peace-maker, not
<hi>to England</hi> onely, <hi>but to Europe,</hi> as a Nurſing Father to his Languiſhing Church, which many had in hope and thought clean devoured. Now Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction is the Royal Juriſdiction, a Principal, inſeperable part of <hi>his Royal Crown and Dignity.</hi> Its Original was from his Noble Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, who ever eſteemed it their Honour to ſupport, and encreaſe it. <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> a Britain, and the Glory of Britain, began it, and tis hoped, it ſhall never be ſaid that any of his Succeſſours conſented to its Funeral, when it was in their power to give it a Reſurrection. The ſubſtance of our Common Law is comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in theſe three things, <hi>jus Regium,</hi> now happily reſtored, <hi>jus Populi,</hi> confirmed, and <hi>jus Eccleſiae,</hi> which only has, and does ſtill ſuffer, by the late imbroylments. Nor can his Sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie ever hope to have his Deſire <hi>accompliſht, and the memory of former paſſages buried in oblivion, till the Church recover her antient Rights, and Priviledges as well as the State.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="epilogue">
            <pb n="95" facs="tcp:40451:48"/>
            <head>EPILOGVE.</head>
            <p>I Shall now end all with a breife Addreſs to the long-deſpiſed Clergy. The Goodneſſe of your God, and Favour of your Prince, have once more reſtored you to your Charges, your Patrimonies, and (tis hoped) will ere long to your Honours, and Priviledges, which Sacriledge, and Uſurpation for many years, have detained from you. Now it ſtands you upon ſeriouſly to conſider, what <hi>Deſign</hi> the Lord had in thus
<hi>humbling you:</hi> for certainly his <hi>wiſe Providence did not bring all this to paſſe for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi> Be intreated then in the bowels of our Common-Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, (though by one of the meaneſt in your number, yet a paſſionat-Well-wiſher of the Sacred Function) to hear the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Commands,</hi> the <hi>Royal Declarations,</hi> the <hi>Prayers, Groans, and Sighs of your Country,</hi> which all with one voice cry aloud to you for
<hi>Diligence in your Callings, and Uprightneſſe in your Converſations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe, theſe will make our <hi>Engliſh Zion</hi> proſper, and our <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> a Praiſe in the Earth. But if through
<hi>Plenty</hi> you forget him, whoſe <hi>Perſon you repreſent,</hi> and through <hi>Security</hi> turn again unto <hi>Folly,</hi> (give me leave to ſpeak my fears) my Heart trembles to think what the iſſue will prove, if the Indignation of the All<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty once more break out. Many eyes are faſtned upon you, ſo that the <hi>leaſt blemiſh</hi> will be eſpied. And as your <hi>Vertues</hi> bring greater Honour to the Goſpel then thoſe of private Perſons, ſo do your <hi>vices</hi> more <hi>Reproach. Chryſoſtom Hom.</hi> 27. in St. <hi>Mat.</hi> is my Authour, <hi>If a Preacher ſin with the People, he ſhall not be puniſhed in like manner as they, but far more grievouſly:</hi> and better would it be for any ſuch that a Milſtone were hang'd about his neck, and he caſt into the midſt of the Sea, then to prove a juſt occaſion of Scandal to any to ſpeak evill of the waies of God. It hath pleaſed the <hi>Great Diſpoſer of all things,</hi> once more to make trial of you. Let your Moderation be known unto all men, that none may complain
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:40451:49"/>of your Jurisdiction (if re-eſtabliſht) which the unqueſtionable Practiſe of all Ages, (except when wars, and perſecutions put every thing out of Frame) will abundantly juſtify. May your <hi>Goodneſſe</hi> equal your <hi>Greatneſſe, your Humility</hi> ſhine in the midſt of your <hi>Honours,</hi> the <hi>memory of your late Afflictions, and Vows made in your low eſtate never dye with you.</hi> Let your Converſation be with Covetuouſneſſe, that the hungry Bellies of the poor, and needy may find the Benefit of your <hi>happy</hi> Reſtauration, that no envious eye may repine, no foul mouth raile at your large Incomes, but all may confeſſe tis more for the Glory of God, and the good of the Nation, that your <hi>Charity be intruſted with thoſe Revenues,</hi> then the
<hi>griping Avarice</hi> of your Sacrilegious Adverſaries.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <opener>
               <salute>READER,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe importunat Haſt of the Stationer to diſpatch theſe Papers againſt the Seſſion of Parl. occaſioned many things to be hud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led up, which happily ſecond thoughts might either have enlarged, or altered, and ſundry Errata's have eſcaped the Preſſe, which yet a Charitable Eye may wink at, or a favourable Pen eaſily correct.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:40451:49"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
